<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></title><description><![CDATA[Phil's home on the internet]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com</link><image><url>https://philipliao.com/phil.jpg</url><title>Phil Liao</title><link>https://philipliao.com</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 15:21:36 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://philipliao.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[2020-11-15]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Self Expression, Typeracer, Miscellaneous]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-11-15</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-11-15</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-11-15">&lt;p&gt;Hey friends!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s been a long time (over a month) since I wrote some notes, and I think I&amp;#39;ve learned quite a bit since then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing that happened was that I spent 30 days, spanned across October and November doing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/writing-day-30-of-30&quot;&gt;30 day challenge&lt;/a&gt; to write every day. While my &amp;quot;weekly&amp;quot; (err... monthly?) notes are nice, they aren&amp;#39;t meant to have much of a shelf life - if at all. I love the conversational style of these notes, but they don&amp;#39;t age well on the internet. In contrast, articles stay relevant for far longer. Sigh, the medium is indeed the message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In those 30 days, the plethora of articles I produced allowed me express myself across multiple dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/notes-on-waitzkin-at-sohn&quot;&gt;As someone who enjoys learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/in-my-minor-feelings&quot;&gt;As an Asian American&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/simple-algorithms-and-exponents&quot;&gt;As a software engineer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/good-meeting&quot;&gt;As someone who likes business meetings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/legibility-and-software&quot;&gt;As a techie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/168-hours&quot;&gt;As a regular person just looking to live a more productive life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result? I feel more comfortable online. In the past, when I only had a few pieces of writing on the internet, it felt like each article had to represent me. Like the minority in a group discussion when the topic suddenly stumbles to race and all eyes turn to them to give a portrayal of &amp;quot;the Asian perspective&amp;quot; (as if there is a singular, united opinion), each article felt like it had to be a great &amp;quot;ambassador&amp;quot; to everyone who was stumbling on my website for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cringe when I see some of my old pieces in isolation (for example, some random thoughts on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/airpods&quot;&gt;Airpods&lt;/a&gt;), but combined with the 30 articles I wrote this month, they form a nest of ideas that authentically represent who I am. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, being a complex individual online is bad branding. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kentcdodds.com/about/&quot;&gt;Kent Dodds&lt;/a&gt; is primarily &amp;quot;The Mormon who teaches React Unit Testing&amp;quot;. I know nothing else about him, other than his courses outside of unit testing and snapshot testing are also quite reputable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Branding benefits from focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;#39;m not trying to grow a personal brand, per se. I&amp;#39;m trying to live a life of self expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to the topic I want to write about today&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;self-expression&quot;&gt;Self Expression&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to express oneself honestly, not lying to myself, and to express myself honestly - that - my friend, is very hard to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Bruce Lee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few days, I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about this quote from Bruce Lee quite a bit. In part because I&amp;#39;m trying to incorporate multiple different sides of myself in whatever it is I do &amp;quot;next&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my previous jobs, especially at Uber - which is the largest company I&amp;#39;ve worked for, I felt a certain confinement. Even though my managers were great and supportive, there&amp;#39;s something in the atmosphere of tech that just seemed to tell me &amp;quot;You&amp;#39;re only an engineer. Strive to become a Senior Engineer, and then a manager, and fulfill your destiny&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually think that might be a fine outcome, but I don&amp;#39;t like the path I was taking to get there. Something felt off, and I couldn&amp;#39;t quite put my finger on it. It was as if I had joined Uber by convenience (although, let me tell you, the job search is anything but convenient), that there were forces beyond my control which guided me into a job where I didn&amp;#39;t find an honest expression of who I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that led me to quit in January. For the larger part of pandemic-dominated 2020, I built projects and products with Nick. Some of these were honest attempts at self expression:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software Mentor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summer of Shipping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SpaceTime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others were not, and the outcome felt pre-ordained:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With Feather, I didn&amp;#39;t feel like this was the right expression of what I needed to do. And sure enough, the universe conspired to expose that pretty quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 30 day writing challenge created no real benefits. I didn&amp;#39;t suddenly see a rise in traffic to my website. I didn&amp;#39;t create anything insanely popular. But I did manage to make myself comfortable. I know now that whatever I do next will balance all of those dimensions of myself (scroll back above to see a list of some of those dimensions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, here&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;m looking for in whatever I do next:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something or some place that &lt;strong&gt;empowers Asian Americans&lt;/strong&gt; to be comfortable and proud of their heritage. No need to erase yourself to fit in America. That might have been necessary in 1920, or 1980, or even 2010, but 2020 is time for a new consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thoughtful Software&lt;/strong&gt; - at some point, I realized that it&amp;#39;s not clean code or high quality code that I really care about, it&amp;#39;s about thoughtfulness. Engineers who are empathetic to both the human and the machine are exceedingly rare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self esteem&lt;/strong&gt; - I personally believe that one of the greatest deficiencies on the planet is self esteem. It&amp;#39;s like we&amp;#39;re missing the world&amp;#39;s most important vitamin and everyone&amp;#39;s getting sick from insecurity. I love to teach because it raises self esteem. I focus on productivity because it reinforces (or detracts from) self esteem. I care about racial issues because racism attacks self esteem. Whatever I do, I hope I will either directly or indirectly be able to raise self esteem in others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimizing for &lt;strong&gt;flow&lt;/strong&gt; - there&amp;#39;s something sublime about flow states. When you&amp;#39;re immersed in a task, in full focus and flow, it&amp;#39;s almost a religious experience. You achieve great things when in flow. I believe that we should optimize for &amp;quot;time in flow&amp;quot;. Things like meditation, self esteem, mastery all help us get there. I suspect that minorities have a more difficult time to get in flow when they&amp;#39;re uncomfortable or feel marginalized. It&amp;#39;s a barrier to flow. Really, if you look at all the above points, you&amp;#39;ll realize that they all lead to flow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last one is weird. Not many people see things this way, and I agree it&amp;#39;s a weird mission to optimize the world for getting people into flow states. But if you see flow as an emergent quality that occurs when Maslow&amp;#39;s hierarchy of needs is properly satisfied, then you really see that optimizing for flow is a rather humanist philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that&amp;#39;s how I&amp;#39;m looking to express myself right now. I&amp;#39;m sure my views will evolve, but this is where things stand at this very specific moment. And whatever I do next, it will be based on expressing those values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;typeracer&quot;&gt;Typeracer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t want to end this week&amp;#39;s note on something so deep. I also wanted to discuss something light hearted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of you might have heard, but I&amp;#39;m getting more and more fanatical about Typeracer. I recently just surpassed 4000 races and wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/typeracer-4000&quot;&gt;a reflection about my progress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that post, there are graphs that look like this:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/tr4000_trailing30_full.png&quot; alt=&quot;Typeracer graph&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, those graphs are a huge pain in the ass to make, because I download data from Typeracer as a CSV, go into Google Sheets and make a graph every now and then. It&amp;#39;s a process that easily burns 3-5 minutes every time I want to update my results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But recently, I realized that the Typeracer API is pretty easy to use, and it&amp;#39;s possible to get this data programmatically!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behold, a tool that plots the moving average of my typing race data! (l&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer&quot;&gt;ink&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UI looks terrible right now, but it&amp;#39;s effective. But there are benefits to doing this programmatically beyond the time savings. In addition to my own data, I was able to pull data for other racers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=17maxklivans&quot;&gt;17maxklivans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=anvilclash&quot;&gt;anvilclash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=foggyy&quot;&gt;foggyy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=frostequinox&quot;&gt;frostequinox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=jestercaporado&quot;&gt;jestercaporado&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=parkevan27&quot;&gt;parkevan27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=rogeratbao&quot;&gt;rogeratbao&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=speedracergo&quot;&gt;speedracergo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s amazing about this, is you can see how these different racers improve over time. Anecdotally, I&amp;#39;ve noticed that some people seem to plateau around 110-130 WPM (i.e. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=frostequinox&quot;&gt;frostequinox&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=rogeratbao&quot;&gt;rogeratbao&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=parkevan27&quot;&gt;parkevan27&lt;/a&gt;), and some, who stick with it for a long time seem to be able to break out of a plateau (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/projects/typeracer?user=foggyy&quot;&gt;foggyy&lt;/a&gt;, who was &amp;quot;stuck&amp;quot; in the 130-140WPM for around 20,000 races before breaking through and seeing speeds in the 160 WPM range!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technical aside&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The way this works is that I&amp;#39;ve pulled the data and saved it into S3 as json files. I&amp;#39;ve only done this for 9 users (myself included), but the idea is to turn this process into an AWS Lambda and open up to anyone who wants to see their data. If you play with the query parameter &lt;code&gt;user={your-username}&lt;/code&gt; - it won&amp;#39;t work for anyone other than the profiles I&amp;#39;ve already generated files for. But on demand user data is coming 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, I&amp;#39;ll collect enough data in S3 to perform a large population study. I can finally answer the question - &amp;quot;How many races does it take, to increase your WPM by 1?&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another aside&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I think building this tool would make for an excellent take-home interview problem. What it tests:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you make API calls to Typeracer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can improve performance so you don&amp;#39;t have to call Typeracer every time? (I.e. in my case, I saved the results in S3, like a cache. Fun problems about eventual consistency, and cache invalidation can occur in the onsite)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you write code that calculates a moving average?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you work with graphing libraries? (in my case, D3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, and on the topic of Typeracer, let me share a couple of quotes that I had to type up during Typeracer that really made me stop and think:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Hyperion-Cantos-Book-1-ebook/dp/B004G60EHS&quot;&gt;Hyperion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Words bend our thinking to infinite paths of self-delusion, and the fact that we spend most of our mental lives in brain mansions built of words means that we lack the objectivity necessary to see the terrible distortion of reality which language brings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Technical-Education-Essays-Thomas-Huxley/dp/3742833286&quot;&gt;Technical Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most valuable result of all education is the ability to make yourself do the thing you have to do, when it ought to be done, whether you like it or not; it is the first lesson that ought to be learned; and however early a man&amp;#39;s training begins, it is probably the last lesson that he learns thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, that&amp;#39;s all for now! Go forth and express yourself&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phil&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-10-06]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Goodbye Feather, Hello Dallas, Miscellaneous]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-10-06</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-10-06</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-10-06">&lt;p&gt;Hey friends,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m converting my notes into a newsletter. I&amp;#39;ve enjoyed writing these notes, but distributing them has been a pain. Twitter&amp;#39;s not the right distribution medium. RSS is cool (and I added &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/rss.xml&quot;&gt;a feed&lt;/a&gt;!), but I like the &amp;quot;idea of RSS&amp;quot; more than actually using RSS - and I suspect that&amp;#39;s true for most people as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only good option is a newsletter. I thought about Substack, which I&amp;#39;ve used in the past (exhibit &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacetime.substack.com/&quot;&gt;A&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://softwarementor.substack.com&quot;&gt;B&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofshipping.substack.com&quot;&gt;C&lt;/a&gt;), but Substack newsletters feel too professional these days and I&amp;#39;m not trying to work for the Passion Economy™ here. I gave TinyLetter a look and the price was right, but the vibe was not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, I turned to Buttondown, a product I&amp;#39;ve been secretly admiring for almost a year. It&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://jmduke.com/&quot;&gt;Indie built&lt;/a&gt; and has strong positioning against Substack (more customizable and dev friendly 😍), Mailchimp (cheaper 💸), and TinyLetter (it&amp;#39;s just better 💪).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, welcome to &lt;a href=&quot;https://buttondown.email/pliao39&quot;&gt;my Buttondown&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has changed in the past few weeks so let&amp;#39;s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;goodbye-feather&quot;&gt;Goodbye Feather&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest change is that Nick and I have decided to pause all work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://feather.id/&quot;&gt;Feather&lt;/a&gt;. While I still believe there is an opportunity for someone to come in and make a lot of noise in the Auth space with a bottoms up approach, we&amp;#39;re pretty sure it won&amp;#39;t be us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A startup &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=424495&quot;&gt;runs on morale&lt;/a&gt; and when it comes to Auth - my tank is empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a lot to be learned here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don&amp;#39;t scratch your own itch unless you&amp;#39;ve previously paid for a similar product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a healthy ratio of talking to customers and building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;launch earlier &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://versoly.com/founder-bingo&quot;&gt;Classic founder mistakes&lt;/a&gt;, but perhaps the biggest problem was &amp;quot;Why?&amp;quot;. Not in the sense, &amp;quot;Why is this a good idea&amp;quot;, but rather &amp;quot;Why are YOU working on it?&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was I enthusiastic and passionate about Auth? Was I sufficiently motivated or even angry? No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;#39;t love an idea, aren&amp;#39;t obsessed about it, aren&amp;#39;t staying up late thinking about the customer pain point, then don&amp;#39;t pursue it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all future ideas, I now realize the entire early team needs to be &lt;em&gt;wildly&lt;/em&gt; enthusiastic. Even if the market is amazing, you&amp;#39;ll need to grind it out, and it makes it that much more likely you&amp;#39;ll persevere if your heart is in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hello-dallas&quot;&gt;Hello Dallas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other big change is that I&amp;#39;m currently in Dallas. My parents closed on a new house, and I&amp;#39;m up here &amp;quot;house sitting&amp;quot; as they try to sell their old house back in Houston (btw - got any tips for selling a house? We&amp;#39;re in need of your wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s taken me pretty much an entire week to adjust to living by myself again. Food has been an adjustment. Loneliness has been an adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this adjustment has been great. Uncomfortable but great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cold showers, quitting a job cold turkey to strike out on your own, solo travel, taking the road less traveled by, &lt;a href=&quot;https://breakingsmart.substack.com/p/against-waldenponding&quot;&gt;Waldenponding™&lt;/a&gt; and &amp;quot;Into the Wild&amp;quot;ing - these are all examples where you dive into something uncomfortable and find yourself literally or figuratively fighting for breath. Slowly, you regain some control. Dormant muscles get reactivated - and it reminds you who you truly are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know what I&amp;#39;m trying to say here. It&amp;#39;s probably something about risk, identity, self-reliance, and nature - but there&amp;#39;s no point I&amp;#39;m making, just an observation that I&amp;#39;m feeling good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7 Powers: The Foundations of Business Strategy&lt;/strong&gt; -  I just finished up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/7-Powers-Foundations-Business-Strategy-ebook/dp/B01MRLFFQ7&quot;&gt;this book&lt;/a&gt; (it&amp;#39;s quite short), but I feel like it&amp;#39;s beginning to stitch together some ideas that I had previously known as discrete pieces of information (i.e. Innovator&amp;#39;s Dilemma, Switching Costs, Network Effects, etc). Now, they sit together in a more coherent whole (the path to creating a strategic business moat). I&amp;#39;m trying to distill my knowledge of business strategy into action and I plan to do that by writing amateur equity research in the future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Fortune Cookie Chronicles&lt;/strong&gt; - This is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Fortune-Cookie-Chronicles-Adventures-Chinese-ebook/dp/B0010SKUOW&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on the history of Chinese food in America. I&amp;#39;m a few chapters in and I&amp;#39;m a fan. If you know anything about my stance on Americanized Chinese food, you know it&amp;#39;s not positive. I hate Panda Express (only the Tofu is worth ordering). I eat Orange Chicken, General Tso&amp;#39;s Chicken, and other candied meat with reluctance. There&amp;#39;s nothing Chinese about this food. Reading the book largely confirms what I already know, but the stories are significantly more entrepreneurial than I imagined. It&amp;#39;s a solid read. After I digest this book, I bet I&amp;#39;ll have a lot more to say on Chinese Food in general - to me, it&amp;#39;s a deep symbol for the Chinese experience in America.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Boron Letters&lt;/strong&gt; - one part &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0367279/&quot;&gt;Arrested Development&lt;/a&gt;, one part copywriting masterclass, and one part self help book - this has got to be one of the more interesting ways to learn entrepreneurship fundamentals and the basics of copywriting. It&amp;#39;s a collection of letters written by the legendary copywriter Gary Halbert to his son - while serving time in prison. I&amp;#39;ll do a reaction to this book soon - it&amp;#39;s great. This week&amp;#39;s thread of self reliance is rooted in some of the advice given from father to son&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-09-29]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Book Reviews, Writing and Coding, Enabling Environments]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-29</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-29</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-29">&lt;p&gt;I missed last week and got delayed this week. But the notes keep coming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;book-reviews&quot;&gt;Book Reviews&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main update since my last batch of notes (as it pertains to this website) is that I published &lt;a href=&quot;/books/how-to-take-smart-notes&quot;&gt;my review/summary of How to Take Smart Notes&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m excited about that for a couple reasons: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I enjoy learning about the process of learning and intend to explore this topic further. It&amp;#39;s great to have a milestone to look back upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Book reviews are an excellent &amp;quot;attack vector&amp;quot; into a topic. I&amp;#39;ve always thought about how Vitalik Buterin was &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoinmagazine.com/authors/vitalik-buterin&quot;&gt;first a journalist&lt;/a&gt; in crypto before creating Ethereum. I love this concept of being an archaeologist/anthropologist/researcher of a domain before entering. It gives you credibility and deepens your awareness of the space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s all to say, expect more book reviews. They&amp;#39;re basically &amp;quot;admissions tickets&amp;quot; into any topic of your choosing. They provide the cover fire to enter a new world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-and-coding&quot;&gt;Writing and Coding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval/status/1002106893265920000?s=20&quot;&gt;Naval identified&lt;/a&gt; that media and code are two assets anyone can produce, yet can reach massive audiences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code and media are permissionless leverage. They&amp;#39;re the leverage behind the newly rich. You can create software and media that works for you while you sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if writing forces you to get your ideas into a presentable state, then - as &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Conaw/status/1206037537589850119?s=20&quot;&gt;@conaw observed&lt;/a&gt; - coding takes it a step further:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code is crystallized thought&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really love these similarities between code and writing, but there&amp;#39;s one dimension in which I wish they were more similar: testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With software, you can constantly test your work. The work itself might be more unforgiving - not a single character can be incorrect - but the speed at which you get feedback is unparalleled. With code, you can set up an environment in which you get feedback every time you save a file. And this feedback can execute in seconds, or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With writing, every time a change is made, we have to read our work. We must switch from a writer&amp;#39;s mindset to a reader&amp;#39;s - just to see if what we&amp;#39;ve created makes any sense at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do unit/integration tests give you faster feedback to see if your code works, it allows you to &amp;quot;refactor&amp;quot; or tighten up working code such that the same ideas can be expressed more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no such thing for writing - and thus, the feedback cycles are just so much slower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s not much of a point here - other than to say I wish there was a way we could get faster feedback on our writing...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;enabling-environments&quot;&gt;Enabling Environments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;#39;ve been in a state of &amp;quot;funemployment&amp;quot; for almost 9 months. &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacetime.substack.com/p/1-categories&quot;&gt;Initially&lt;/a&gt;, the goal was to travel and build SpaceTime, but those plans quickly got derailed. Since then, I&amp;#39;ve worked on a variety of random projects: &lt;a href=&quot;https://softwarementor.substack.com&quot;&gt;Software Mentor&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofshipping.com&quot;&gt;Summer of Shipping&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://feather.id&quot;&gt;Feather&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve learned a lot during that time. But I&amp;#39;m not sure I maximized my learning - and the reason for this is that I haven&amp;#39;t quite constructed an environment which provides both sufficient feedback,  motivation, and a rate of iteration that makes it all work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m trying to fix that with my future initiatives - the first of which is to grow this website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when it comes to choosing content, I plan to let growth be my initial guide. I believe growth is key to feedback, which in turn unlocks an &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.andymatuschak.org/Enabling_environment&quot;&gt;Enabling Environments&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, this was the subject of the example I presented in my &amp;quot;How to Take Smart Notes&amp;quot; review: why &amp;quot;looking for growth&amp;quot; seemed to be common career advice. The idea that personal growth is correlated to product growth &amp;quot;sounds about right&amp;quot;, but it&amp;#39;s hard to figure out what action you should take about it. The advice of finding a set of things that can grow fast, and then picking your favorite among that set, is a very useful framing. While I don&amp;#39;t plan to follow that exactly (in fact, I&amp;#39;m doing the opposite - I&amp;#39;m restricting topics by my personal interest first, and then focusing on growth), it&amp;#39;s useful to recognize the importance of growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a bit of rambling, but in sum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to create an enabling environment for myself, which I believe needs product growth. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe this website can be such an environment, if it grows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus, I intend to grow this website by first being open about the topics I explore, and then doubling down on whatever works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will report back if this works. I&amp;#39;m sure there are tons of little details I&amp;#39;ll need to overcome to make this happen.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-09-13]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Attention, How to Take Smart Notes, Portability, Miscellaneous]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-13</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-13</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-13">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, my day started with errands. They say you have to win the morning to win the day, and I found that to be true, just in reverse. I lost the morning, and I certainly lost the day.  But otherwise, it was a good week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; In fact, I feel like I had a great week in terms of notes. Some highlights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;attention&quot;&gt;Attention&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On HackerNews, the article &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24391686&quot;&gt;Attention is your scarcest resource&lt;/a&gt; made its rounds last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key quote from the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“50%+ focus” is roughly when something becomes the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/top.html&quot;&gt;top idea in your mind&lt;/a&gt;. It’s when you start caring enough to think about it in the shower. It’s when you start habitually asking “how could this go faster?” It’s when you get &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/relres.html&quot;&gt;relentlessly resourceful&lt;/a&gt;. It’s around when you start &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benkuhn.net/impatient/&quot;&gt;annoying your coworkers and/or significant other&lt;/a&gt;, although that part is avoidable with practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having one top idea in your mind (itself, an essay from Paul Graham) is extremely powerful. Anecdotally, it seems that my teammates&amp;#39; best ideas emerge spontaneously, and outside of work. One day, we&amp;#39;ll show up to work in the morning and they&amp;#39;ll tell me &amp;quot;Hey, had this idea, what if we...&amp;quot;- and suddenly we&amp;#39;re on a new trajectory. Personally, I come up with a lot of my best ideas in the early morning, or after working up a sweat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attention is scarce, and we all understand how constant context switching can kill productivity. But there&amp;#39;s another cost to splintering your attention - an opportunity cost of sorts. Our brains run a variety of processes, of which we&amp;#39;re only conscious of &amp;quot;linear thinking&amp;quot;. When it comes to problem solving and searching for creative solutions, our subconscious brain, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/lecture/learning-how-to-learn/introduction-to-the-focused-and-diffuse-modes-75EsZ&quot;&gt;diffuse mode&lt;/a&gt; of thinking, needs to be activated too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#39;t seen any instructions on how to activate this creative, diffuse mode of &amp;quot;connecting the dots&amp;quot; - but I believe that curiosity is necessary. If you only keep deeply &lt;a href=&quot;/weekly_notes/2020-07-26#questions&quot;&gt;interesting questions&lt;/a&gt; in your mind, you stand a chance. But, there&amp;#39;s clearly a limit to the number of interesting questions we can load into our brains. 1,000 is too many. But what about 2? Can our diffuse modes consider even 2 simultaneous questions? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not so sure. I believe we must focus on one thing at a time. On any given day - focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-take-smart-notes&quot;&gt;How to Take Smart Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started reading, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Take-Smart-Notes-Nonfiction-ebook/dp/B06WVYW33Y&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;How to Take Smart Notes&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;m not entirely sure how I ended up buying it, but it popped up on my radar enough times to warrant a look (likely the #roamcult). When a few smart people start recommending the same thing, that&amp;#39;s a good sign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, I&amp;#39;m about halfway through the book and I&amp;#39;m convinced it will change my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s why: this book will change the way you read and learn. When it comes to knowledge, most people are living paycheck to paycheck - we are as smart as the most recent stuff we&amp;#39;ve read. This book presents a system that allows us to create a knowledge bank that can accrue learning AND compound in value. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools like Roam and Obsidian facilitate this system. But the tool is insufficient, you must learn the procedure of how to maintain your ever growing web of knowledge. Simply having a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memex&quot;&gt;memex&lt;/a&gt; is not enough. How you manage it is everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll be summarizing/reviewing this book soon - its lessons are hard to put into practice. But I believe that those who do will reap benefits that are hard to imagine. After all, the human brain isn&amp;#39;t very good at intuiting exponential growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;portability&quot;&gt;Portability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea came up in the context of the term &amp;quot;digital sharecropping&amp;quot; - or the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/skmurphy/status/1304955612384485376?s=20&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;investing in a platform you don&amp;#39;t own&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;. It happens in the context of &amp;quot;user generated content&amp;quot;, but also when building a business on top of another platform which might shut down at any moment (i.e. Facebook games, Twitter API). Or the platform might just shut &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; down (i.e. via a cease and desist or &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourincrediblejourney.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Acquihire&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is also interesting as it relates to the careers of software engineers. Compare, as an exercise, a software engineer to a salesperson. The salesperson gains skills at a company, learns a process, but most importantly, builds up a rolodex of people that work at other companies. By doing deals with a lot of different people, they accumulate a network that grows more valuable every month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast this to the software engineer. The engineer gains skills, learns processes, but in contrast, builds up a resume of commits that are only visible within the company. Sure, the engineer may develop relationships with people, but there&amp;#39;s a limit to the number of &amp;quot;career changing connections&amp;quot; they make as mere a byproduct of their job. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider internal transfers vs external hires. With transfers, we can look at someone&amp;#39;s commits and see their work product. We do half the number of interviews we normally would for an outside hire, and the process is greatly relaxed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, software engineers get paid a good amount (especially early in their careers), but they need to realize that there&amp;#39;s limited liquidity to their skills. Outside of the knowledge you gain and a title bump, there&amp;#39;s very little you can take with you (and even then, the title bump might not be respected by a new employer). You can&amp;#39;t always take your domain expertise. You can&amp;#39;t take your commits (which you can use to reference previous best practices).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will you work at the same company forever? If you suspect the answer is no, then you&amp;#39;ll likely need to change some of your habits. Invest in transferable technical skills (focus less time on company specific excellence and more on general excellence). Write on the internet, use social media, do open source - build yourself a bit of a reputation. Invest in portability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;False Dichotomies&lt;/strong&gt; - I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about ways in which the world is not black or white. Not enough here to share an idea, but consider these constructs: &amp;quot;Architect vs Gardener&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Bootstrap or VC&amp;quot;. To me, they&amp;#39;re all false dichotomies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep&lt;/strong&gt; - my sleep this last week has improved 🙌. Or at the very least, I&amp;#39;ve used melatonin and orange tinted, blue light blocking glasses to adjust my sleep schedule to about Midnight to ~8AM. Not sure if my sleep has improved, but productivity has seen a small boost!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rewire your Anxious Brain&lt;/strong&gt; - another book that I&amp;#39;m reading that I think has useful applications to my life. I&amp;#39;ve always found truth in the idea that &amp;quot;what we need to do is often what we fear the most&amp;quot; But I&amp;#39;ve never had a good strategy for dealing with it. This book doesn&amp;#39;t solve the psychological, but it does help you understand the neuroscience behind why you can&amp;#39;t &amp;quot;think your way&amp;quot; past anxiety, and you need different tools for this rewiring 🧠. Will do a summary/review of it soon-ish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-09-06]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Meme Marketing, Open Source Business Models, Miscellaneous]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-06</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-06</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-06">&lt;p&gt;After a week off, I’m back. And there’s a ton of stuff to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;meme-marketing&quot;&gt;Meme Marketing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic emerged from a conversation with my friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ChalupaBatmanGG&quot;&gt;David Park&lt;/a&gt;. David’s company, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kippoapp.com/&quot;&gt;Kippo&lt;/a&gt;, is a dating app for gamers. And while there’s much to talk about regarding the &lt;a href=&quot;/weekly_notes/2020-08-09#internet-friends&quot;&gt;digitization of dating and social interaction&lt;/a&gt;, the company’s early growth strategy is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lennysan/status/1252324468002713600?s=20&quot;&gt;Lenny Rachitsky asked on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer app founders: How did you get your first 2,000 users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ChalupaBatmanGG/status/1252359322329157638?s=20&quot;&gt;David responded&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a meme with a footer to our website. Made it to the front page with 52k upvotes. Free impressions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally got a chance to catch up with David last week and had to ask him about it. Here&amp;#39;s a brief summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(One day, we&amp;#39;ll need to get David to deconstruct this process some more, but for now, you&amp;#39;re stuck with my rendition.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reddit is the self proclaimed &amp;quot;Front Page of the Internet&amp;quot;. When successfully harnessed, Reddit can send your website a stampede of traffic. That&amp;#39;s great for marketers, but Redditors HATE being marketed to. Perhaps due to unsavory past experiences, the moment they smell a marketer, Redditors attack. The visual I imagine is much like &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/a-game-of-drones-why-some-bees-kill-their-queens-83624&quot;&gt;bees turning on their queen&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending far too much time on Reddit, David noticed that Memes outperformed other posts. He started asking: “How could we make memes work for Kippo?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he didn&amp;#39;t just blindly start making Memes. Instead, he asked a pivotal follow up &lt;a href=&quot;/weekly_notes/2020-07-26#questions&quot;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; “Why is a meme funny on Reddit?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kippo team noticed patterns. Some memes were unexpectedly relatable. Others had shock value. And they got to work producing memes that reconstructed those sensations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some duds, but soon enough the Memes started to catch fire. Here are a couple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EWUPV5mUMA4NuMV?format=png&amp;name=small&quot; alt=&quot;True Love meme&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EWUPX7ZU4AEEKj5?format=jpg&amp;name=medium&quot; alt=&quot;What people think Gaming is like&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kippo doesn’t rely on Memes as much these days (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kippoapp.com/comics&quot;&gt;Kippo Comics&lt;/a&gt; for their primary meme distribution channel), but I found this 0 to 2,000 users story fascinating. It reminds me of this grab-bag of tactics &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kapwing.com/blog/viral-content/&quot;&gt;used by Kapwing&lt;/a&gt; - which is presumably, the maturation of tactics from Kapwing&amp;#39;s early days of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kapwing.com/blog/how-we-got-our-first-10-customers/&quot;&gt;(successful) floundering&lt;/a&gt;. As well as this tactic used by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.towerpaddleboards.com/&quot;&gt;Tower Paddle Boards&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://marketingexamples.com/seo/unsplash&quot;&gt;grow via Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unconventional, but very effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-source-business-models&quot;&gt;Open Source Business Models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money and open source have a funny relationship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;#39;s clarify that there is no philosophical tension between Open Source and profits. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fsf.org/about/&quot;&gt;Free Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, arguably the spiritual center of Open Source, has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/selling.html&quot;&gt;this to say&lt;/a&gt; on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people believe that the spirit of the GNU Project is that you should not charge money for distributing copies of software, or that you should charge as little as possible—just enough to cover the cost. This is a misunderstanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, we encourage people who redistribute free software to charge as much as they wish or can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More fundamentally, there seems to be a contradiction in &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to make money with Open Source. How do you charge money for software that is 100% open and free to run? Would that not yield perfect competition, eliminate profits, and turn these into untenable businesses?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, Red Hat (&lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2019/08/01/with-the-acquisition-closed-ibm-goes-all-in-on-red-hat/&quot;&gt;acq. by IBM&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/CLDR?p=CLDR&amp;amp;.tsrc=fin-srch&quot;&gt;Cloudera&lt;/a&gt;, MuleSoft (&lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2018/03/20/salesforce-is-buying-mulesoft-at-enterprise-value-of-6-5-billion/&quot;&gt;acq. by SalesForce&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/MDB?p=MDB&amp;amp;.tsrc=fin-srch&quot;&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/ESTC?p=ESTC&amp;amp;.tsrc=fin-srch&quot;&gt;Elastic&lt;/a&gt; all beg to differ. These are all multi-billion dollar companies that trade (or traded) on the public markets. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you look at the IPO pipeline, you might see Confluent, Hashicorp, Databricks and others not too far away from the event horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do these companies charge for? A survey in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/10/04/commercializing-open-source/&quot;&gt;history&lt;/a&gt; of enterprise open source will yield the following story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support (i.e. Red Hat)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proprietary software built upon an open source core - aka Open Core - and sold as an annual license (i.e. most of Elastic&amp;#39;s business)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SaaS offering of the open source code, in partnership with public cloud (i.e., the fastest growing segment of Mongo&amp;#39;s business)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who follow enterprise software, it&amp;#39;s the SaaS angle that has recently unlocked Open Source for these venture backed businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s interesting that all of the examples I cited so far are very much &amp;quot;infrastructure&amp;quot; products. But the trend of Open Source business models has caught on elsewhere too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattermost.com/&quot;&gt;Mattermost&lt;/a&gt; (an Open source Slack alternative) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.org/&quot;&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; (an alternative to Wordpress). Two examples of how Open Source software is expanding beyond it&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;home court&amp;quot; of developers, and capturing a broader spectrum of users. (Ghost, btw, is not only Open Source, but a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.org/about/&quot;&gt;non-profit&lt;/a&gt; too. One that just happens to make $200K+ in MRR)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you look at smaller products (yet admittedly, more targeted at developers), you might find &lt;a href=&quot;https://tailwindui.com/&quot;&gt;TailwindUI&lt;/a&gt;, which is built atop the Open Source project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tailwindlabs/tailwindcss&quot;&gt;TailwindCSS&lt;/a&gt;. Or &lt;a href=&quot;https://forge.laravel.com/&quot;&gt;Laravel Forge&lt;/a&gt;, which is similarly built atop the Open Source project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/laravel/laravel&quot;&gt;Laravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without considering all these examples, you might have believed that there is no business model in open source. That the only way to get funds doing Open Source is getting backed by a corporate patron (ie React), or decentralized patronage (ie Vue). And for many (most?) open source maintainers, survival is indeed about finding patrons. (Choose one of: 1) GitHub sponsors/Open Collective, 2) work for Google/Facebook on Open Source, or 3) burnout).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;#39;s simply not the full story. Too many developers get into the &amp;quot;business&amp;quot; of Open Source without ever realizing that they&amp;#39;re sitting atop a potential goldmine (in the form of a community and audience). Open Source maintainers are often influencers by accident. The challenge is monetizing this influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Source businesses are going to become increasingly important moving forward (especially for developer focused products). Open Source builds trust, transforms the community into &amp;quot;co-creators&amp;quot; (superfans), generates another distribution channel, establishes goodwill. A well run open source company has natural advantages that its closed source counterparts simply do not have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say Open Source business is easy. Simply that it is the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll be writing about this topic a lot, but just giving you a first glance into my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m introducing a new section to these weekly notes, where I write bullet points about random things that I came across this week. If the above are half baked notes, the following are uncooked. Here we go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First thoughts on Rust-lang. Coming from Golang and Java, the idea of eliminating concurrency issues like race conditions &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ch04-02-references-and-borrowing.html#mutable-references&quot;&gt;by design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is amazing. Sadly, I also miss Golang&amp;#39;s compilation speeds. Go compiles fast &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/a/2976675&quot;&gt;by design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finally watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt11394168/&quot;&gt;Be Water&lt;/a&gt; - the documentary on Bruce Lee. His unyielding refusal to take on any demeaning role, paired with a  mentality of &amp;quot;your loss&amp;quot; towards those who didn&amp;#39;t value his vision - is a model of self-respect. We lost Bruce when he was 32 and right on the cusp of superstardom. Far too early. And in a huge blow to Asian American masculinity, Hollywood picked Jackie Chan as his successor. I love Jackie, but -  let me just say this, Jackie worked in the house, and Bruce in the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Datadog is an amazing company - or at least &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; think it is, after looking at their 10K. Sales and Marketing efficiency is best in class. Their strategy is amazing too (unified metrics, tracing, and logs &lt;em&gt;chefs kiss&lt;/em&gt;). So much to learn and unpack about this company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The next time you&amp;#39;re scared and want to &amp;quot;bury your head in the sand&amp;quot;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://animals.howstuffworks.com/birds/do-ostriches-really-bury-heads-in-sand.htm&quot;&gt;consider the facts&lt;/a&gt;. Ostriches do not actually bury their heads when scared. Rather, they bury their eggs in the sand, and rotate their eggs multiple times a day. They are not scared, they&amp;#39;re just taking care of their young. I mean, just think about it, why would a 9 ft, 350 lb animal be scared? Not to mention they&amp;#39;re fast (40 MPH, which is 10+ MPH faster than Usain Bolt). You&amp;#39;ve seen &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aMmX-n1YGlA&quot;&gt;the Kevin Hart skit&lt;/a&gt;. Fear the Ostrich &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-08-23]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Mental Health]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-23</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-23</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-23">&lt;p&gt;I started writing my notes yesterday and I just didn&amp;#39;t &amp;quot;have it&amp;quot;. Despite consecutive days of great sleep, solid exercise, and good weather, something was just off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, my parents and I sent my little brother off to college. I did not expect it to be a massive challenge, but the psychological effect on my parents has been brutal. Yes, there&amp;#39;s an element of empty nesting, which every parent goes through, but there&amp;#39;s also the circumstances around my brother&amp;#39;s college selection (he&amp;#39;s on a plan to transfer schools in his sophomore/junior year - anyone who&amp;#39;s been in that position knows the stress).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their emotions have stirred within me, a sense of unease. Combined with an increased level of anxiety from previous weeks and the result is cratering levels of productivity. Attempting to be productive right now feels as beneficial as running with increasingly painful shin splints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I won&amp;#39;t. This week, my only note will be a short one on mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mental-health&quot;&gt;Mental Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s 2020, and we all know [[Mental Health]] is supremely important. We crave authenticity (after being flooded by people&amp;#39;s Best Selves™ on [[Facebook]] and Instagram for years, we want to see real people). And we need &amp;quot;depressurized&amp;quot; spaces to talk and meet new people. And while the need is astronomical, I still think we&amp;#39;re extremely bad at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, mental health is a lot like physical health. In both, there are exercises you can do to improve (i.e. meditation and journaling on one side, squats and [[HIIT]] on the other). When you&amp;#39;re feeling healthy, either mentally or physically, you reap benefits to everything else in your life. On the other hand, if you are &amp;quot;injured&amp;quot;, even simple things can be difficult. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unlike physical health, mental [[wellness]] is probably more complex and certainly harder to measure. When someone is physically healthy, you can look for obvious signals (healthy HR, BMI, VO2 max, etc). When someone has great mental health, how can you measure that? And how do you know if the measurement is accurate (not faked)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly have no answer for this, but I&amp;#39;m trying a few things to help me feel comfortable in all aspects of my life. It involves reading books on spiritual wellness, practicing mindfulness meditation and self care, improving my relationship with my parents, learning my history and heritage so I can be rooted in my identity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to start adding a books section on my personal site for this reason. When I&amp;#39;m having an issue with my mental health, I often find that the right book is the perfect medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, in addition to reading, I often find talking to my [[Otter]] app very useful. It&amp;#39;s just [[Audio]] transcription software, but it feels a bit like a therapist. It&amp;#39;s lower friction that writing and pairs nicely with journaling. But that&amp;#39;s just me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is to say that I&amp;#39;ve surprisingly found myself at the &amp;quot;bust&amp;quot; of another [[boom and bust]] cycle, one that I did not imagine would have come so soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel comfortable sharing, I&amp;#39;d love to hear from you - what strategies do you find effective when dealing with degraded mental health?&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-08-16]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Mistakes, Audio]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-16</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-16</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-16">&lt;p&gt;This week I read [[Siddhartha]] by Herman Hesse (as translated by Hilda Rosner). There&amp;#39;s a lot to say about the book - it&amp;#39;s tremendous - but today I&amp;#39;ll focus on one idea from the book, which is the necessity of mistakes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to talk about [[Audio]]. So to expect two sections this week: mistakes, and audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mistakes&quot;&gt;Mistakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to draw an image personifying spirituality, I might sketch a picture of a monk at a monastery, practicing sitting meditation and drinking tea. He has found peace - having renounced all worldly possessions. I&amp;#39;d draw his mouth with a subtle upward curve, to resemble the slightest of smiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I certainly would not draw a gambler, mired in a midlife existential crisis, experiencing a nauseating level of depression. But that is precisely what our protagonist, Siddhartha, experienced:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to experience despair, I had to sink to the greatest mental depths, to thoughts of suicide, in order to experience grace, to hear Om again, to sleep deeply again and to awaken refreshed again. I had to become a fool again in order to find Atman in myself. I had to sin in order to live again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something extremely relatable about despair. Whereas wild success is a rare fruit tasted only by a small fragment of civilization&amp;#39;s elite - all of us have known failure. Some to darker nadirs, but all of us know this suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what&amp;#39;s beautiful about this - is that the book shows us not only can we &amp;quot;bounce back&amp;quot; from the lowest points in our life, but they are actually necessary. Without them, you may gain an intellectual understanding of wisdom. But to truly know what wisdom and truth are, you must take your own unique path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my life, I find this question recur with frequency. Is it possible to &amp;quot;beeline&amp;quot; to peace? Or must you take the winding path? Or as my mother describes &amp;quot;弯路&amp;quot; - a torturous, bending road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engineer in me says that optimization is possible. But all signs point elsewhere. We each have moments where we know something is wrong, something is off - but choose it anyways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take for example, this software engineer on a Reddit thread that I found recently. This young engineer took a job for prestige and is now miserable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate everything about it. I had a choice between a company with great people, better CoL and same pay and my current company.
The only thing better here is the prestige, I fell for it. I knew something felt off during the interview but I took the job anyway.
People here are assholes who live to work, pretend to be nice and backstab you as soon as they can.
Fuck them, fuck me. I wish I I could go back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/i3g44t/i_picked_a_job_for_the_prestige_and_i_regret_it/&quot;&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/i3g44t/i_picked_a_job_for_the_prestige_and_i_regret_it/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;#39;s this engineer. But we&amp;#39;ve all made that same decision before. And maybe not for prestige, but for reasons that we knew were wrong, but simply couldn&amp;#39;t override.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no lesson here. These are my notes. Not an essay. There is no point I&amp;#39;m trying to make. No argument I&amp;#39;m advancing. Simply that I thought the idea of [[Mistakes | mistakes]] as not only beneficial, but necessary for spiritual growth was deeply beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the number of times I have felt existential pangs as a consequence of my decisions - it&amp;#39;s possible that I&amp;#39;ve made enough mistakes to set the stage for growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But probably not. I suspect I have many more mistakes ahead of me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio&quot;&gt;Audio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so let&amp;#39;s change gears from the spiritual to the technical, and talk about audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re not familiar with these two articles, bookmark them and read them after you&amp;#39;ve consumed this piece:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alexdanco.com/2019/10/17/the-audio-revolution/&quot;&gt;The Audio Revolution&lt;/a&gt; by Alex Danco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2020/02/24/a-text-renaissance/&quot;&gt;A Text Renaissance&lt;/a&gt; by Venkatesh Rao&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;#39;m certainly missing other blog posts/tweets on what I&amp;#39;m sure will be a trend of tech writers discussing the future of audio. I&amp;#39;m less interested in predictions on Audio though, and would rather focus on getting the pulse on what is out there today, and what I feel like each of these technologies might unleash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the style of Venkat&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;A Text Renaissance&amp;quot; (or at least the first half of that piece), I will briefly outline a series of technologies that I think have put us at the precipice of a Cambrian explosion in audio. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebRTC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AirPods (and Fast Pair)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discord and Clubhouse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI Transcription&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcasting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to skip around, these sections came out to be much longer than I anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;webrtc&quot;&gt;WebRTC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[[WebRTC]] is here. Finally. After initial release in 2011, and so many teasers along the way, we&amp;#39;re finally at the point where browsers have deployed stable and high quality versions of WebRTC. In fact, the stable spec was only finalized on May 4, 2018 - and security vulnerabilities have been discovered and patched since. It&amp;#39;s been a long road, but it&amp;#39;s finally here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, developer productivity has seen massive benefits due to browser affordances like &amp;quot;flexbox&amp;quot;, native promises (leading to async/await), and countless other small improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for most of us, WebRTC was just a thing that was always on the horizon. But it sort of crept up on all of us, and now it&amp;#39;s there, ready for the tinkering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, I don&amp;#39;t think this means the fall of Zoom anytime soon. Zoom has invested heavily in their own architecture and technology and probably have a massive lead on everyone. But that&amp;#39;s for video - which consumes significantly more bandwidth than audio and is a different kind of problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WebRTC and audio work very well today. For example, my friends Azlen and Jon built &lt;a href=&quot;https://cozyroom.xyz/&quot;&gt;Cozyroom&lt;/a&gt;, which sits atop of WebRTC. They&amp;#39;ve since polished it after their humble hackathon beginnings, but these types of experiences are about to explode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myself, I&amp;#39;m working with Nick on &lt;a href=&quot;https://openhouse.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Openhouse&lt;/a&gt;. Which I&amp;#39;ll talk about much more in the future - but for now, know that it is a project built with the intention of learning WebRTC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;airpods&quot;&gt;AirPods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a trend that didn&amp;#39;t really make a whole lot of sense to me at first. How does a stupid little accessory change the face of computing, especially since it doesn&amp;#39;t do anything structurally different from its corded predecessors?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it changed a lot. It changed our fashion sensibilities around wearables. It changed how often we plug into audio. It taught us that we could replace our own thoughts with the voice/laugh of Joe Rogen.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has completely surprised Apple, demolishing their own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macrumors.com/2019/11/27/apple-doubling-airpods-pro-production-report/&quot;&gt;sales projections&lt;/a&gt;. And the demand for AirPods, feels as insatiable as the demand for Teslas in a world of unlimited access to a subprime auto loans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#39;s not just AirPods. Apple&amp;#39;s forever copycat, Android, has finally shipped &amp;quot;Fast Pair&amp;quot; earbuds that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blog.google/products/android/fast-pair-easier-bluetooth/&quot;&gt;might not suck&lt;/a&gt;. When the proliferation of fashionable Android wireless earbuds finally hits mass adoption, get ready for a further acceleration of people escaping from their own thoughts via podcasts and other monkey mind pacifiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;discord-and-clubhouse&quot;&gt;Discord and Clubhouse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who still think Discord competes with Slack for communities... Where the hell have you been? It&amp;#39;s been my experience that all communities that have started after COVID-19 have chosen Discord, and the only Slack communities that I still get invites from are legacy ones, or businesses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s silly to think Discord and Slack compete on instant messaging. Slack is the &amp;quot;semi-async&amp;quot; text communication solution for startups, which competes with Microsoft Teams in the enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord is a social &lt;strong&gt;space&lt;/strong&gt; that embraces pseudonymity and gamers. It facilitates seamless jumping between communities (something that is an architectural impossibility given Slack&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.engineering/how-slack-built-shared-channels/&quot;&gt;sharded MySQL strategy&lt;/a&gt;), but most importantly (imo), it provides persistent voice channels for communities to congregate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These voice channels seemed stupid to me at first. Like why would you want an always open connection to friends that you can hop in and hop out of at any time? Why not just call them? Why would this change behavior at all? I mean, as far as the technology is concerned, this idea has ALWAYS been possible - so why didn&amp;#39;t it take off before?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the reduction in friction to communicating with people does change behavior. It makes it feel like walking into a common room at a youth hostel and seeing who&amp;#39;s there. It creates audio serendipity in a way that is impossible on Slack. It feels like a physical space, made possible by... audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is a great segue into Clubhouse. See, Clubhouse and Discord share something in common. I described Discord voice channels via the metaphor of a &amp;quot;common room&amp;quot;. Well, in Clubhouse, the primary interface is a list of &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;rooms&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;, or shared audio spaces - they lean into that metaphor big time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the larger rooms, there&amp;#39;s a small handful of speakers on stage enjoying a free-flowing (often moderated) discussion. All while an audience listens silently from their muted perch (audience members cannot speak unless selected by the moderator to join the stage). And in the smaller rooms, it&amp;#39;s a public, participatory discussion about anything random.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clubhouse to me - and it might morph into something very different in the coming weeks, such is the pace of mutation - feels like a book festival. If you&amp;#39;ve never heard of a book festival, then you&amp;#39;re not alone. The only reason I know the term is I randomly found myself in Berkeley once upon a time - and it just so happened to be during the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.baybookfest.org/content/2015/schedule.html&quot;&gt;first annual&lt;/a&gt; Bay Area book festival. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a lot like a music festival, but instead of featuring musicians, there were authors and literary figures. And instead of performing music, they just talked. Different bookstores and theaters around Berkeley were all booked for the extravaganza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I opened Clubhouse for the first time, it felt like I was transported to downtown Berkeley for the book festival. There were a list of different talks happening right then, and list of upcoming events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It amazes me how audio, seems to create the illusion of spaces. Definitely not physically, but it creates an imaginative space that feels &amp;quot;cozy&amp;quot; in a way that Zoom and Google Meet simply do not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m particularly excited about our Openhouse project because it allows for these affordances and to create spaces that can feel cozy. The internet is mutating, and open source is the highly editable RNA that powers the rapid evolution of new tech. I want to see a world where any community can embed a Clubhouse like experience on any site or in any app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if that happens, then we&amp;#39;ll chip away at the value prop of universities. Their lectures have already been digitized and commoditized. Now, with Clubhouse/Openhouse, we see talks, guest speakers, and seminars getting commoditized. We&amp;#39;re getting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-transcription&quot;&gt;AI Transcription&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio and Text have a very peculiar relationship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we had text messaging, we had phone calls. But before we had phones, we had mail. And before we wrote letters, we just talked to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio and Text seem to come in alternating waves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio Transcription has been around for a long time. I remember many years ago, TJ-Maxx would sell last-year&amp;#39;s Dragon speech recognition software in their discount software section (well, I guess the entire store is a discount section, so apologies for that redundant adjective). But they were pretty limited back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, AI transcription is getting good. And it&amp;#39;s available as an API via things like Temi, [[Otter]], Trint (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/wirecutter/reviews/best-transcription-services/&quot;&gt;see comparison&lt;/a&gt;). But it&amp;#39;s not that good though yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can get really good AI transcription, for cheap, then audio and text will blur in ways we haven&amp;#39;t seen previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re not there yet, but watch this trend. As GPT-3 has proven, when we start throwing lots of parameters (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GPT-3&quot;&gt;175+ billion&lt;/a&gt;) and money (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/MachineLearning/comments/hwfjej/d_the_cost_of_training_gpt3/&quot;&gt;millions of $&lt;/a&gt;) at a really really massive neural net, things start getting uncanny - or possibly, beyond uncanny (in the sense of crossing the uncanny chasm... err valley).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m no expert in AI, I barely understand what a neural network is (thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/machine-learning?&quot;&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;, the first mover in unbundling the university), but I know to follow this trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment we can get fast, highly-accurate automated transcription for cheap, the line between audio and text will blur so much that it&amp;#39;ll lead to innovations that are hard to predict. As is though, transcription seems to get something every sentence and that&amp;#39;s good, but not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phase change, when it comes, will come suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;podcasting&quot;&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have little to say about podcasting other than it is digitizing Radio for the AirPod generation. This has been a trend for years and is uninteresting because it&amp;#39;s so &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thepodcasthost.com/listening/podcast-industry-stats/&quot;&gt;huge already&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be uninteresting, but it&amp;#39;s hugely important. According to Infinite Dial, about 55% of Americans have listened to a podcast in 2020, up from 33% in 2015. The shift in behavior has tipped to the majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love how podcasting is based on RSS, an architecturally open technology - which Apple has supported for years. I love that openness. It&amp;#39;s contribute to the rapid growth and proliferation of podcasting - the barrier to entry is so low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monetizing it will be a pain. The fact that it sits on top of RSS, an architecturally open technology, makes it more frustrating for podcasters to get stats on their listeners, which means less potent ad targeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotify has made a big play on podcasts, we&amp;#39;ll see how that plays out for them. The key here is to build the world&amp;#39;s best podcast player (classic &lt;a href=&quot;https://stratechery.com/2019/spotifys-podcast-aggregation-play/&quot;&gt;Aggregation Theory at play&lt;/a&gt;) and get everyone to use that. Then, once you have the user&amp;#39;s identity and listening history, you can drop targeted ads for days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Spotify doesn&amp;#39;t have the best podcast player, and it will probably be pretty hard to get me to switch to them. So they&amp;#39;ve resorted to exclusive deals with big names. It didn&amp;#39;t work for Mixer when they signed Ninja. Maybe it will work for Spotify though? The moment the aggregate demand though, they win. To do so, I think they&amp;#39;ll need a Google-search level quantum leap in utility over the current podcast players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, apologies for the digression on Spotify. What I really want to point out is you&amp;#39;ve probably heard all those Clubhassholes say stuff like &amp;quot;Clubhouse has completely replaced podcasts for me&amp;quot;. I think that&amp;#39;s actually how podcasting fits into this greater narrative of audio explosion - it is the gateway behavior to newer audio experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you podcast, then you clubhouse, then we all become Joaquin Phoenix with an ever present audio-presence in our ear canals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-it-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping it up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio is exploding. You already knew that. But I hope you&amp;#39;ve gotten a better sense of &amp;quot;Why now?&amp;quot;, along with a few trends that might push us into explosive adoption of audio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcasting as a gateway behavior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AirPods and Fast Pair as the physical enabler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebRTC as the technological tectonic shift&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discord and Clubhouse as the first successful innovators on this frontier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and AI Transcription maturing into a new &amp;quot;tinker&amp;quot; vector for future mutations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petri dish is ripe for a combinatorial expansion of random ideas in audio 🧫🎧. Get excited!&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-08-09]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Internet Friends, Internet Cities]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-09</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-09</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-09">&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#39;m in the mood of making predictions. Predictions on the rise of Internet Friends and Internet Cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are fledgling ideas and there&amp;#39;s a strong chance that I&amp;#39;m saying nothing new. Additionally, this might be more wishful thinking than thoughtful analysis. But I found these thoughts interesting enough and I want to develop some of them a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a more personal side, this week wasn&amp;#39;t productive. That&amp;#39;s because I&amp;#39;m helping getting my parent&amp;#39;s house ready for a sale - lots of cleaning and staging. While exhausting and distracting, it yielded some unexpected psychic benefits. There&amp;#39;s something powerful about having a clean and beautiful living space. A physical manifestation of the ideas of [[Work Clean]] and &amp;quot;[[Fewer, more beautiful things]]&amp;quot; (an idea I haven&amp;#39;t yet explored, but certainly want to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And another tiny personal update. After a conversation with a friend, I&amp;#39;ve developed a renewed commitment to personal development. That starts with re-listening to &amp;quot;The Power of Now&amp;quot; on audiobook, which sort of feels similar to listening to a spiritual lecture or sermon. And to put things into practice, I&amp;#39;m also re-listening to &amp;quot;Atomic Habits&amp;quot;. More on both of these topics in the future, but it felt necessary to mention them (you know, for the accountability).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It&amp;#39;s funny, I own a lot of audiobooks (Audible subscriber), but I seem to listen to the same ones over and over...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, now that all of that is out of the way, my predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;internet-friends&quot;&gt;Internet Friends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve made a handful of [[Internet Friends]] in 2020. The more I use Twitter, the more internet friends I&amp;#39;ve made. But it&amp;#39;s not just Twitter, I&amp;#39;ve also found internet friends on [[IndieHackers]] and [[MakerLog]] and various invite only Discords/Group chats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more than I&amp;#39;ve ever made in all my previous years. In the past, I made practically all of my friends in the real world. I had a few Internet-only connections, but things like Discord and Zoom have changed the game. I used to know what people on the internet think like. Now, I know what they sound like. And what they laugh like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s obvious to say the future is going to be a whole lot more digital. But the second order effects on our social lives are going to be weird. Imagine a world in which half of your friends you&amp;#39;ve met in person and the other half online. (Which is a strange distinction - &amp;quot;in person&amp;quot; vs &amp;quot;online&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is important to consider because meeting people online is different. You can actually meet someone online for the first time without interacting with them at all. You can visit their profile and read up on how they want to present themselves. Or better yet, if they have a website, you can spend a moment immersed in their brain. All without ever meeting them. And they can do the same for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internet Friends are typically more aligned with you, in terms of how you think. In the past, location was king. Now, thoughts and values reign supreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fascinating wrinkle - you can have multiple identities. And none of them have to be associated with your face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trend is massively important to understand. It&amp;#39;s going to fundamentally shake our conception of what it means to be social and what it means to be friends. Right now, people sort of understand this. But the new tools that we&amp;#39;ve gotten recently (video chat via Zoom/Google Meets, audio discussion with voyeurism as a feature via Clubhouse/Discord) are changing the dynamics of how &amp;quot;close&amp;quot;, an Internet Friend can feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collectively, these tools are a disruptive innovation to friendship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let that sink in - Friendship is getting disrupted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience is worse in important ways (you can&amp;#39;t hug or high five or share food), but better in many others (meet people on the merit of thoughts and values, without restriction to geography).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means producing content (writing, videos, art, etc) is going to be hugely important. Your content is the new coffee chat - it replaces the first meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no game plan for what you need to do to position yourself for this change, but I believe building your own personal site is at the core. It&amp;#39;s highly related to the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;https://trends.vc/trends-0023-personal-brands/&quot;&gt;Personal Brands&lt;/a&gt; that Dru Riley explored, but in this case, it&amp;#39;s not about business. It&amp;#39;s more about being a person of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;internet-cities&quot;&gt;Internet Cities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I stumbled across &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bogleheads.org/AboutUs.php&quot;&gt;Bogleheads&lt;/a&gt; and it felt like visiting another world. From my internet spaceship (Firefox), I had touched down and landed on a strange planet, a place called Bogleheads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My visit was short, but it was fascinating to explore this backwater. For about 10 minutes, I immersed myself in a culture of responsible personal finance (Bogleheads take their name from John Bogle, the founder of Vanguard and champion of ETF &amp;quot;set it and forget it&amp;quot; type investing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bogleheads is an old community. It started in 1998 as a subcommunity of the MorningStar forums, and then in 2007 branched off to settle new territory. Those MorningStar Internet Pilgrims spun up phpBB and created a new town square dedicated to the creed of John Bogle. Over time, this little Internet City sprawled with more low-code tools, adding a wiki (mediaWiki), and a blog (WordPress). In 2020, it&amp;#39;s still a lively little city, but it certainly feels dated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take for example, a newer digital community like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiehackers.com/&quot;&gt;IndieHackers&lt;/a&gt;, which itself is entirely custom. Built on Firebase, IndieHackers is a new type of Internet City that doesn&amp;#39;t use off the shelf parts. Thus, it has its own distinctive feel - that&amp;#39;s reminiscent of Reddit or HackerNews, but altogether quite different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe we are about to see the founding of a great number of new [[Internet Cities]] over the next few years. Some may call them communities, but I think they&amp;#39;re closer to [[MMO RPG]]s, that will share similarities to cities. These &amp;quot;communities&amp;quot; will have job boards, and commerce, and events, and governance. You might pay a tax to the community (a membership fee, or a transaction fee on all commerce), or more likely, it will be sponsored by a corporation (in the way IndieHackers is today by Stripe). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the great digitization of our social and professional lives means that interest based Internet Cities are begging to be created. In the future, we&amp;#39;ll probably spend most of our time interacting in Internet Cities and Towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we already spend a ton of time on these Internet Cities. To me, Twitter feels like the Big City, Bogleheads feels like the a small town in the Midwest, and IndieHackers feels like a young Singapore. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know if this idea makes any sense to you, but I&amp;#39;m excited for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is going to be fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-08-02]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Authenticity, Two Energies, Multiple Discovery]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-02</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-02</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-02">&lt;p&gt;This week I had a ton of anxiety. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#39;t write about the root cause, yet I felt that it was important to recognize this, because A) it makes me feel better to do so and B)  if there&amp;#39;s something on my mind and I don&amp;#39;t write about it - well, that&amp;#39;s a bit inauthentic and these notes are supposed to be authentic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is a good segue into this week&amp;#39;s first topic - [[Authenticity]]. But before we do that, I&amp;#39;d like to update you that I have indeed conquered last week&amp;#39;s challenge. The [[Vue]] plugin for &lt;a href=&quot;https://feather.id/&quot;&gt;Feather&lt;/a&gt; is out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/feather-client-vue&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;authenticity&quot;&gt;Authenticity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being authentic on the internet is hard. When anyone can see what you&amp;#39;ve posted, you must proceed with some degree of caution. The fact that I started these notes by redacting the root cause of my anxiety is an example of me exercising that caution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Cancel culture&amp;quot; has revealed how simple it is to weaponize someone&amp;#39;s past comments against them on the internet. Anything you say can and will be used against. You have the right to remain silent. But [[cancel culture]] isn&amp;#39;t what I want to focus on today - maybe another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather, I want to talk about the inner challenge of being authentic online. The challenge of finding your voice in the face of fear - the fear of being perceived as &amp;quot;less than perfect&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us want to be [[perfect]] online. Not in the sense that we have no flaws, but more so that we want to invoke admiration in others. I want others to be like &amp;quot;oh man, I think Phil is great. He&amp;#39;s thoughtful, original, etc&amp;quot; and I suspect most others want something to that effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I&amp;#39;ve found is that aiming for perfection tends to lead to two outcomes: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your work becomes performative &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first case, you never publish, for fear of not being perfect. And in the second, your work sounds off - forced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Perell has an interesting take on this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are bad writers, but excellent text messagers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their writing is bad because they try to sound smart once they open Microsoft Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when they text, they write with clarity and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re stuck, write like you’re sending an important text message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/david_perell/status/1240836363190222848?s=20&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/david_perell/status/1240836363190222848?s=20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performative work is cringeworthy, even if the underlying work is valuable. It lacks voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is the solution to simply &amp;quot;write with voice&amp;quot;? I don&amp;#39;t think so. Voice isn&amp;#39;t something you turn on or off. Voice is nurtured, and not just by you, but by engaging with others. You reflect on your style, you evaluate what elements of your work you like, and what you don&amp;#39;t. You put it in front of others and you listen to what they say. Voice is a beautiful thing - if writing is a form of self expression, then writing with voice is prose that has expressed the self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem isn&amp;#39;t that someone has &amp;quot;voice&amp;quot; and simply needs to choose to use it. The problem is more that your voice needs to be nurtured. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, it&amp;#39;s a better goal to produce work that is interesting to yourself. With a low bar for quality. Giving yourself permission to write about what you want, without regard for how it&amp;#39;s perceived will give you wings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See, this is why I write these notes. This concept is half baked.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;two-energies&quot;&gt;Two Energies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I experienced a sharp turn in my energy levels. Monday and Tuesday were great. Then, something happened on Wednesday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ability to think abstract thoughts and generate any semblance of creative work left my brain. I felt like [[Cinderella]] when the clock struck 12, or that movie [[Limitless]] when the Adderall++ pills began to wear off. The magic faded away and thereafter, I was forced to welcome the reign of tiredness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This happens to me a lot. I seem to operate in two forms, one in which ideas and productivity comes naturally - and another in which everything is a struggle. I don&amp;#39;t drink caffeine, and maybe that&amp;#39;s part of my problem, but I find that these &amp;quot;two energies&amp;quot; and the transition between them feels a lot like the [[boom and bust]] cycle of the stock market. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The [[bull]] market run up to feeling good is rooted in strong personal [[wellness]] fundamentals (good sleep, exercise, diet, and psychological care), but as the good times roll on, those fundamentals slowly (or quickly) fall by the wayside. Things continue to go well, but a reckoning is awaiting. Lack of sleep. Burnout. Anxiety. A crash. The [[bear]] falls into a sudden hibernation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;#39;s kind of where I&amp;#39;m at right now. Wednesday was the bust in my boom and bust energy cycle, and the last few days, things went from bad to worse, and here I am trying to re-invest in the fundamentals to get myself firing on all cylinders again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;multiple-discovery&quot;&gt;Multiple Discovery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was going to publish these notes on Sunday, but because I didn&amp;#39;t get to it, I thought I&amp;#39;d throw in a bonus this morning (Monday 08-03).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One idea that popped up on my radar last week (a couple times) was the idea of [[multiple discovery]], or the idea that an invention or a discovery happens at the same time at different places in the world. We often cite Leibniz and Newton discovering Calculus or Wallace and Darwin discovering Evolution as stories of when this occurs in science. Of course, the list of this is enormous:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_multiple_discoveries&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_multiple_discoveries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a similar phenomenon in Hollywood, called &amp;quot;Twin films&amp;quot;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twin_films&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twin_films&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s not just Hollywood and Science - this happens ALL the time in business. From billionaire entrepreneurs who both happen to have side businesses that produce rockets (Bezos/Musk) to your average SaaS product that has dozens of competitors, multiple discovery is a very human thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why does this happen in so many disciplines? One might be tempted to say that we&amp;#39;re less original than we think we are - and I think that would be 100% correct. But it goes a little further than that. I hypothesize there are a LIMITED set of things that CAN be discovered/invented/built at any given point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have zero experience in science and film so I&amp;#39;ll refrain from making any generalizations there. But I believe that when it comes to business, there are a limited number of solutions that the market is able to accept at any given moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It depends on the skills of the consumers (do they know how to use Smartphones, do they know how to type on a keyboard?) and the taste of the market. There&amp;#39;s an element of fashion to business, and I wish we&amp;#39;d understand that better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So on the consumer side, there are a limited number of things they will respond positively to. And on the entrepreneur side, people have extremely similar information diets. So the space of &amp;quot;valid ideas&amp;quot; is actually very small, leading to plenty of collisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I tweeted out this idea: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That idea you have? There&amp;#39;s pretty much a 100% chance someone else has the exact same one and is executing on it TODAY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pliao39/status/1288900847309664256?s=20&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/pliao39/status/1288900847309664256?s=20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I believe that we now live in a world that&amp;#39;s going to become ultra competitive. Get used to it. In a world with billions of humans, all coming online, multiple discovery will be the norm in everything (if it wasn&amp;#39;t already).&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-07-26]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Work Clean, Learning and Drowning, Questions]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-07-26</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-07-26</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://philipliao.com/weekly_notes/2020-07-26">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m trying something new. After a conversation with a friend on Tuesday, I&amp;#39;ve decided that my inability to stick with a &amp;quot;Weekly Reflection&amp;quot; routine has simply because I lacked accountability. Combined with my desire to perform &amp;quot;post processing&amp;quot; on my Roam Notes (which itself is a [[forcing function]] to take better Roam Notes), I&amp;#39;m publishing a set of notes from each week. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;#39;re not meant to be read weekly, but I&amp;#39;ve got to tidy up my thoughts somehow. This is that somehow. Future posts and essays will likely have their origins in these weekly notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the backlinks don&amp;#39;t go anywhere for now. I&amp;#39;m using &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsidian.md&quot;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt; to write these markdown notes, and there&amp;#39;s utility for me to add them. One day, I might build a UI in which readers can jump between these links and explore them - semi-Roam style. In other words, these links are purely for my benefit, but one day, they might be more useful to you, the reader, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that sense, those broken backlinks are a metaphor for these weekly notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;work-clean&quot;&gt;Work Clean!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I was struck by how important it is to [[Work Clean]]. Every morning I spend so much time rearranging my workspace by wrangling in a cacophony of browser tabs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who has tried Mari Kondo&amp;#39;s [[Spark Joy]], you know that sentimental items are hard to toss. And in a way, I form sentimental attachments to tabs I have opened, but haven&amp;#39;t read. Each of those tabs feels like it has life-changing potential - and that makes them plausibly valuable. I&amp;#39;m excited to read them, perhaps primed by some form of [[social proof]] in the form of a Tweet, or a large number of upvotes on [[HackerNews]], yet I never asked myself, &amp;quot;Is this really worth reading?&amp;quot;. In other words, I don&amp;#39;t do the important work of [[pre-reading]]. But I should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thus, every morning, I start in the red. I clean up after the previous day&amp;#39;s irresponsibility - of spawning browser tabs filled with potential, but no certain value. And this clean up is draining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what&amp;#39;s worse is if I don&amp;#39;t clean up. My computer begins to run hot, its fans spinning ever faster as it attempts to dissipate heat, and emitting the sound of exhaustion - its version of panting. And those tabs that my computer is working to maintain, those tabs are black holes for productivity. If I accidentally open one, or see a certain tab, then my brain begins a subconscious context switch, which I have to interrupt, and refocus. That costs mental energy. And if I don&amp;#39;t interrupt, well I&amp;#39;m jumping down a 10 minute or so rabbit hole of distraction, thinking about a random topic I had no intention of exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heat from my computer, the torrent of air emitted by its fan, and the context switches from seeing an unwanted browser tab slowly brings my productivity to a crawl. It&amp;#39;s a death by a thousand papercuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes, it&amp;#39;s better to clean up every morning. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But would be better to work clean. Mise en place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-and-drowning&quot;&gt;Learning and Drowning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been struck by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZtfTOuSHGg8&quot;&gt;Michael Siebel&amp;#39;s observation&lt;/a&gt; that successful startup founders are [[formidable]]. Essentially, a person is formidable if they are able to accomplish exactly what they set out to accomplish. &amp;quot;I will sign 10 customers this week&amp;quot; and then go out and do that very daunting task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formidable people are forces to be reckoned with. Because they find ways to consistently push themselves and operate at the edge of what is possible, they become super human. But, I believe this is an outsider&amp;#39;s view of a successful, productive person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inside view of a formidable person is actually the development of [[confidence]] and [[self-esteem]], bordering into arrogance and over-confidence, but not quite. And while I will talk a lot more about self-esteem in the future, I want to touch briefly about the origins of confidence and self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-esteem comes from a place of believing &amp;quot;I am worthy&amp;quot;, regardless of how much I fail or how much society hates me. You must give yourself permission to be. Simply to be. &amp;quot;I am who I am and I am worthy&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For young people, this can come from your parents. I recall [[Kobe]] saying in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WY0wONSarXA&quot;&gt;an interview&lt;/a&gt;, that his father did exactly that. He was 10 or 11 at the time and went to a summer camp, playing against other 10 or 11 year olds, and where his father and uncle had played in their youth and done well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Kobe scored 0 points, the entire summer. His quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I scored, not a free throw, nothing - not a lucky shot, not a breakaway layup. Zero points. And I remember crying about it and being upset about it, and my father gives me a hug and says, &amp;quot;Listen, whether you score 0 or you score 60, I&amp;#39;m gonna love you no matter what.&amp;quot; Now that is the most important thing you can say to a child. Because from there I was like &amp;quot;okay&amp;quot;, that gives me all the confidence in the world to fail. I have the security there. But to hell with that, I&amp;#39;m scoring 60. Let&amp;#39;s go. From there, I just went to work.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what&amp;#39;s amazing about this is those words from Kobe&amp;#39;s father gave him that sense of self worth. To become formidable you need a bedrock of love, that safety net to fail and still be worthy of love. Young people get it from their parents and others. Older people must learn to build that sense of self appreciation themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kobe was formidable, but had his father not been there for him, who knows what if we would associate the name Kobe with basketball royalty or a type of beef (after which Kobe was named). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so this is a long winded way to make a point about Learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I was learning [[Vue]] and made great initial progress. In 7 days, I went from complete noob to a working component that did exactly what I wanted it to do. And then I hit a massive roadblock. I was at the point of packaging my work and putting it on npm as a Vue plugin, and suddenly my momentum crashed as I was stonewalled by an unmoveable object. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, it felt like drowning out at sea. All that confidence and momentum was gone. Now, I have to build up my knowledge of bundling (which I have almost none of, because that&amp;#39;s almost always abstracted away from me) and slowly piece together the puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And right now, I certainly don&amp;#39;t feel formidable. In fact, I feel the complete opposite - incompetent. It&amp;#39;s in this very moment, where this practice of weekly reflection comes in - I&amp;#39;m practicing self appreciation and a giving myself that foundation of worthiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sensation of drowning, of spending an entire summer and scoring 0 points, of spending days on an npm packaging problem with no results, will test your confidence. But to fall back onto a belief that &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m worthy of being me, failures and all&amp;quot; - well that, as Kobe said &amp;quot;gives you all the confidence in the world&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon that safety-net of self belief and appreciation, I&amp;#39;m gonna get this Vue package out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark my words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always been a somewhat curious person, but I think I&amp;#39;ve relied on my natural curiosity and haven&amp;#39;t developed an intentional &amp;quot;question practice&amp;quot;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions are extremely important. They have a way of priming the mind and sharpening focus. They can be used as an attack (i.e. &amp;quot;What do you mean?&amp;quot;). They can reframe a problem (i.e. &amp;quot;What if&amp;quot;). They can be used to challenge assumptions (i.e. &amp;quot;Why do we believe this?&amp;quot;). Questions change the tone. Questions break you out of your normal thinking patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On HackerNews, there was a post this week titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.anup.io/2020/07/20/invert-always-invert/&quot;&gt;Invert, Always Invert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core idea is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the problem - what are you trying to achieve?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invert it - what would guarantee failure?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, consider solutions to avoid this failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s funny how powerful this can be. Thinking of the same problem from the opposite perspective. Hiking the same trail looks different on the return trip - inversion makes the familiar feel new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good questions activate the mind. A new friend of mine (the one who prompted these weekly_notes) asked me &amp;quot;What was the one thing at Uber that you were most excited about or passionate working on?&amp;quot; and it was a good question because I honestly couldn&amp;#39;t answer it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work wasn&amp;#39;t done for passion or purpose, but pragmatism. And perhaps that&amp;#39;s why I&amp;#39;m doing what I&amp;#39;m doing now. Writing^1 and building as a way to make sense of the world - flailing (ahem, writing and building) my way to passion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;^1 - (&lt;a href=&quot;https://softwarementor.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Software Mentor&lt;/a&gt;, and now these weekly notes, to go along with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacetime.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Spacetime Newsletter&lt;/a&gt; which is basically just a public journal of what Nick and I are building) &lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[software-engineering-interview-prep]]></title><description><![CDATA[A list of resources to help you prepare for software engineering interviews. There are links to questions and tips]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/software-engineering-interview-prep</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/software-engineering-interview-prep</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 15:20:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[how-to-type-faster]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is how I learned to type faster (from 65 WPM to 100 WPM). From touch typing (not looking at the keyboard), to speed drills, and finally getting results on TypeRacer]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/how-to-type-faster</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/how-to-type-faster</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2020 17:14:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[becoming-a-blockchain-developer]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is my learning plan to become a blockchain developer. Updated frequently with resources and articles]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/becoming-a-blockchain-developer</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/becoming-a-blockchain-developer</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 02:33:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[uniswap-and-participatory-equity]]></title><description><![CDATA[Uniswap shows us what it looks like to reward users with equity]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/uniswap-and-participatory-equity</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/uniswap-and-participatory-equity</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 02:07:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[how-to-yield-farm]]></title><description><![CDATA[Yield farming might not be as profitable as it was earlier this year, but if you're curious about this opportunity in DeFi, read this guide.]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/how-to-yield-farm</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/how-to-yield-farm</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 20:38:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[writing-day-30-of-30]]></title><description><![CDATA[I'm finally done with my 30 day writing challenge! Here's my immediate reflection of how it went]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/writing-day-30-of-30</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/writing-day-30-of-30</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 04:25:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[rent-free-in-your-head]]></title><description><![CDATA[How do we evict, or at least manage, ideas that live rent free in our heads?]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/rent-free-in-your-head</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/rent-free-in-your-head</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 04:43:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[minor-feelings-quotes]]></title><description><![CDATA[A collection of quotes from the book "Minor Feelings" - and some minor commentary]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/minor-feelings-quotes</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/minor-feelings-quotes</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 01:46:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[in-my-minor-feelings]]></title><description><![CDATA[Reacting to "Minor Feelings" by Cathy Park Hong]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/in-my-minor-feelings</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/in-my-minor-feelings</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 21:51:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[latent-value]]></title><description><![CDATA[Sometimes, we succeed because of seemingly unwise or strange decisions we made in the past]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/latent-value</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/latent-value</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 02:55:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[meditation-day-11]]></title><description><![CDATA[I started Naval's 60 x 60 meditation challenge. Did a quick check in for day 11]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/meditation-day-11</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/meditation-day-11</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 19:17:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[simple-algorithms-and-exponents]]></title><description><![CDATA[What do Bitcoin, TCP, and retries have in common? They all employ some simple form of exponential growth (or decay) in their operations.]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/simple-algorithms-and-exponents</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/simple-algorithms-and-exponents</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 17:04:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[implementing-advice]]></title><description><![CDATA[Psychologists say we only learn when we change our behavior. So how can we implement advice such that it really changes behavior? ]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/implementing-advice</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/implementing-advice</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 05:47:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[getting-into-flow]]></title><description><![CDATA[Yesterday and today could not have been more different - and the difference was flow. Here's what helped me get into flow today. ]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/getting-into-flow</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/getting-into-flow</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 03:59:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[typeracer-4000]]></title><description><![CDATA[I just finished my 4000th typeracer competition. Time to reflect]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/typeracer-4000</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/typeracer-4000</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 23:02:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[writing-day-20-of-30]]></title><description><![CDATA[Day 20/30 of my writing challenge. Some additional reflections]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/writing-day-20-of-30</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/writing-day-20-of-30</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:25:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[halloween-2020]]></title><description><![CDATA[If we left out a bin of candy, with guidance to take only 3 pieces, what would happen? Well, the obvious happened]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/halloween-2020</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/halloween-2020</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 03:47:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[legibility-and-software]]></title><description><![CDATA[Legibility is simplicity, but not all simplicity is good. Where do we have opportunities to introduce "good" legibility into our systems?]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/legibility-and-software</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/legibility-and-software</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 19:17:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[feynman-and-dumb-questions]]></title><description><![CDATA[Richard Feynman used to ask some pretty dumb questions. Here's what we can learn from him]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/feynman-and-dumb-questions</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/feynman-and-dumb-questions</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 20:46:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[ddia-glossary]]></title><description><![CDATA[A glossary of "hard to remember" terms from Designing Data Intensive Applications]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/ddia-glossary</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/ddia-glossary</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 04:38:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[168-hours]]></title><description><![CDATA[I started tracking my time in 15 minute intervals. This is what my practice looks like]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/168-hours</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/168-hours</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 03:33:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[postman-on-technology]]></title><description><![CDATA[Neil Postman warns us that technology is disruptive - not of industries, but of our culture and our wisdom. My notes from his talk in 1998]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/postman-on-technology</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/postman-on-technology</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 04:27:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[two-energies]]></title><description><![CDATA[Sometimes, I've got a lot of energy. Othertimes, nothing. They connect together like booms and busts of the stock market]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/two-energies</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/two-energies</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 03:44:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[notes-on-waitzkin-at-sohn]]></title><description><![CDATA[In an interview, Josh Waitzkin shares some wisdom about learning and life. Here are some notes and takeaways]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/notes-on-waitzkin-at-sohn</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/notes-on-waitzkin-at-sohn</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 05:40:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[good-meeting]]></title><description><![CDATA[I'm weird. I love meetings. Here are my tips for having good ones]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/good-meeting</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/good-meeting</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 02:48:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[writing-day-10-of-30]]></title><description><![CDATA[Today is day 10 of my 30 day writing challenge. Some reflections]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/writing-day-10-of-30</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/writing-day-10-of-30</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 23:56:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[metawork]]></title><description><![CDATA[All things are created twice. Do the metawork so the real work gets done right]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/metawork</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/metawork</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 04:18:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[good-teammates]]></title><description><![CDATA[Working on a good team is a joyful. Over the years, here are a few patterns I have seen in good teammates]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/good-teammates</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/good-teammates</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 18:30:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[where-are-you-from]]></title><description><![CDATA[My thoughts on the question "Where are you from?"]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/where-are-you-from</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/where-are-you-from</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 22:34:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[subconscious-emotional-memories]]></title><description><![CDATA[Our brains form emotional memories that are inaccessible to our conscious minds]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/subconscious-emotional-memories</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/subconscious-emotional-memories</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 23:18:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[start-where-you-are]]></title><description><![CDATA[Making a change? Here's a lesson from Anthony Davis: Start where you are. Use what you have. Do what you can]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/start-where-you-are</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/start-where-you-are</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 20:23:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[writing-as-input]]></title><description><![CDATA[Day 3 of my 30 day writing challenge, and I'm making a shift in how I think about the pieces I write]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/writing-as-input</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/writing-as-input</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 17:15:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[combinatorial-networking]]></title><description><![CDATA[According to LinkedIn, most of us have 50,000 second degree connections. Here's a thought on how to meet more of them]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/combinatorial-networking</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/combinatorial-networking</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 23:14:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[talking-to-yourself]]></title><description><![CDATA[Writing online can be scary. If you're freezing up, here's a tip to make it more approachable]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/talking-to-yourself</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/talking-to-yourself</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 23:00:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[30-days]]></title><description><![CDATA[What can you do in 30 days? It turns out - quite a lot. Here are some stories of people who catalyzed big changes with 30 day challenges]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/30-days</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/30-days</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 18:40:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[airpods]]></title><description><![CDATA[Some lessons from AirPods: small delights, naming matters, real life virality]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/airpods</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/airpods</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 01:08:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[itchier]]></title><description><![CDATA[Should you "scratch your own itch" before validating the market?]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/itchier</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/itchier</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 20:40:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[idea-to-product-hunt-launch]]></title><description><![CDATA[Built a "throwaway project" to get a feel for launching on ProductHunt]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/idea-to-product-hunt-launch</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/idea-to-product-hunt-launch</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 21:58:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[job-search]]></title><description><![CDATA[The story of how I landed at Uber. At a glance: 65 days, 18 companies, 9 onsites, 3 offers. Lots of details for job seekers]]></description><link>https://philipliao.com/job-search</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://philipliao.com/job-search</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 06:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>