<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[@pliao39]]></title><description><![CDATA[Phil's home on the internet]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com</link><image><url>https://pliao39.com/phil.jpg</url><title>@pliao39</title><link>https://pliao39.com</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:36:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pliao39.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[2020-10-06]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Goodbye Feather, Hello Dallas, Miscellaneous]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-10-06</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-10-06</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-10-06">&lt;p&gt;Hey friends,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m converting my notes into a newsletter. I&amp;#39;ve enjoyed writing these notes, but distributing them has been a pain. Twitter&amp;#39;s not the right distribution medium. RSS is cool (and I added &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/rss.xml&quot;&gt;a feed&lt;/a&gt;!), but I like the &amp;quot;idea of RSS&amp;quot; more than actually using RSS - and I suspect that&amp;#39;s true for most people as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only good option is a newsletter. I thought about Substack, which I&amp;#39;ve used in the past (exhibit &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacetime.substack.com/&quot;&gt;A&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://softwarementor.substack.com&quot;&gt;B&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofshipping.substack.com&quot;&gt;C&lt;/a&gt;), but Substack newsletters feel too professional these days and I&amp;#39;m not trying to work for the Passion Economy™ here. I gave TinyLetter a look and the price was right, but the vibe was not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, I turned to Buttondown, a product I&amp;#39;ve been secretly admiring for almost a year. It&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://jmduke.com/&quot;&gt;Indie built&lt;/a&gt; and has strong positioning against Substack (more customizable and dev friendly 😍), Mailchimp (cheaper 💸), and TinyLetter (it&amp;#39;s just better 💪).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, welcome to &lt;a href=&quot;https://buttondown.email/pliao39&quot;&gt;my Buttondown&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has changed in the past few weeks so let&amp;#39;s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;goodbye-feather&quot;&gt;Goodbye Feather&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest change is that Nick and I have decided to pause all work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://feather.id/&quot;&gt;Feather&lt;/a&gt;. While I still believe there is an opportunity for someone to come in and make a lot of noise in the Auth space with a bottoms up approach, we&amp;#39;re pretty sure it won&amp;#39;t be us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A startup &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=424495&quot;&gt;runs on morale&lt;/a&gt; and when it comes to Auth - my tank is empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a lot to be learned here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don&amp;#39;t scratch your own itch unless you&amp;#39;ve previously paid for a similar product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a healthy ratio of talking to customers and building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;launch earlier &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://versoly.com/founder-bingo&quot;&gt;Classic founder mistakes&lt;/a&gt;, but perhaps the biggest problem was &amp;quot;Why?&amp;quot;. Not in the sense, &amp;quot;Why is this a good idea&amp;quot;, but rather &amp;quot;Why are YOU working on it?&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was I enthusiastic and passionate about Auth? Was I sufficiently motivated or even angry? No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;#39;t love an idea, aren&amp;#39;t obsessed about it, aren&amp;#39;t staying up late thinking about the customer pain point, then don&amp;#39;t pursue it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all future ideas, I now realize the entire early team needs to be &lt;em&gt;wildly&lt;/em&gt; enthusiastic. Even if the market is amazing, you&amp;#39;ll need to grind it out, and it makes it that much more likely you&amp;#39;ll persevere if your heart is in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hello-dallas&quot;&gt;Hello Dallas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other big change is that I&amp;#39;m currently in Dallas. My parents closed on a new house, and I&amp;#39;m up here &amp;quot;house sitting&amp;quot; as they try to sell their old house back in Houston (btw - got any tips for selling a house? We&amp;#39;re in need of your wisdom!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s taken me pretty much an entire week to adjust to living by myself again. Food has been an adjustment. Loneliness has been an adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this adjustment has been great. Uncomfortable but great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cold showers, quitting a job cold turkey to strike out on your own, solo travel, taking the road less traveled by, &lt;a href=&quot;https://breakingsmart.substack.com/p/against-waldenponding&quot;&gt;Waldenponding™&lt;/a&gt; and &amp;quot;Into the Wild&amp;quot;ing - these are all examples where you dive into something uncomfortable and find yourself literally or figuratively fighting for breath. Slowly, you regain some control. Dormant muscles get reactivated - and it reminds you who you truly are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know what I&amp;#39;m trying to say here. It&amp;#39;s probably something about risk, identity, self-reliance, and nature - but there&amp;#39;s no point I&amp;#39;m making, just an observation that I&amp;#39;m feeling good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7 Powers: The Foundations of Business Strategy&lt;/strong&gt; -  I just finished up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/7-Powers-Foundations-Business-Strategy-ebook/dp/B01MRLFFQ7&quot;&gt;this book&lt;/a&gt; (it&amp;#39;s quite short), but I feel like it&amp;#39;s beginning to stitch together some ideas that I had previously known as discrete pieces of information (i.e. Innovator&amp;#39;s Dilemma, Switching Costs, Network Effects, etc). Now, they sit together in a more coherent whole (the path to creating a strategic business moat). I&amp;#39;m trying to distill my knowledge of business strategy into action and I plan to do that by writing amateur equity research in the future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Fortune Cookie Chronicles&lt;/strong&gt; - This is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Fortune-Cookie-Chronicles-Adventures-Chinese-ebook/dp/B0010SKUOW&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on the history of Chinese food in America. I&amp;#39;m a few chapters in and I&amp;#39;m a fan. If you know anything about my stance on Americanized Chinese food, you know it&amp;#39;s not positive. I hate Panda Express (only the Tofu is worth ordering). I eat Orange Chicken, General Tso&amp;#39;s Chicken, and other candied meat with reluctance. There&amp;#39;s nothing Chinese about this food. Reading the book largely confirms what I already know, but the stories are significantly more entrepreneurial than I imagined. It&amp;#39;s a solid read. After I digest this book, I bet I&amp;#39;ll have a lot more to say on Chinese Food in general - to me, it&amp;#39;s a deep symbol for the Chinese experience in America.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Boron Letters&lt;/strong&gt; - one part &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0367279/&quot;&gt;Arrested Development&lt;/a&gt;, one part copywriting masterclass, and one part self help book - this has got to be one of the more interesting ways to learn entrepreneurship fundamentals and the basics of copywriting. It&amp;#39;s a collection of letters written by the legendary copywriter Gary Halbert to his son - while serving time in prison. I&amp;#39;ll do a reaction to this book soon - it&amp;#39;s great. This week&amp;#39;s thread of self reliance is rooted in some of the advice given from father to son&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-09-29]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Book Reviews, Writing and Coding, Enabling Environments]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-29</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-29</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-29">&lt;p&gt;I missed last week and got delayed this week. But the notes keep coming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;book-reviews&quot;&gt;Book Reviews&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main update since my last batch of notes (as it pertains to this website) is that I published &lt;a href=&quot;/books/how-to-take-smart-notes&quot;&gt;my review/summary of How to Take Smart Notes&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m excited about that for a couple reasons: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I enjoy learning about the process of learning and intend to explore this topic further. It&amp;#39;s great to have a milestone to look back upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Book reviews are an excellent &amp;quot;attack vector&amp;quot; into a topic. I&amp;#39;ve always thought about how Vitalik Buterin was &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoinmagazine.com/authors/vitalik-buterin&quot;&gt;first a journalist&lt;/a&gt; in crypto before creating Ethereum. I love this concept of being an archaeologist/anthropologist/researcher of a domain before entering. It gives you credibility and deepens your awareness of the space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s all to say, expect more book reviews. They&amp;#39;re basically &amp;quot;admissions tickets&amp;quot; into any topic of your choosing. They provide the cover fire to enter a new world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-and-coding&quot;&gt;Writing and Coding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval/status/1002106893265920000?s=20&quot;&gt;Naval identified&lt;/a&gt; that media and code are two assets anyone can produce, yet can reach massive audiences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code and media are permissionless leverage. They&amp;#39;re the leverage behind the newly rich. You can create software and media that works for you while you sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if writing forces you to get your ideas into a presentable state, then - as &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Conaw/status/1206037537589850119?s=20&quot;&gt;@conaw observed&lt;/a&gt; - coding takes it a step further:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code is crystallized thought&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really love these similarities between code and writing, but there&amp;#39;s one dimension in which I wish they were more similar: testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With software, you can constantly test your work. The work itself might be more unforgiving - not a single character can be incorrect - but the speed at which you get feedback is unparalleled. With code, you can set up an environment in which you get feedback every time you save a file. And this feedback can execute in seconds, or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With writing, every time a change is made, we have to read our work. We must switch from a writer&amp;#39;s mindset to a reader&amp;#39;s - just to see if what we&amp;#39;ve created makes any sense at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do unit/integration tests give you faster feedback to see if your code works, it allows you to &amp;quot;refactor&amp;quot; or tighten up working code such that the same ideas can be expressed more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no such thing for writing - and thus, the feedback cycles are just so much slower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s not much of a point here - other than to say I wish there was a way we could get faster feedback on our writing...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;enabling-environments&quot;&gt;Enabling Environments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;#39;ve been in a state of &amp;quot;funemployment&amp;quot; for almost 9 months. &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacetime.substack.com/p/1-categories&quot;&gt;Initially&lt;/a&gt;, the goal was to travel and build SpaceTime, but those plans quickly got derailed. Since then, I&amp;#39;ve worked on a variety of random projects: &lt;a href=&quot;https://softwarementor.substack.com&quot;&gt;Software Mentor&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofshipping.com&quot;&gt;Summer of Shipping&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://feather.id&quot;&gt;Feather&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve learned a lot during that time. But I&amp;#39;m not sure I maximized my learning - and the reason for this is that I haven&amp;#39;t quite constructed an environment which provides both sufficient feedback,  motivation, and a rate of iteration that makes it all work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m trying to fix that with my future initiatives - the first of which is to grow this website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when it comes to choosing content, I plan to let growth be my initial guide. I believe growth is key to feedback, which in turn unlocks an &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.andymatuschak.org/Enabling_environment&quot;&gt;Enabling Environments&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, this was the subject of the example I presented in my &amp;quot;How to Take Smart Notes&amp;quot; review: why &amp;quot;looking for growth&amp;quot; seemed to be common career advice. The idea that personal growth is correlated to product growth &amp;quot;sounds about right&amp;quot;, but it&amp;#39;s hard to figure out what action you should take about it. The advice of finding a set of things that can grow fast, and then picking your favorite among that set, is a very useful framing. While I don&amp;#39;t plan to follow that exactly (in fact, I&amp;#39;m doing the opposite - I&amp;#39;m restricting topics by my personal interest first, and then focusing on growth), it&amp;#39;s useful to recognize the importance of growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a bit of rambling, but in sum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to create an enabling environment for myself, which I believe needs product growth. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe this website can be such an environment, if it grows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus, I intend to grow this website by first being open about the topics I explore, and then doubling down on whatever works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will report back if this works. I&amp;#39;m sure there are tons of little details I&amp;#39;ll need to overcome to make this happen.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-09-13]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Attention, How to Take Smart Notes, Portability, Miscellaneous]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-13</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-13</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-13">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, my day started with errands. They say you have to win the morning to win the day, and I found that to be true, just in reverse. I lost the morning, and I certainly lost the day.  But otherwise, it was a good week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; In fact, I feel like I had a great week in terms of notes. Some highlights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;attention&quot;&gt;Attention&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On HackerNews, the article &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24391686&quot;&gt;Attention is your scarcest resource&lt;/a&gt; made its rounds last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key quote from the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“50%+ focus” is roughly when something becomes the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/top.html&quot;&gt;top idea in your mind&lt;/a&gt;. It’s when you start caring enough to think about it in the shower. It’s when you start habitually asking “how could this go faster?” It’s when you get &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/relres.html&quot;&gt;relentlessly resourceful&lt;/a&gt;. It’s around when you start &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benkuhn.net/impatient/&quot;&gt;annoying your coworkers and/or significant other&lt;/a&gt;, although that part is avoidable with practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having one top idea in your mind (itself, an essay from Paul Graham) is extremely powerful. Anecdotally, it seems that my teammates&amp;#39; best ideas emerge spontaneously, and outside of work. One day, we&amp;#39;ll show up to work in the morning and they&amp;#39;ll tell me &amp;quot;Hey, had this idea, what if we...&amp;quot;- and suddenly we&amp;#39;re on a new trajectory. Personally, I come up with a lot of my best ideas in the early morning, or after working up a sweat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attention is scarce, and we all understand how constant context switching can kill productivity. But there&amp;#39;s another cost to splintering your attention - an opportunity cost of sorts. Our brains run a variety of processes, of which we&amp;#39;re only conscious of &amp;quot;linear thinking&amp;quot;. When it comes to problem solving and searching for creative solutions, our subconscious brain, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/lecture/learning-how-to-learn/introduction-to-the-focused-and-diffuse-modes-75EsZ&quot;&gt;diffuse mode&lt;/a&gt; of thinking, needs to be activated too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#39;t seen any instructions on how to activate this creative, diffuse mode of &amp;quot;connecting the dots&amp;quot; - but I believe that curiosity is necessary. If you only keep deeply &lt;a href=&quot;weekly_notes/2020-07-26#questions&quot;&gt;interesting questions&lt;/a&gt; in your mind, you stand a chance. But, there&amp;#39;s clearly a limit to the number of interesting questions we can load into our brains. 1,000 is too many. But what about 2? Can our diffuse modes consider even 2 simultaneous questions? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not so sure. I believe we must focus on one thing at a time. On any given day - focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-take-smart-notes&quot;&gt;How to Take Smart Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started reading, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Take-Smart-Notes-Nonfiction-ebook/dp/B06WVYW33Y&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;How to Take Smart Notes&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;m not entirely sure how I ended up buying it, but it popped up on my radar enough times to warrant a look (likely the #roamcult). When a few smart people start recommending the same thing, that&amp;#39;s a good sign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, I&amp;#39;m about halfway through the book and I&amp;#39;m convinced it will change my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s why: this book will change the way you read and learn. When it comes to knowledge, most people are living paycheck to paycheck - we are as smart as the most recent stuff we&amp;#39;ve read. This book presents a system that allows us to create a knowledge bank that can accrue learning AND compound in value. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools like Roam and Obsidian facilitate this system. But the tool is insufficient, you must learn the procedure of how to maintain your ever growing web of knowledge. Simply having a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memex&quot;&gt;memex&lt;/a&gt; is not enough. How you manage it is everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll be summarizing/reviewing this book soon - its lessons are hard to put into practice. But I believe that those who do will reap benefits that are hard to imagine. After all, the human brain isn&amp;#39;t very good at intuiting exponential growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;portability&quot;&gt;Portability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea came up in the context of the term &amp;quot;digital sharecropping&amp;quot; - or the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/skmurphy/status/1304955612384485376?s=20&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;investing in a platform you don&amp;#39;t own&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;. It happens in the context of &amp;quot;user generated content&amp;quot;, but also when building a business on top of another platform which might shut down at any moment (i.e. Facebook games, Twitter API). Or the platform might just shut &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; down (i.e. via a cease and desist or &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourincrediblejourney.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Acquihire&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is also interesting as it relates to the careers of software engineers. Compare, as an exercise, a software engineer to a salesperson. The salesperson gains skills at a company, learns a process, but most importantly, builds up a rolodex of people that work at other companies. By doing deals with a lot of different people, they accumulate a network that grows more valuable every month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast this to the software engineer. The engineer gains skills, learns processes, but in contrast, builds up a resume of commits that are only visible within the company. Sure, the engineer may develop relationships with people, but there&amp;#39;s a limit to the number of &amp;quot;career changing connections&amp;quot; they make as mere a byproduct of their job. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider internal transfers vs external hires. With transfers, we can look at someone&amp;#39;s commits and see their work product. We do half the number of interviews we normally would for an outside hire, and the process is greatly relaxed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, software engineers get paid a good amount (especially early in their careers), but they need to realize that there&amp;#39;s limited liquidity to their skills. Outside of the knowledge you gain and a title bump, there&amp;#39;s very little you can take with you (and even then, the title bump might not be respected by a new employer). You can&amp;#39;t always take your domain expertise. You can&amp;#39;t take your commits (which you can use to reference previous best practices).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will you work at the same company forever? If you suspect the answer is no, then you&amp;#39;ll likely need to change some of your habits. Invest in transferable technical skills (focus less time on company specific excellence and more on general excellence). Write on the internet, use social media, do open source - build yourself a bit of a reputation. Invest in portability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;False Dichotomies&lt;/strong&gt; - I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about ways in which the world is not black or white. Not enough here to share an idea, but consider these constructs: &amp;quot;Architect vs Gardener&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Bootstrap or VC&amp;quot;. To me, they&amp;#39;re all false dichotomies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep&lt;/strong&gt; - my sleep this last week has improved 🙌. Or at the very least, I&amp;#39;ve used melatonin and orange tinted, blue light blocking glasses to adjust my sleep schedule to about Midnight to ~8AM. Not sure if my sleep has improved, but productivity has seen a small boost!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rewire your Anxious Brain&lt;/strong&gt; - another book that I&amp;#39;m reading that I think has useful applications to my life. I&amp;#39;ve always found truth in the idea that &amp;quot;what we need to do is often what we fear the most&amp;quot; But I&amp;#39;ve never had a good strategy for dealing with it. This book doesn&amp;#39;t solve the psychological, but it does help you understand the neuroscience behind why you can&amp;#39;t &amp;quot;think your way&amp;quot; past anxiety, and you need different tools for this rewiring 🧠. Will do a summary/review of it soon-ish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-09-06]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Meme Marketing, Open Source Business Models, Miscellaneous]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-06</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-06</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-09-06">&lt;p&gt;After a week off, I’m back. And there’s a ton of stuff to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;meme-marketing&quot;&gt;Meme Marketing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic emerged from a conversation with my friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ChalupaBatmanGG&quot;&gt;David Park&lt;/a&gt;. David’s company, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kippoapp.com/&quot;&gt;Kippo&lt;/a&gt;, is a dating app for gamers. And while there’s much to talk about regarding the &lt;a href=&quot;/weekly_notes/2020-08-09#internet-friends&quot;&gt;digitization of dating and social interaction&lt;/a&gt;, the company’s early growth strategy is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lennysan/status/1252324468002713600?s=20&quot;&gt;Lenny Rachitsky asked on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer app founders: How did you get your first 2,000 users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ChalupaBatmanGG/status/1252359322329157638?s=20&quot;&gt;David responded&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a meme with a footer to our website. Made it to the front page with 52k upvotes. Free impressions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally got a chance to catch up with David last week and had to ask him about it. Here&amp;#39;s a brief summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(One day, we&amp;#39;ll need to get David to deconstruct this process some more, but for now, you&amp;#39;re stuck with my rendition.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reddit is the self proclaimed &amp;quot;Front Page of the Internet&amp;quot;. When successfully harnessed, Reddit can send your website a stampede of traffic. That&amp;#39;s great for marketers, but Redditors HATE being marketed to. Perhaps due to unsavory past experiences, the moment they smell a marketer, Redditors attack. The visual I imagine is much like &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/a-game-of-drones-why-some-bees-kill-their-queens-83624&quot;&gt;bees turning on their queen&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending far too much time on Reddit, David noticed that Memes outperformed other posts. He started asking: “How could we make memes work for Kippo?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he didn&amp;#39;t just blindly start making Memes. Instead, he asked a pivotal follow up &lt;a href=&quot;weekly_notes/2020-07-26#questions&quot;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; “Why is a meme funny on Reddit?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kippo team noticed patterns. Some memes were unexpectedly relatable. Others had shock value. And they got to work producing memes that reconstructed those sensations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some duds, but soon enough the Memes started to catch fire. Here are a couple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EWUPV5mUMA4NuMV?format=png&amp;name=small&quot; alt=&quot;True Love meme&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/EWUPX7ZU4AEEKj5?format=jpg&amp;name=medium&quot; alt=&quot;What people think Gaming is like&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kippo doesn’t rely on Memes as much these days (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kippoapp.com/comics&quot;&gt;Kippo Comics&lt;/a&gt; for their primary meme distribution channel), but I found this 0 to 2,000 users story fascinating. It reminds me of this grab-bag of tactics &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kapwing.com/blog/viral-content/&quot;&gt;used by Kapwing&lt;/a&gt; - which is presumably, the maturation of tactics from Kapwing&amp;#39;s early days of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kapwing.com/blog/how-we-got-our-first-10-customers/&quot;&gt;(successful) floundering&lt;/a&gt;. As well as this tactic used by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.towerpaddleboards.com/&quot;&gt;Tower Paddle Boards&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://marketingexamples.com/seo/unsplash&quot;&gt;grow via Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unconventional, but very effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-source-business-models&quot;&gt;Open Source Business Models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money and open source have a funny relationship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;#39;s clarify that there is no philosophical tension between Open Source and profits. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fsf.org/about/&quot;&gt;Free Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, arguably the spiritual center of Open Source, has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/selling.html&quot;&gt;this to say&lt;/a&gt; on the topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people believe that the spirit of the GNU Project is that you should not charge money for distributing copies of software, or that you should charge as little as possible—just enough to cover the cost. This is a misunderstanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, we encourage people who redistribute free software to charge as much as they wish or can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More fundamentally, there seems to be a contradiction in &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to make money with Open Source. How do you charge money for software that is 100% open and free to run? Would that not yield perfect competition, eliminate profits, and turn these into untenable businesses?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, Red Hat (&lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2019/08/01/with-the-acquisition-closed-ibm-goes-all-in-on-red-hat/&quot;&gt;acq. by IBM&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/CLDR?p=CLDR&amp;amp;.tsrc=fin-srch&quot;&gt;Cloudera&lt;/a&gt;, MuleSoft (&lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2018/03/20/salesforce-is-buying-mulesoft-at-enterprise-value-of-6-5-billion/&quot;&gt;acq. by SalesForce&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/MDB?p=MDB&amp;amp;.tsrc=fin-srch&quot;&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/ESTC?p=ESTC&amp;amp;.tsrc=fin-srch&quot;&gt;Elastic&lt;/a&gt; all beg to differ. These are all multi-billion dollar companies that trade (or traded) on the public markets. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you look at the IPO pipeline, you might see Confluent, Hashicorp, Databricks and others not too far away from the event horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do these companies charge for? A survey in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/10/04/commercializing-open-source/&quot;&gt;history&lt;/a&gt; of enterprise open source will yield the following story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support (i.e. Red Hat)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proprietary software built upon an open source core - aka Open Core - and sold as an annual license (i.e. most of Elastic&amp;#39;s business)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SaaS offering of the open source code, in partnership with public cloud (i.e., the fastest growing segment of Mongo&amp;#39;s business)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who follow enterprise software, it&amp;#39;s the SaaS angle that has recently unlocked Open Source for these venture backed businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s interesting that all of the examples I cited so far are very much &amp;quot;infrastructure&amp;quot; products. But the trend of Open Source business models has caught on elsewhere too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattermost.com/&quot;&gt;Mattermost&lt;/a&gt; (an Open source Slack alternative) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.org/&quot;&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; (an alternative to Wordpress). Two examples of how Open Source software is expanding beyond it&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;home court&amp;quot; of developers, and capturing a broader spectrum of users. (Ghost, btw, is not only Open Source, but a &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.org/about/&quot;&gt;non-profit&lt;/a&gt; too. One that just happens to make $200K+ in MRR)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you look at smaller products (yet admittedly, more targeted at developers), you might find &lt;a href=&quot;https://tailwindui.com/&quot;&gt;TailwindUI&lt;/a&gt;, which is built atop the Open Source project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tailwindlabs/tailwindcss&quot;&gt;TailwindCSS&lt;/a&gt;. Or &lt;a href=&quot;https://forge.laravel.com/&quot;&gt;Laravel Forge&lt;/a&gt;, which is similarly built atop the Open Source project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/laravel/laravel&quot;&gt;Laravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without considering all these examples, you might have believed that there is no business model in open source. That the only way to get funds doing Open Source is getting backed by a corporate patron (ie React), or decentralized patronage (ie Vue). And for many (most?) open source maintainers, survival is indeed about finding patrons. (Choose one of: 1) GitHub sponsors/Open Collective, 2) work for Google/Facebook on Open Source, or 3) burnout).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;#39;s simply not the full story. Too many developers get into the &amp;quot;business&amp;quot; of Open Source without ever realizing that they&amp;#39;re sitting atop a potential goldmine (in the form of a community and audience). Open Source maintainers are often influencers by accident. The challenge is monetizing this influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Source businesses are going to become increasingly important moving forward (especially for developer focused products). Open Source builds trust, transforms the community into &amp;quot;co-creators&amp;quot; (superfans), generates another distribution channel, establishes goodwill. A well run open source company has natural advantages that its closed source counterparts simply do not have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say Open Source business is easy. Simply that it is the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll be writing about this topic a lot, but just giving you a first glance into my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m introducing a new section to these weekly notes, where I write bullet points about random things that I came across this week. If the above are half baked notes, the following are uncooked. Here we go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First thoughts on Rust-lang. Coming from Golang and Java, the idea of eliminating concurrency issues like race conditions &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ch04-02-references-and-borrowing.html#mutable-references&quot;&gt;by design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is amazing. Sadly, I also miss Golang&amp;#39;s compilation speeds. Go compiles fast &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/a/2976675&quot;&gt;by design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finally watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt11394168/&quot;&gt;Be Water&lt;/a&gt; - the documentary on Bruce Lee. His unyielding refusal to take on any demeaning role, paired with a  mentality of &amp;quot;your loss&amp;quot; towards those who didn&amp;#39;t value his vision - is a model of self-respect. We lost Bruce when he was 32 and right on the cusp of superstardom. Far too early. And in a huge blow to Asian American masculinity, Hollywood picked Jackie Chan as his successor. I love Jackie, but -  let me just say this, Jackie worked in the house, and Bruce in the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Datadog is an amazing company - or at least &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; think it is, after looking at their 10K. Sales and Marketing efficiency is best in class. Their strategy is amazing too (unified metrics, tracing, and logs &lt;em&gt;chefs kiss&lt;/em&gt;). So much to learn and unpack about this company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The next time you&amp;#39;re scared and want to &amp;quot;bury your head in the sand&amp;quot;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://animals.howstuffworks.com/birds/do-ostriches-really-bury-heads-in-sand.htm&quot;&gt;consider the facts&lt;/a&gt;. Ostriches do not actually bury their heads when scared. Rather, they bury their eggs in the sand, and rotate their eggs multiple times a day. They are not scared, they&amp;#39;re just taking care of their young. I mean, just think about it, why would a 9 ft, 350 lb animal be scared? Not to mention they&amp;#39;re fast (40 MPH, which is 10+ MPH faster than Usain Bolt). You&amp;#39;ve seen &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aMmX-n1YGlA&quot;&gt;the Kevin Hart skit&lt;/a&gt;. Fear the Ostrich &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-08-23]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Mental Health]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-23</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-23</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-23">&lt;p&gt;I started writing my notes yesterday and I just didn&amp;#39;t &amp;quot;have it&amp;quot;. Despite consecutive days of great sleep, solid exercise, and good weather, something was just off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, my parents and I sent my little brother off to college. I did not expect it to be a massive challenge, but the psychological effect on my parents has been brutal. Yes, there&amp;#39;s an element of empty nesting, which every parent goes through, but there&amp;#39;s also the circumstances around my brother&amp;#39;s college selection (he&amp;#39;s on a plan to transfer schools in his sophomore/junior year - anyone who&amp;#39;s been in that position knows the stress).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their emotions have stirred within me, a sense of unease. Combined with an increased level of anxiety from previous weeks and the result is cratering levels of productivity. Attempting to be productive right now feels as beneficial as running with increasingly painful shin splints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I won&amp;#39;t. This week, my only note will be a short one on mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mental-health&quot;&gt;Mental Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s 2020, and we all know [[Mental Health]] is supremely important. We crave authenticity (after being flooded by people&amp;#39;s Best Selves™ on [[Facebook]] and Instagram for years, we want to see real people). And we need &amp;quot;depressurized&amp;quot; spaces to talk and meet new people. And while the need is astronomical, I still think we&amp;#39;re extremely bad at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, mental health is a lot like physical health. In both, there are exercises you can do to improve (i.e. meditation and journaling on one side, squats and [[HIIT]] on the other). When you&amp;#39;re feeling healthy, either mentally or physically, you reap benefits to everything else in your life. On the other hand, if you are &amp;quot;injured&amp;quot;, even simple things can be difficult. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unlike physical health, mental [[wellness]] is probably more complex and certainly harder to measure. When someone is physically healthy, you can look for obvious signals (healthy HR, BMI, VO2 max, etc). When someone has great mental health, how can you measure that? And how do you know if the measurement is accurate (not faked)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly have no answer for this, but I&amp;#39;m trying a few things to help me feel comfortable in all aspects of my life. It involves reading books on spiritual wellness, practicing mindfulness meditation and self care, improving my relationship with my parents, learning my history and heritage so I can be rooted in my identity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to start adding a books section on my personal site for this reason. When I&amp;#39;m having an issue with my mental health, I often find that the right book is the perfect medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, in addition to reading, I often find talking to my [[Otter]] app very useful. It&amp;#39;s just [[Audio]] transcription software, but it feels a bit like a therapist. It&amp;#39;s lower friction that writing and pairs nicely with journaling. But that&amp;#39;s just me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is to say that I&amp;#39;ve surprisingly found myself at the &amp;quot;bust&amp;quot; of another [[boom and bust]] cycle, one that I did not imagine would have come so soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel comfortable sharing, I&amp;#39;d love to hear from you - what strategies do you find effective when dealing with degraded mental health?&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-08-16]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Mistakes, Audio]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-16</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-16</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-16">&lt;p&gt;This week I read [[Siddhartha]] by Herman Hesse (as translated by Hilda Rosner). There&amp;#39;s a lot to say about the book - it&amp;#39;s tremendous - but today I&amp;#39;ll focus on one idea from the book, which is the necessity of mistakes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to talk about [[Audio]]. So to expect two sections this week: mistakes, and audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mistakes&quot;&gt;Mistakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to draw an image personifying spirituality, I might sketch a picture of a monk at a monastery, practicing sitting meditation and drinking tea. He has found peace - having renounced all worldly possessions. I&amp;#39;d draw his mouth with a subtle upward curve, to resemble the slightest of smiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I certainly would not draw a gambler, mired in a midlife existential crisis, experiencing a nauseating level of depression. But that is precisely what our protagonist, Siddhartha, experienced:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to experience despair, I had to sink to the greatest mental depths, to thoughts of suicide, in order to experience grace, to hear Om again, to sleep deeply again and to awaken refreshed again. I had to become a fool again in order to find Atman in myself. I had to sin in order to live again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something extremely relatable about despair. Whereas wild success is a rare fruit tasted only by a small fragment of civilization&amp;#39;s elite - all of us have known failure. Some to darker nadirs, but all of us know this suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what&amp;#39;s beautiful about this - is that the book shows us not only can we &amp;quot;bounce back&amp;quot; from the lowest points in our life, but they are actually necessary. Without them, you may gain an intellectual understanding of wisdom. But to truly know what wisdom and truth are, you must take your own unique path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my life, I find this question recur with frequency. Is it possible to &amp;quot;beeline&amp;quot; to peace? Or must you take the winding path? Or as my mother describes &amp;quot;弯路&amp;quot; - a torturous, bending road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engineer in me says that optimization is possible. But all signs point elsewhere. We each have moments where we know something is wrong, something is off - but choose it anyways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take for example, this software engineer on a Reddit thread that I found recently. This young engineer took a job for prestige and is now miserable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate everything about it. I had a choice between a company with great people, better CoL and same pay and my current company.
The only thing better here is the prestige, I fell for it. I knew something felt off during the interview but I took the job anyway.
People here are assholes who live to work, pretend to be nice and backstab you as soon as they can.
Fuck them, fuck me. I wish I I could go back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/i3g44t/i_picked_a_job_for_the_prestige_and_i_regret_it/&quot;&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/i3g44t/i_picked_a_job_for_the_prestige_and_i_regret_it/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;#39;s this engineer. But we&amp;#39;ve all made that same decision before. And maybe not for prestige, but for reasons that we knew were wrong, but simply couldn&amp;#39;t override.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no lesson here. These are my notes. Not an essay. There is no point I&amp;#39;m trying to make. No argument I&amp;#39;m advancing. Simply that I thought the idea of [[Mistakes | mistakes]] as not only beneficial, but necessary for spiritual growth was deeply beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the number of times I have felt existential pangs as a consequence of my decisions - it&amp;#39;s possible that I&amp;#39;ve made enough mistakes to set the stage for growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But probably not. I suspect I have many more mistakes ahead of me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio&quot;&gt;Audio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so let&amp;#39;s change gears from the spiritual to the technical, and talk about audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re not familiar with these two articles, bookmark them and read them after you&amp;#39;ve consumed this piece:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alexdanco.com/2019/10/17/the-audio-revolution/&quot;&gt;The Audio Revolution&lt;/a&gt; by Alex Danco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2020/02/24/a-text-renaissance/&quot;&gt;A Text Renaissance&lt;/a&gt; by Venkatesh Rao&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;#39;m certainly missing other blog posts/tweets on what I&amp;#39;m sure will be a trend of tech writers discussing the future of audio. I&amp;#39;m less interested in predictions on Audio though, and would rather focus on getting the pulse on what is out there today, and what I feel like each of these technologies might unleash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the style of Venkat&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;A Text Renaissance&amp;quot; (or at least the first half of that piece), I will briefly outline a series of technologies that I think have put us at the precipice of a Cambrian explosion in audio. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebRTC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AirPods (and Fast Pair)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discord and Clubhouse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI Transcription&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcasting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to skip around, these sections came out to be much longer than I anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;webrtc&quot;&gt;WebRTC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[[WebRTC]] is here. Finally. After initial release in 2011, and so many teasers along the way, we&amp;#39;re finally at the point where browsers have deployed stable and high quality versions of WebRTC. In fact, the stable spec was only finalized on May 4, 2018 - and security vulnerabilities have been discovered and patched since. It&amp;#39;s been a long road, but it&amp;#39;s finally here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, developer productivity has seen massive benefits due to browser affordances like &amp;quot;flexbox&amp;quot;, native promises (leading to async/await), and countless other small improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for most of us, WebRTC was just a thing that was always on the horizon. But it sort of crept up on all of us, and now it&amp;#39;s there, ready for the tinkering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, I don&amp;#39;t think this means the fall of Zoom anytime soon. Zoom has invested heavily in their own architecture and technology and probably have a massive lead on everyone. But that&amp;#39;s for video - which consumes significantly more bandwidth than audio and is a different kind of problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WebRTC and audio work very well today. For example, my friends Azlen and Jon built &lt;a href=&quot;https://cozyroom.xyz/&quot;&gt;Cozyroom&lt;/a&gt;, which sits atop of WebRTC. They&amp;#39;ve since polished it after their humble hackathon beginnings, but these types of experiences are about to explode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myself, I&amp;#39;m working with Nick on &lt;a href=&quot;https://openhouse.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Openhouse&lt;/a&gt;. Which I&amp;#39;ll talk about much more in the future - but for now, know that it is a project built with the intention of learning WebRTC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;airpods&quot;&gt;AirPods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a trend that didn&amp;#39;t really make a whole lot of sense to me at first. How does a stupid little accessory change the face of computing, especially since it doesn&amp;#39;t do anything structurally different from its corded predecessors?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it changed a lot. It changed our fashion sensibilities around wearables. It changed how often we plug into audio. It taught us that we could replace our own thoughts with the voice/laugh of Joe Rogen.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has completely surprised Apple, demolishing their own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macrumors.com/2019/11/27/apple-doubling-airpods-pro-production-report/&quot;&gt;sales projections&lt;/a&gt;. And the demand for AirPods, feels as insatiable as the demand for Teslas in a world of unlimited access to a subprime auto loans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#39;s not just AirPods. Apple&amp;#39;s forever copycat, Android, has finally shipped &amp;quot;Fast Pair&amp;quot; earbuds that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blog.google/products/android/fast-pair-easier-bluetooth/&quot;&gt;might not suck&lt;/a&gt;. When the proliferation of fashionable Android wireless earbuds finally hits mass adoption, get ready for a further acceleration of people escaping from their own thoughts via podcasts and other monkey mind pacifiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;discord-and-clubhouse&quot;&gt;Discord and Clubhouse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who still think Discord competes with Slack for communities... Where the hell have you been? It&amp;#39;s been my experience that all communities that have started after COVID-19 have chosen Discord, and the only Slack communities that I still get invites from are legacy ones, or businesses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s silly to think Discord and Slack compete on instant messaging. Slack is the &amp;quot;semi-async&amp;quot; text communication solution for startups, which competes with Microsoft Teams in the enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord is a social &lt;strong&gt;space&lt;/strong&gt; that embraces pseudonymity and gamers. It facilitates seamless jumping between communities (something that is an architectural impossibility given Slack&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://slack.engineering/how-slack-built-shared-channels/&quot;&gt;sharded MySQL strategy&lt;/a&gt;), but most importantly (imo), it provides persistent voice channels for communities to congregate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These voice channels seemed stupid to me at first. Like why would you want an always open connection to friends that you can hop in and hop out of at any time? Why not just call them? Why would this change behavior at all? I mean, as far as the technology is concerned, this idea has ALWAYS been possible - so why didn&amp;#39;t it take off before?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the reduction in friction to communicating with people does change behavior. It makes it feel like walking into a common room at a youth hostel and seeing who&amp;#39;s there. It creates audio serendipity in a way that is impossible on Slack. It feels like a physical space, made possible by... audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is a great segue into Clubhouse. See, Clubhouse and Discord share something in common. I described Discord voice channels via the metaphor of a &amp;quot;common room&amp;quot;. Well, in Clubhouse, the primary interface is a list of &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;rooms&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;, or shared audio spaces - they lean into that metaphor big time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the larger rooms, there&amp;#39;s a small handful of speakers on stage enjoying a free-flowing (often moderated) discussion. All while an audience listens silently from their muted perch (audience members cannot speak unless selected by the moderator to join the stage). And in the smaller rooms, it&amp;#39;s a public, participatory discussion about anything random.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clubhouse to me - and it might morph into something very different in the coming weeks, such is the pace of mutation - feels like a book festival. If you&amp;#39;ve never heard of a book festival, then you&amp;#39;re not alone. The only reason I know the term is I randomly found myself in Berkeley once upon a time - and it just so happened to be during the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.baybookfest.org/content/2015/schedule.html&quot;&gt;first annual&lt;/a&gt; Bay Area book festival. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a lot like a music festival, but instead of featuring musicians, there were authors and literary figures. And instead of performing music, they just talked. Different bookstores and theaters around Berkeley were all booked for the extravaganza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I opened Clubhouse for the first time, it felt like I was transported to downtown Berkeley for the book festival. There were a list of different talks happening right then, and list of upcoming events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It amazes me how audio, seems to create the illusion of spaces. Definitely not physically, but it creates an imaginative space that feels &amp;quot;cozy&amp;quot; in a way that Zoom and Google Meet simply do not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m particularly excited about our Openhouse project because it allows for these affordances and to create spaces that can feel cozy. The internet is mutating, and open source is the highly editable RNA that powers the rapid evolution of new tech. I want to see a world where any community can embed a Clubhouse like experience on any site or in any app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if that happens, then we&amp;#39;ll chip away at the value prop of universities. Their lectures have already been digitized and commoditized. Now, with Clubhouse/Openhouse, we see talks, guest speakers, and seminars getting commoditized. We&amp;#39;re getting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-transcription&quot;&gt;AI Transcription&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio and Text have a very peculiar relationship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we had text messaging, we had phone calls. But before we had phones, we had mail. And before we wrote letters, we just talked to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio and Text seem to come in alternating waves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio Transcription has been around for a long time. I remember many years ago, TJ-Maxx would sell last-year&amp;#39;s Dragon speech recognition software in their discount software section (well, I guess the entire store is a discount section, so apologies for that redundant adjective). But they were pretty limited back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, AI transcription is getting good. And it&amp;#39;s available as an API via things like Temi, [[Otter]], Trint (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/wirecutter/reviews/best-transcription-services/&quot;&gt;see comparison&lt;/a&gt;). But it&amp;#39;s not that good though yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can get really good AI transcription, for cheap, then audio and text will blur in ways we haven&amp;#39;t seen previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re not there yet, but watch this trend. As GPT-3 has proven, when we start throwing lots of parameters (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GPT-3&quot;&gt;175+ billion&lt;/a&gt;) and money (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/MachineLearning/comments/hwfjej/d_the_cost_of_training_gpt3/&quot;&gt;millions of $&lt;/a&gt;) at a really really massive neural net, things start getting uncanny - or possibly, beyond uncanny (in the sense of crossing the uncanny chasm... err valley).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m no expert in AI, I barely understand what a neural network is (thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/machine-learning?&quot;&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;, the first mover in unbundling the university), but I know to follow this trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment we can get fast, highly-accurate automated transcription for cheap, the line between audio and text will blur so much that it&amp;#39;ll lead to innovations that are hard to predict. As is though, transcription seems to get something every sentence and that&amp;#39;s good, but not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phase change, when it comes, will come suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;podcasting&quot;&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have little to say about podcasting other than it is digitizing Radio for the AirPod generation. This has been a trend for years and is uninteresting because it&amp;#39;s so &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thepodcasthost.com/listening/podcast-industry-stats/&quot;&gt;huge already&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be uninteresting, but it&amp;#39;s hugely important. According to Infinite Dial, about 55% of Americans have listened to a podcast in 2020, up from 33% in 2015. The shift in behavior has tipped to the majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love how podcasting is based on RSS, an architecturally open technology - which Apple has supported for years. I love that openness. It&amp;#39;s contribute to the rapid growth and proliferation of podcasting - the barrier to entry is so low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monetizing it will be a pain. The fact that it sits on top of RSS, an architecturally open technology, makes it more frustrating for podcasters to get stats on their listeners, which means less potent ad targeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotify has made a big play on podcasts, we&amp;#39;ll see how that plays out for them. The key here is to build the world&amp;#39;s best podcast player (classic &lt;a href=&quot;https://stratechery.com/2019/spotifys-podcast-aggregation-play/&quot;&gt;Aggregation Theory at play&lt;/a&gt;) and get everyone to use that. Then, once you have the user&amp;#39;s identity and listening history, you can drop targeted ads for days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Spotify doesn&amp;#39;t have the best podcast player, and it will probably be pretty hard to get me to switch to them. So they&amp;#39;ve resorted to exclusive deals with big names. It didn&amp;#39;t work for Mixer when they signed Ninja. Maybe it will work for Spotify though? The moment the aggregate demand though, they win. To do so, I think they&amp;#39;ll need a Google-search level quantum leap in utility over the current podcast players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, apologies for the digression on Spotify. What I really want to point out is you&amp;#39;ve probably heard all those Clubhassholes say stuff like &amp;quot;Clubhouse has completely replaced podcasts for me&amp;quot;. I think that&amp;#39;s actually how podcasting fits into this greater narrative of audio explosion - it is the gateway behavior to newer audio experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you podcast, then you clubhouse, then we all become Joaquin Phoenix with an ever present audio-presence in our ear canals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-it-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping it up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio is exploding. You already knew that. But I hope you&amp;#39;ve gotten a better sense of &amp;quot;Why now?&amp;quot;, along with a few trends that might push us into explosive adoption of audio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcasting as a gateway behavior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AirPods and Fast Pair as the physical enabler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebRTC as the technological tectonic shift&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discord and Clubhouse as the first successful innovators on this frontier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and AI Transcription maturing into a new &amp;quot;tinker&amp;quot; vector for future mutations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petri dish is ripe for a combinatorial expansion of random ideas in audio 🧫🎧. Get excited!&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-08-09]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Internet Friends, Internet Cities]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-09</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-09</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-09">&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#39;m in the mood of making predictions. Predictions on the rise of Internet Friends and Internet Cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are fledgling ideas and there&amp;#39;s a strong chance that I&amp;#39;m saying nothing new. Additionally, this might be more wishful thinking than thoughtful analysis. But I found these thoughts interesting enough and I want to develop some of them a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a more personal side, this week wasn&amp;#39;t productive. That&amp;#39;s because I&amp;#39;m helping getting my parent&amp;#39;s house ready for a sale - lots of cleaning and staging. While exhausting and distracting, it yielded some unexpected psychic benefits. There&amp;#39;s something powerful about having a clean and beautiful living space. A physical manifestation of the ideas of [[Work Clean]] and &amp;quot;[[Fewer, more beautiful things]]&amp;quot; (an idea I haven&amp;#39;t yet explored, but certainly want to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And another tiny personal update. After a conversation with a friend, I&amp;#39;ve developed a renewed commitment to personal development. That starts with re-listening to &amp;quot;The Power of Now&amp;quot; on audiobook, which sort of feels similar to listening to a spiritual lecture or sermon. And to put things into practice, I&amp;#39;m also re-listening to &amp;quot;Atomic Habits&amp;quot;. More on both of these topics in the future, but it felt necessary to mention them (you know, for the accountability).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It&amp;#39;s funny, I own a lot of audiobooks (Audible subscriber), but I seem to listen to the same ones over and over...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, now that all of that is out of the way, my predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;internet-friends&quot;&gt;Internet Friends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve made a handful of [[Internet Friends]] in 2020. The more I use Twitter, the more internet friends I&amp;#39;ve made. But it&amp;#39;s not just Twitter, I&amp;#39;ve also found internet friends on [[IndieHackers]] and [[MakerLog]] and various invite only Discords/Group chats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more than I&amp;#39;ve ever made in all my previous years. In the past, I made practically all of my friends in the real world. I had a few Internet-only connections, but things like Discord and Zoom have changed the game. I used to know what people on the internet think like. Now, I know what they sound like. And what they laugh like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s obvious to say the future is going to be a whole lot more digital. But the second order effects on our social lives are going to be weird. Imagine a world in which half of your friends you&amp;#39;ve met in person and the other half online. (Which is a strange distinction - &amp;quot;in person&amp;quot; vs &amp;quot;online&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is important to consider because meeting people online is different. You can actually meet someone online for the first time without interacting with them at all. You can visit their profile and read up on how they want to present themselves. Or better yet, if they have a website, you can spend a moment immersed in their brain. All without ever meeting them. And they can do the same for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internet Friends are typically more aligned with you, in terms of how you think. In the past, location was king. Now, thoughts and values reign supreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fascinating wrinkle - you can have multiple identities. And none of them have to be associated with your face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trend is massively important to understand. It&amp;#39;s going to fundamentally shake our conception of what it means to be social and what it means to be friends. Right now, people sort of understand this. But the new tools that we&amp;#39;ve gotten recently (video chat via Zoom/Google Meets, audio discussion with voyeurism as a feature via Clubhouse/Discord) are changing the dynamics of how &amp;quot;close&amp;quot;, an Internet Friend can feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collectively, these tools are a disruptive innovation to friendship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let that sink in - Friendship is getting disrupted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience is worse in important ways (you can&amp;#39;t hug or high five or share food), but better in many others (meet people on the merit of thoughts and values, without restriction to geography).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means producing content (writing, videos, art, etc) is going to be hugely important. Your content is the new coffee chat - it replaces the first meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no game plan for what you need to do to position yourself for this change, but I believe building your own personal site is at the core. It&amp;#39;s highly related to the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;https://trends.vc/trends-0023-personal-brands/&quot;&gt;Personal Brands&lt;/a&gt; that Dru Riley explored, but in this case, it&amp;#39;s not about business. It&amp;#39;s more about being a person of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;internet-cities&quot;&gt;Internet Cities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I stumbled across &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bogleheads.org/AboutUs.php&quot;&gt;Bogleheads&lt;/a&gt; and it felt like visiting another world. From my internet spaceship (Firefox), I had touched down and landed on a strange planet, a place called Bogleheads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My visit was short, but it was fascinating to explore this backwater. For about 10 minutes, I immersed myself in a culture of responsible personal finance (Bogleheads take their name from John Bogle, the founder of Vanguard and champion of ETF &amp;quot;set it and forget it&amp;quot; type investing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bogleheads is an old community. It started in 1998 as a subcommunity of the MorningStar forums, and then in 2007 branched off to settle new territory. Those MorningStar Internet Pilgrims spun up phpBB and created a new town square dedicated to the creed of John Bogle. Over time, this little Internet City sprawled with more low-code tools, adding a wiki (mediaWiki), and a blog (WordPress). In 2020, it&amp;#39;s still a lively little city, but it certainly feels dated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take for example, a newer digital community like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiehackers.com/&quot;&gt;IndieHackers&lt;/a&gt;, which itself is entirely custom. Built on Firebase, IndieHackers is a new type of Internet City that doesn&amp;#39;t use off the shelf parts. Thus, it has its own distinctive feel - that&amp;#39;s reminiscent of Reddit or HackerNews, but altogether quite different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe we are about to see the founding of a great number of new [[Internet Cities]] over the next few years. Some may call them communities, but I think they&amp;#39;re closer to [[MMO RPG]]s, that will share similarities to cities. These &amp;quot;communities&amp;quot; will have job boards, and commerce, and events, and governance. You might pay a tax to the community (a membership fee, or a transaction fee on all commerce), or more likely, it will be sponsored by a corporation (in the way IndieHackers is today by Stripe). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the great digitization of our social and professional lives means that interest based Internet Cities are begging to be created. In the future, we&amp;#39;ll probably spend most of our time interacting in Internet Cities and Towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we already spend a ton of time on these Internet Cities. To me, Twitter feels like the Big City, Bogleheads feels like the a small town in the Midwest, and IndieHackers feels like a young Singapore. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know if this idea makes any sense to you, but I&amp;#39;m excited for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is going to be fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-08-02]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Authenticity, Two Energies, Multiple Discovery]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-02</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-02</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-08-02">&lt;p&gt;This week I had a ton of anxiety. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#39;t write about the root cause, yet I felt that it was important to recognize this, because A) it makes me feel better to do so and B)  if there&amp;#39;s something on my mind and I don&amp;#39;t write about it - well, that&amp;#39;s a bit inauthentic and these notes are supposed to be authentic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is a good segue into this week&amp;#39;s first topic - [[Authenticity]]. But before we do that, I&amp;#39;d like to update you that I have indeed conquered last week&amp;#39;s challenge. The [[Vue]] plugin for &lt;a href=&quot;https://feather.id/&quot;&gt;Feather&lt;/a&gt; is out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/feather-client-vue&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;authenticity&quot;&gt;Authenticity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being authentic on the internet is hard. When anyone can see what you&amp;#39;ve posted, you must proceed with some degree of caution. The fact that I started these notes by redacting the root cause of my anxiety is an example of me exercising that caution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Cancel culture&amp;quot; has revealed how simple it is to weaponize someone&amp;#39;s past comments against them on the internet. Anything you say can and will be used against. You have the right to remain silent. But [[cancel culture]] isn&amp;#39;t what I want to focus on today - maybe another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather, I want to talk about the inner challenge of being authentic online. The challenge of finding your voice in the face of fear - the fear of being perceived as &amp;quot;less than perfect&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us want to be [[perfect]] online. Not in the sense that we have no flaws, but more so that we want to invoke admiration in others. I want others to be like &amp;quot;oh man, I think Phil is great. He&amp;#39;s thoughtful, original, etc&amp;quot; and I suspect most others want something to that effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I&amp;#39;ve found is that aiming for perfection tends to lead to two outcomes: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your work becomes performative &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first case, you never publish, for fear of not being perfect. And in the second, your work sounds off - forced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Perell has an interesting take on this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are bad writers, but excellent text messagers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their writing is bad because they try to sound smart once they open Microsoft Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when they text, they write with clarity and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re stuck, write like you’re sending an important text message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/david_perell/status/1240836363190222848?s=20&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/david_perell/status/1240836363190222848?s=20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performative work is cringeworthy, even if the underlying work is valuable. It lacks voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is the solution to simply &amp;quot;write with voice&amp;quot;? I don&amp;#39;t think so. Voice isn&amp;#39;t something you turn on or off. Voice is nurtured, and not just by you, but by engaging with others. You reflect on your style, you evaluate what elements of your work you like, and what you don&amp;#39;t. You put it in front of others and you listen to what they say. Voice is a beautiful thing - if writing is a form of self expression, then writing with voice is prose that has expressed the self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem isn&amp;#39;t that someone has &amp;quot;voice&amp;quot; and simply needs to choose to use it. The problem is more that your voice needs to be nurtured. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, it&amp;#39;s a better goal to produce work that is interesting to yourself. With a low bar for quality. Giving yourself permission to write about what you want, without regard for how it&amp;#39;s perceived will give you wings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See, this is why I write these notes. This concept is half baked.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;two-energies&quot;&gt;Two Energies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I experienced a sharp turn in my energy levels. Monday and Tuesday were great. Then, something happened on Wednesday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ability to think abstract thoughts and generate any semblance of creative work left my brain. I felt like [[Cinderella]] when the clock struck 12, or that movie [[Limitless]] when the Adderall++ pills began to wear off. The magic faded away and thereafter, I was forced to welcome the reign of tiredness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This happens to me a lot. I seem to operate in two forms, one in which ideas and productivity comes naturally - and another in which everything is a struggle. I don&amp;#39;t drink caffeine, and maybe that&amp;#39;s part of my problem, but I find that these &amp;quot;two energies&amp;quot; and the transition between them feels a lot like the [[boom and bust]] cycle of the stock market. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The [[bull]] market run up to feeling good is rooted in strong personal [[wellness]] fundamentals (good sleep, exercise, diet, and psychological care), but as the good times roll on, those fundamentals slowly (or quickly) fall by the wayside. Things continue to go well, but a reckoning is awaiting. Lack of sleep. Burnout. Anxiety. A crash. The [[bear]] falls into a sudden hibernation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;#39;s kind of where I&amp;#39;m at right now. Wednesday was the bust in my boom and bust energy cycle, and the last few days, things went from bad to worse, and here I am trying to re-invest in the fundamentals to get myself firing on all cylinders again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;multiple-discovery&quot;&gt;Multiple Discovery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was going to publish these notes on Sunday, but because I didn&amp;#39;t get to it, I thought I&amp;#39;d throw in a bonus this morning (Monday 08-03).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One idea that popped up on my radar last week (a couple times) was the idea of [[multiple discovery]], or the idea that an invention or a discovery happens at the same time at different places in the world. We often cite Leibniz and Newton discovering Calculus or Wallace and Darwin discovering Evolution as stories of when this occurs in science. Of course, the list of this is enormous:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_multiple_discoveries&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_multiple_discoveries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a similar phenomenon in Hollywood, called &amp;quot;Twin films&amp;quot;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twin_films&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twin_films&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s not just Hollywood and Science - this happens ALL the time in business. From billionaire entrepreneurs who both happen to have side businesses that produce rockets (Bezos/Musk) to your average SaaS product that has dozens of competitors, multiple discovery is a very human thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why does this happen in so many disciplines? One might be tempted to say that we&amp;#39;re less original than we think we are - and I think that would be 100% correct. But it goes a little further than that. I hypothesize there are a LIMITED set of things that CAN be discovered/invented/built at any given point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have zero experience in science and film so I&amp;#39;ll refrain from making any generalizations there. But I believe that when it comes to business, there are a limited number of solutions that the market is able to accept at any given moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It depends on the skills of the consumers (do they know how to use Smartphones, do they know how to type on a keyboard?) and the taste of the market. There&amp;#39;s an element of fashion to business, and I wish we&amp;#39;d understand that better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So on the consumer side, there are a limited number of things they will respond positively to. And on the entrepreneur side, people have extremely similar information diets. So the space of &amp;quot;valid ideas&amp;quot; is actually very small, leading to plenty of collisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I tweeted out this idea: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That idea you have? There&amp;#39;s pretty much a 100% chance someone else has the exact same one and is executing on it TODAY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pliao39/status/1288900847309664256?s=20&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/pliao39/status/1288900847309664256?s=20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I believe that we now live in a world that&amp;#39;s going to become ultra competitive. Get used to it. In a world with billions of humans, all coming online, multiple discovery will be the norm in everything (if it wasn&amp;#39;t already).&lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[2020-07-26]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week's topics: Work Clean, Learning and Drowning, Questions]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-07-26</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-07-26</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/weekly_notes/2020-07-26">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m trying something new. After a conversation with a friend on Tuesday, I&amp;#39;ve decided that my inability to stick with a &amp;quot;Weekly Reflection&amp;quot; routine has simply because I lacked accountability. Combined with my desire to perform &amp;quot;post processing&amp;quot; on my Roam Notes (which itself is a [[forcing function]] to take better Roam Notes), I&amp;#39;m publishing a set of notes from each week. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;#39;re not meant to be read weekly, but I&amp;#39;ve got to tidy up my thoughts somehow. This is that somehow. Future posts and essays will likely have their origins in these weekly notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the backlinks don&amp;#39;t go anywhere for now. I&amp;#39;m using &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsidian.md&quot;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt; to write these markdown notes, and there&amp;#39;s utility for me to add them. One day, I might build a UI in which readers can jump between these links and explore them - semi-Roam style. In other words, these links are purely for my benefit, but one day, they might be more useful to you, the reader, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that sense, those broken backlinks are a metaphor for these weekly notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;work-clean&quot;&gt;Work Clean!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I was struck by how important it is to [[Work Clean]]. Every morning I spend so much time rearranging my workspace by wrangling in a cacophony of browser tabs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who has tried Mari Kondo&amp;#39;s [[Spark Joy]], you know that sentimental items are hard to toss. And in a way, I form sentimental attachments to tabs I have opened, but haven&amp;#39;t read. Each of those tabs feels like it has life-changing potential - and that makes them plausibly valuable. I&amp;#39;m excited to read them, perhaps primed by some form of [[social proof]] in the form of a Tweet, or a large number of upvotes on [[HackerNews]], yet I never asked myself, &amp;quot;Is this really worth reading?&amp;quot;. In other words, I don&amp;#39;t do the important work of [[pre-reading]]. But I should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thus, every morning, I start in the red. I clean up after the previous day&amp;#39;s irresponsibility - of spawning browser tabs filled with potential, but no certain value. And this clean up is draining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what&amp;#39;s worse is if I don&amp;#39;t clean up. My computer begins to run hot, its fans spinning ever faster as it attempts to dissipate heat, and emitting the sound of exhaustion - its version of panting. And those tabs that my computer is working to maintain, those tabs are black holes for productivity. If I accidentally open one, or see a certain tab, then my brain begins a subconscious context switch, which I have to interrupt, and refocus. That costs mental energy. And if I don&amp;#39;t interrupt, well I&amp;#39;m jumping down a 10 minute or so rabbit hole of distraction, thinking about a random topic I had no intention of exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heat from my computer, the torrent of air emitted by its fan, and the context switches from seeing an unwanted browser tab slowly brings my productivity to a crawl. It&amp;#39;s a death by a thousand papercuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes, it&amp;#39;s better to clean up every morning. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But would be better to work clean. Mise en place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-and-drowning&quot;&gt;Learning and Drowning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been struck by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZtfTOuSHGg8&quot;&gt;Michael Siebel&amp;#39;s observation&lt;/a&gt; that successful startup founders are [[formidable]]. Essentially, a person is formidable if they are able to accomplish exactly what they set out to accomplish. &amp;quot;I will sign 10 customers this week&amp;quot; and then go out and do that very daunting task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formidable people are forces to be reckoned with. Because they find ways to consistently push themselves and operate at the edge of what is possible, they become super human. But, I believe this is an outsider&amp;#39;s view of a successful, productive person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inside view of a formidable person is actually the development of [[confidence]] and [[self-esteem]], bordering into arrogance and over-confidence, but not quite. And while I will talk a lot more about self-esteem in the future, I want to touch briefly about the origins of confidence and self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-esteem comes from a place of believing &amp;quot;I am worthy&amp;quot;, regardless of how much I fail or how much society hates me. You must give yourself permission to be. Simply to be. &amp;quot;I am who I am and I am worthy&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For young people, this can come from your parents. I recall [[Kobe]] saying in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WY0wONSarXA&quot;&gt;an interview&lt;/a&gt;, that his father did exactly that. He was 10 or 11 at the time and went to a summer camp, playing against other 10 or 11 year olds, and where his father and uncle had played in their youth and done well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Kobe scored 0 points, the entire summer. His quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I scored, not a free throw, nothing - not a lucky shot, not a breakaway layup. Zero points. And I remember crying about it and being upset about it, and my father gives me a hug and says, &amp;quot;Listen, whether you score 0 or you score 60, I&amp;#39;m gonna love you no matter what.&amp;quot; Now that is the most important thing you can say to a child. Because from there I was like &amp;quot;okay&amp;quot;, that gives me all the confidence in the world to fail. I have the security there. But to hell with that, I&amp;#39;m scoring 60. Let&amp;#39;s go. From there, I just went to work.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what&amp;#39;s amazing about this is those words from Kobe&amp;#39;s father gave him that sense of self worth. To become formidable you need a bedrock of love, that safety net to fail and still be worthy of love. Young people get it from their parents and others. Older people must learn to build that sense of self appreciation themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kobe was formidable, but had his father not been there for him, who knows what if we would associate the name Kobe with basketball royalty or a type of beef (after which Kobe was named). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so this is a long winded way to make a point about Learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I was learning [[Vue]] and made great initial progress. In 7 days, I went from complete noob to a working component that did exactly what I wanted it to do. And then I hit a massive roadblock. I was at the point of packaging my work and putting it on npm as a Vue plugin, and suddenly my momentum crashed as I was stonewalled by an unmoveable object. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, it felt like drowning out at sea. All that confidence and momentum was gone. Now, I have to build up my knowledge of bundling (which I have almost none of, because that&amp;#39;s almost always abstracted away from me) and slowly piece together the puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And right now, I certainly don&amp;#39;t feel formidable. In fact, I feel the complete opposite - incompetent. It&amp;#39;s in this very moment, where this practice of weekly reflection comes in - I&amp;#39;m practicing self appreciation and a giving myself that foundation of worthiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sensation of drowning, of spending an entire summer and scoring 0 points, of spending days on an npm packaging problem with no results, will test your confidence. But to fall back onto a belief that &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m worthy of being me, failures and all&amp;quot; - well that, as Kobe said &amp;quot;gives you all the confidence in the world&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon that safety-net of self belief and appreciation, I&amp;#39;m gonna get this Vue package out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark my words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always been a somewhat curious person, but I think I&amp;#39;ve relied on my natural curiosity and haven&amp;#39;t developed an intentional &amp;quot;question practice&amp;quot;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions are extremely important. They have a way of priming the mind and sharpening focus. They can be used as an attack (i.e. &amp;quot;What do you mean?&amp;quot;). They can reframe a problem (i.e. &amp;quot;What if&amp;quot;). They can be used to challenge assumptions (i.e. &amp;quot;Why do we believe this?&amp;quot;). Questions change the tone. Questions break you out of your normal thinking patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On HackerNews, there was a post this week titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.anup.io/2020/07/20/invert-always-invert/&quot;&gt;Invert, Always Invert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core idea is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the problem - what are you trying to achieve?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invert it - what would guarantee failure?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, consider solutions to avoid this failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s funny how powerful this can be. Thinking of the same problem from the opposite perspective. Hiking the same trail looks different on the return trip - inversion makes the familiar feel new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good questions activate the mind. A new friend of mine (the one who prompted these weekly_notes) asked me &amp;quot;What was the one thing at Uber that you were most excited about or passionate working on?&amp;quot; and it was a good question because I honestly couldn&amp;#39;t answer it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work wasn&amp;#39;t done for passion or purpose, but pragmatism. And perhaps that&amp;#39;s why I&amp;#39;m doing what I&amp;#39;m doing now. Writing^1 and building as a way to make sense of the world - flailing (ahem, writing and building) my way to passion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;^1 - (&lt;a href=&quot;https://softwarementor.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Software Mentor&lt;/a&gt;, and now these weekly notes, to go along with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://spacetime.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Spacetime Newsletter&lt;/a&gt; which is basically just a public journal of what Nick and I are building) &lt;/p&gt;
</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[writing-day-20-of-30]]></title><description><![CDATA[Day 20/30 of my writing challenge. Some additional reflections]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/writing-day-20-of-30</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/writing-day-20-of-30</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:25:12 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/writing-day-20-of-30">&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve made it to day 20 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/talking-to-yourself&quot;&gt;my 30 day writing challenge&lt;/a&gt; and I&apos;m noticing quite a few shifts. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this pace, there is only one strategy that works: write with reckless abandon. Shed perfection. Shed the need for insight and viral-worthy content. The breakneck speed means you have to drop your armor. Publish with no remorse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you do this, your voice has no choice but to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-buttock-playing&quot;&gt;&quot;One-buttock playing&quot;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt; I&apos;m reminded of Benjamin Zander&apos;s TED talk about classical music:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/r9LCwI5iErE?feature=oembed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;And in particular, the story of the hypothetical child&apos;s progression from dull, perfunctory note hitting to soulful, melodic expression:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Now, what happened was not maybe what you thought, which is, he suddenly became passionate, engaged, involved, got a new teacher, he hit puberty, or whatever it is. What actually happened was the impulses were reduced. You see, the first time, he was playing with an impulse on every note.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;And the second, with an impulse every other note.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The nine-year-old put an impulse on every four notes.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The 10-year-old, on every eight notes.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;And the 11-year-old, one impulse on the whole phrase.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And of course, this spectacular sound bite:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;I don&apos;t know how we got into this position. I didn&apos;t say, &quot;I&apos;m going to move my shoulder over, move my body.&quot; No, the music pushed me over, which is why I call it one-buttock playing.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/wd20of30_zander_one_buttock.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;One-buttock playing&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t know what the equivalent for &quot;impulses&quot; are for writing online, but I do know that forcing yourself to publish at a pace that is beyond comfortable brings something out of you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It might even push you to write with one buttock. Will not confirm nor deny if I&apos;ve had such an experience over the last 20 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;abundance&quot;&gt;Abundance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the last few years, I&apos;ve been playing a typing game called Typeracer. Here&apos;s a graph of my first 1000 races:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/wd20of30_typeracer1000.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;First 1000 races&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see, this graph is extremely noisy, and looks a bit like a seismograph.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if you look closely, towards the right of the graph, you can see some &quot;space&quot; where the 75 WPM (words per minute) mark is visible. It&apos;s as if the seismograph has shifted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, let&apos;s take a look at all my races (3800):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/wd20of30_typeracer3800.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;3800 races&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still a ton of variance, but if you squint, there&apos;s a trend!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To see what that looks like, I plotted the trailing 100 race average on a chart:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/wd20of30_typeracer-smoothed.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;smoothed race data&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ah, so now we can see the trends clearly, unobstructed by the noise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you only do a single Typeracer competition, you&apos;re going to feel like your skill level is determined by your performance on that one race. But when you do thousands, your skill level is determined by the trend line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you&apos;re the only X in a room full of Y, there&apos;s this sense that you must speak for all of X. But if you&apos;re one of many, then you can relax and not worry about representing an entire group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you only have one essay on your website, that one essay must speak for you. But when you write something every day, your internet presence is defined by your body of work. One low quality post won&apos;t define you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That&apos;s the beauty of abundance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;foundations&quot;&gt;Foundations&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now, I feel like I&apos;m writing to the crowd that &quot;was there from the start&quot;, except it&apos;s still the start and no one else is here, and it&apos;s not clear that they&apos;ll be joining.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regardless, this work feels necessary. At the very least, it&apos;s forced me to clarify my thinking, and put some ideas to text. I&apos;ve written some articles I will very likely build upon in the near future:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/good-meeting&quot;&gt;Good meetings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/good-teammates&quot;&gt;Good teammates &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/legibility-and-software&quot;&gt;Legibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/where-are-you-from&quot;&gt;Where are you from?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many of the posts are just examples of me taking notes in public, and then there are some articles that I wrote just to meet my quota and don&apos;t intend to see again. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But regardless, the foundation is forming.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This practice is unlikely to be sustainable over the long run, but it&apos;s having a strong effect. I&apos;m finding my internet voice, and getting comfortable in more contexts. I&apos;m shedding the need for perfection, because each piece doesn&apos;t just exist in isolation, but as part of larger and longer story arc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve used this practice to induce other habits too, such as time tracking (wrote about it &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/168-hours&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and meditation, which I will write about soon. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways, I&apos;ll see you again in 10 days, at the culmination of the challenge!&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[halloween-2020]]></title><description><![CDATA[If we left out a bin of candy, with guidance to take only 3 pieces, what would happen? Well, the obvious happened]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/halloween-2020</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/halloween-2020</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 03:47:54 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/halloween-2020">&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m 100% mailing it in today. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had some things I felt like writing (topics on deck: Pace Layering, &quot;What comes before discipline?&quot;), but I just didn&apos;t get to it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead, I figured I&apos;d share some &quot;learnings&quot; from Halloween this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With covid cases on the rise and the weather cooling down, repeatedly opening the door to a bunch of super spreader younglings was the last thing I wanted to do. But, my parents had just moved into a new neighborhood and we felt that it&apos;d be a good idea to contribute to Halloween, even if it&apos;d be in some form of socially distant form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, we set up a &quot;self-serve&quot; station:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/halloween2020_server.jpg&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;Our Halloween self-serve station&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s zoom in on the text:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/halloween2020_server_zoom.jpg&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;Take 3 pieces of candy sign&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided to try an experiment to see if the text &quot;Smile, you&apos;re on camera!&quot; would deter kids from taking more than the recommended amount. Sadly, there was no camera - but my Mom was watching.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;lessons&quot;&gt;Lessons&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As far as automation is concerned, this is pretty great. We buy candy, dump it into a bin, put up some signs, and the kids can help themselves. We had enough candy to refill the station once.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, the problem with this setup is all too apparent - there are bad actors out there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wish I could share video footage of what my mom and I observed (mostly my mom, I lost patience of watching this setup after the first couple trick or treaters came by) but, like I mentioned, there was no camera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyways, my mom noticed some amusing trends:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Some kids are greedy (obviously)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Most kids don&apos;t take too much (surprising)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Older kids come out later and the greedy ones are shameless (sometimes camping out by the bin, picking out their favorite chocolates, while their friends quickly take their few pieces and watch on, in disgust. Behold, a transformation into Augustus Gloop before our very eyes) &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Kids who went with their parents were more likely to follow the rules, although not always (and some parents even took more than 3 pieces of candy themselves 😂)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;One little girl read the instructions out loud, counted her candy one piece at a time, waved hi to the &quot;camera&quot;, and wished us &quot;Happy Halloween!&quot;. Obviously, she was our favorite&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We didn&apos;t tally the number of kids who were able to visit the station, but I wouldn&apos;t be surprised if some kids took upwards of 20 pieces. Fistfuls upon fistfuls. All in all, we had to refill the station after about 1 hour, and the reinforcements only lasted another hour or so.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Had the rules been followed, the candy reserves should have been enough for about 80 kids. I&apos;d guess we saw closer to 30 trick or treaters before it ran out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflections&quot;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I could do it again, I&apos;d set up a legit camera the next time, directly visible - just to make sure the kids knew for sure they were being watched. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, I take solace in the poetic justice inherent in gluttony. The greedy are rewiring their brains to crave sugar and sweets even further. That&apos;s a slippery slope that leads nowhere good.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human nature is fascinating. It&apos;s always reassuring to see that most people are good actors. But it&apos;s always the 20% that cause the rest of us to dedicate our lives to incentive design.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just your daily reminder that everything in life obeys a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law&quot;&gt;Power Law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[legibility-and-software]]></title><description><![CDATA[Legibility is simplicity, but not all simplicity is good. Where do we have opportunities to introduce "good" legibility into our systems?]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/legibility-and-software</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/legibility-and-software</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 19:17:35 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/legibility-and-software">&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m beginning to familiarize myself with the topic of legibility - a concept from the book &quot;Seeing Like a State&quot;. While I haven&apos;t dug in deep, it appears the following are &quot;cannon&quot; for the topic:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/&quot;&gt;A Big Little Idea Called Legibility&lt;/a&gt; by Venkatesh Rao&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/03/16/book-review-seeing-like-a-state/&quot;&gt;Book Review: Seeing Like a State&lt;/a&gt; by Scott Alexander&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;And these are great accompaniments:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theoildrum.com/node/5528&quot;&gt;&quot;Peak Civilization&quot;: The Fall of the Roman Empire&lt;/a&gt; by Ugo Bardi&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eugenewei.com/blog/2020/9/18/seeing-like-an-algorithm&quot;&gt;Seeing Like an Algorithm&lt;/a&gt; by Eugene Wei&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So let me take a quick stab at defining legibility, then take a glance at complexity, and finally bring this back to software.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Legibility&lt;/strong&gt; - the idea that complex systems are inefficient and can be rearranged with authoritarian mandates to optimize for ease of governance (in other words, when central authorities desire complex systems to be simplified for easier management, they desire legibility)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alright, that was quick - onto complexity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;complexity&quot;&gt;Complexity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I expect to write about this in the future, but here&apos;s a quote I&apos;ve begun to cite with religious zeal and frequency:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;For the simplicity that lies this side of complexity, I would not give a fig, but for the simplicity that lies on the other side of complexity, I would give my life&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This quote explains that there are &lt;strong&gt;two forms of simplicity&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first is the type possessed by those who suffer from Dunning-Kruger&apos;s: you know too little, and thus you think you know it all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second is the type wielded by experts who truly &lt;a href=&quot;https://nabeelqu.co/understanding&quot;&gt;understand&lt;/a&gt;. This form of simplicity has &quot;scaled&quot; the complexity curve. If information is wild, then this form of simplicity is information tamed into a mental model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.planplusonline.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/The-Simplicity-on-the-Far-Side-of-Complexity_blogheader1.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;For humans, complexity is not legible, whereas simplicity is. We desire legibility, but as you can see, one form is good. The other.. is quite bad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;complexity-legibility-and-software&quot;&gt;Complexity, Legibility, and Software&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Software tends towards entropy. With time, as each feature gets added, as each bug gets &quot;fixed&quot;, as developers come and go, the software system inevitably becomes a mess - no matter how pristine it started.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At some point, this complexity and entropy slows the team down. The company yearns for legibility!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Alexander&apos;s review of &quot;Seeing Like A State&quot;, he describes a similar situation in 18th century Prussia:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Enlightenment rationalists noticed that peasants were just cutting down whatever trees happened to grow in the forests, &lt;em&gt;like a chump&lt;/em&gt;. They came up with a better idea: clear all the forests and replace them by planting identical copies of Norway spruce (the highest-lumber-yield-per-unit-time tree) in an evenly-spaced rectangular grid&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And then?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;This went poorly. The impoverished ecosystem couldn’t support the game animals and medicinal herbs that sustained the surrounding peasant villages, and they suffered an economic collapse. The endless rows of identical trees were a perfect breeding ground for plant diseases and forest fires. And the complex ecological processes that sustained the soil stopped working, so after a generation the Norway spruces grew stunted and malnourished. Yet for some reason, everyone involved got promoted, and “scientific forestry” spread across Europe and the world.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sadly, this tale does not only apply to these Enlightenment rationalists. Anyone who has worked on a software team long enough to witness a regime change might resonate with this hypothetical:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imagine a software engineering team who is growing fast, but lacks a CTO. The previous VP of Engineering was well liked, but resigned because he wanted to live in Boulder, CO and be among the rock climbing trails. And so, someone new comes in. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to govern their empire, this new CTO yearns for legibility. After 7 weeks on the job, they demand that all systems be rewritten in Java 7. Because Java 8+ and functional programming is &quot;too hard to hire for&quot; (which is code for the leadership by insecurity).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the bright side, they&apos;ve decided to start small and break up the monolith into microservices - and have chosen a couple of pilot projects to start.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the downside, these projects will be led by the Council of The CTO, which is comprised of a few senior engineers the new CTO has spent the last 7 weeks hiring. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can&apos;t help but notice that this collection of senior &quot;talent&quot; bears striking resemblance to Wormtongue whispering sweet sycophantic yes-man, yes-boss, reality-ignoring stupidity into the ears of the CTO. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://memegenerator.net/img/instances/85070803/we-must-rewrite-in-java-7-my-lord.jpg&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note, however, there is a difference between King Theoden and our hypothetical CTO: the causal relationship of incompetence doesn&apos;t run in the direction of powerful brownnosers leading to degraded leadership skills. Rather, it&apos;s ego-centric leadership leading to a festering entourage of way-too-highly-compensated henchmen, who reign for a brief moment of time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And thus, we begin yet another &quot;High Modernist&quot; attempt at enforcing top down, rectangular grid, central planning on a software codebase. We all know how this disaster ends. The complexity wins, and the floundering CTO and their Council has found themselves thrashing about in &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/themythicalmanmonth/tmmm/tar-pit&quot;&gt;the tar pit&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sigh, one should not dive head first into the tar pit - it&apos;s best to &quot;lay some boardwalks across the tar&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;boardwalks-for-complexity&quot;&gt;Boardwalks for Complexity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;So if hiring Mr. CTO isn&apos;t the way to go, how can we balance our need for legibility without causing an ecological meltdown?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I can&apos;t answer this conclusively, but I&apos;m offering &quot;boardwalks&quot; - some tools that might help this dangerous traversal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-archaeologists-not-architects&quot;&gt;1) Archaeologists not Architects&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to reining in the complexity of software, I believe that there is one truth we are trying to optimize for. It comes from the line in &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.csc.gov.sg/articles/how-to-build-good-software&quot;&gt;How to Build Good Software&lt;/a&gt;&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The main value in software is not the code produced, but the knowledge accumulated by the people who produced it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In many cases, the root cause of disastrous rewrites simply occurs because the people who wrote the first version of the software did not leave a legible trail for the people behind them. In fact, it&apos;s often the case that the trail blazers/code cowboys and cowgirls who wrote the code never even understood the domain themselves, simply brute-forcing, fire fighting, bug squashing, and praying their way to something that was Good Enough™.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the onus of legibility is never on the original crew, the onus is on the team doing the rewrite. This squad must understand the situation on the ground before attacking. Whether or not the original crew left breadcrumbs is irrelevant. They left code and that, sadly, is Your King. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point, you want archaeologists and anthropologists, not architects. Anyone who starts architecting before digging is preparing to swim in the tar pit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-clean-code-and-legibility&quot;&gt;2) Clean Code and Legibility&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;At its core, I believe clean code is simply code that is &quot;legible to humans&quot;. If code is quickly understood by the engineers on your team, and can be modified safely, then I believe it is &quot;clean&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I like this concept because it shows us that legibility CAN be imposed on something, without sacrificing correctness and robustness. In fact, clean code is often more correct and more robust - because the abstractions are in place to add optimizations over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The concept here is that legibility can be achieved at the micro level if we strive for clean code. If new hires can make progress on your code base without much polite complaining, then your code is reasonably clean (i.e. they don&apos;t say things like &quot;The code&apos;s pretty good, although A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K... has slowed me a bit down this week&quot;). If they&apos;re complimenting the codebase, then you know it&apos;s clean (the joke here is that this doesn&apos;t happen).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So micro-legibility is great and all, but we&apos;re really looking for something bigger. Where else can we increase legibility in software without sacrificing correctness?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-the-micro-in-microservices&quot;&gt;3) The micro in Microservices&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As software systems get more complex, they often face &quot;The Decision&quot;. That&apos;s the point in a startup&apos;s lifecycle where there are just too many engineers - and not everyone can coexist happily under one roof.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How a company negotiates the transition to microservices is important. Having seen a failed attempt at this, I have increased conviction that the right way to think about microservices (as with most new things, really) is to start super small.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s how you might start:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Start a new feature as its own tiny microservice (typically when you need new resources and endpoints, not when you&apos;re adding fields to an existing resource)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Refactor tiny, stateless portions of your application into Serverless functions (anything that uses ImageMagick is a fantastic example - thumbnail generation, image resizing, etc. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serverless.com/learn/use-cases/&quot;&gt;Here&apos;s some more&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In these cases, it&apos;s possible to chip away at pieces of the monolith while still preserving most of the hard earned &quot;learnings&quot; of the legacy code. That&apos;s because the ambitions are small. This avoids the hubris of diving straight into the tar pit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-the-strangler&quot;&gt;4) The Strangler &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your ambitions are not small, and you want to finish this rewrite before the next promotion cycle - then good luck, I can&apos;t help you. But if you&apos;re open to the idea that these things will take time, let&apos;s consider, The Strangler.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve written about this in detail &lt;a href=&quot;https://softwarementor.substack.com/p/9-the-strangler-pattern&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, and I don&apos;t wish to rehash everything from then. That said, let me pluck a few choice quotes so you don&apos;t have to redirect off this page:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Thankfully, Azure has put out a great description of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/architecture/patterns/strangler&quot;&gt;Strangler Pattern&lt;/a&gt;... Here’s their illustration of how to use it:&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.substack.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F430262d4-a3b7-4b07-a3c9-729a0e695276_1833x552.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The key point to note is that in this case, the Strangler is a Facade, a  wrapper around both the legacy and “modern” systems. This differs  slightly from Martin Fowler’s formulation. For Fowler, there isn’t  necessarily a Strangler Facade, just a legacy and modern system that  take different amounts of traffic.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legibility is a fascinating idea, especially in the context of complexity. And there&apos;s one thing I haven&apos;t really spoken about yet, which is human systems that are too complex tend to become brittle. Was the Fall of Rome simply the Empire reaching a tipping point of complexity?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And thus, we reach for legibility, not necessarily because we like it and want to look like geniuses, but sometimes, because we have to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t have any answers, but I have offered &quot;boardwalks&quot; that you can place atop the tar pit:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Favor &lt;strong&gt;Archaeologists&lt;/strong&gt;, not Architects&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Strive for &lt;strong&gt;Clean Code&lt;/strong&gt; and Legibility&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Put the micro in &lt;strong&gt;Micro&lt;/strong&gt;services&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;strong&gt;Strangler&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whether or not we can achieve legibility in software is not something I can answer. But hopefully, this article helps us to understand how we can &quot;See Like a Software Engineer&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[feynman-and-dumb-questions]]></title><description><![CDATA[Richard Feynman used to ask some pretty dumb questions. Here's what we can learn from him]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/feynman-and-dumb-questions</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/feynman-and-dumb-questions</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 20:46:36 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/feynman-and-dumb-questions">&lt;blockquote&gt;Some people think in the beginning that I’m kind of slow and I don’t understand the problem, because I ask a lot of these ‘dumb’ questions: ‘Is a cathode plus or minus? Is an an-ion this way, or that way?’&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;-Richard Feynman, &lt;em&gt;Surely You Must Be Joking, Mr. Feynman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I love this quote because it hits upon some of my favorite themes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Go slow, then go fast&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Understand the fundamentals&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But my favorite aspect of this quote is Feynman&apos;s willingness to look dumb. Here, he is probing for seemingly obvious facts, and if this was your first encounter with him, you might start to think this Mr. Feynman wasn&apos;t all he&apos;s been cracked up to be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yet sure enough, Feynman&apos;s mastery of the basics paid dividends:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;[L]ater, when the guy&apos;s in the middle of a bunch of equations, he&apos;ll say something and I&apos;ll say, &quot;Wait a minute! There&apos;s an error! That can&apos;t be right!&quot; The guy looks at his equations, and sure enough, after a while, he finds the mistake and wonders, &quot;How the hell did this guy, who hardly understood at the beginning, find that mistake in the mess of all these equations?&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-willingness-to-look-dumb&quot;&gt;The Willingness to Look Dumb&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The advice here is not &quot;be willing to look dumb&quot;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rather, you should think of &quot;the willingness to look dumb&quot; as a wager - and like all speculative endeavors with probabilistic returns, there&apos;s a chance that you will come out on top, and one where you might tank your confidence into &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/incerto/the-logic-of-risk-taking-107bf41029d3&quot;&gt;ruin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feynman&apos;s willingness to look dumb, I believe, was a bet. One that he felt comfortable taking for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A previously high level of intellectual confidence (such a small wager was relatively inconsequential)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;He knew that his typical ROI from clarifying the basics was positive &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fact that Feyman himself called these &quot;dumb questions&quot; shows how self aware he was. This is not the case of a socially unaware genius just bulldozing his way through life. This was someone who felt the sting of social cues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yet he did it anyways. And he did it repeatedly. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-to-look-dumb&quot;&gt;When to Look Dumb&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imagine that confidence can be banked (think of it as a bank account). And then imagine that &quot;dumb&quot; questions have a price, which is paid in a small amount of confidence. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we ask dumb questions, we take a withdrawl from that confidence bank account.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we have a lot of confidence, then this price is trivial. Go ahead, and ask your dumb questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if you do not have a lot of confidence, you can&apos;t be so nonchalant. You must determine if this question will genereate a positive yield.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So let&apos;s walk through how we can think about this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, let&apos;s consider the cost:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Will these people remember that I asked this question &lt;strong&gt;in 1 month&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Will this question disrupt the flow of conversation for everyone for more than 30 seconds?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the answer is yes to either of these, then this question is relatively expensive. Think twice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, let&apos;s consider the benefits:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Is this question a &lt;strong&gt;clarifying question&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Is this question relatively &lt;strong&gt;fundamental&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Does the answer to this question &lt;strong&gt;help you participate&lt;/strong&gt; in the conversation? That is to say, does the conversation build on top of this?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you answered yes to any of these, then there&apos;s a good chance that the ROI from asking the question will at the very least lead you to break even. In each of these, you will use the knowledge gained a few times in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are some more considerations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Are you &lt;strong&gt;actively curious&lt;/strong&gt; about the answer?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Will you &lt;strong&gt;use the answer to build&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;up a mental model&lt;/strong&gt; of how something works?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you answered yes here, asking a dumb question is almost always a good idea. You&apos;re capturing your own intellectual momentum. The answer will help you understand something better than a Google search because you&apos;re emotionally involved. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strike when the iron is hot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dumb questions can be mortifying to ask. You are trading vulnerability in the present for an unproven potential return in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But building up a practice of asking questions will slowly build up your confidence. Not only that, but asking these uncomfortable questions can actually deepen your understanding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hell, even questions that don&apos;t make any sense can generate positive results. Consider this quote from Randall Munroe (of &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com&quot;&gt;xkcd&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;They say there are no stupid questions. That’s obviously wrong; I think my question about hard and soft things, for example, is pretty stupid. But it turns out that trying to thoroughly answer a stupid question can take you to some pretty interesting places.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(That&apos;s in his foreword to his book &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/What-Scientific-Hypothetical-Questions-International/dp/0544456866&quot;&gt;What if?&lt;/a&gt;&quot;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A lot of us don&apos;t ask enough questions because we&apos;re too risk averse. I hope this post helps you think through the issue a little more clearly - and to start asking more questions.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[ddia-glossary]]></title><description><![CDATA[A glossary of "hard to remember" terms from Designing Data Intensive Applications]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/ddia-glossary</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/ddia-glossary</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 04:38:53 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/ddia-glossary">&lt;p&gt;One of the last ongoing activities of Summer of Shipping is a book club, where we meet weekly to work through the excellent book - Designing Data Intensive Applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, this book is the gold standard for technical writing. Martin Kleppmann commands an expert level understanding of data architectures, yet delivers that expertise in a way that any engineer can follow. This is a great accomplishment with a tremendous &lt;a href=&quot;https://martin.kleppmann.com/2020/09/29/is-book-writing-worth-it.html&quot;&gt;impact&lt;/a&gt; -  it makes the field of databases and distributed systems &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eugenewei.com/blog/2020/9/18/seeing-like-an-algorithm&quot;&gt;legible&lt;/a&gt;&quot; for many.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I love the book - it&apos;s still a book. The medium is the message and it&apos;s not meant to be glanced at for quick recall. Thus, with the help of the SoS cohort, we&apos;ve provided an accompaniment. This effort is ongoing, but the goal here is to provide a glossary of &quot;hard to remember&quot; terms paired with &quot;easy to grasp&quot; explanations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-replication&quot;&gt;Chapter 5 - Replication&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Single Leader Replication&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Semi-synchronous replication&lt;/strong&gt; - A configuration of replicated databases where there is one synchronous follower, and all others are asynchronous. This means there is at least one guaranteed in sync follower, without a terrible performance penalty. It&apos;s a popular configuration&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Failover&lt;/strong&gt; - the process of picking a new leader once a leader has failed. Complications may arise, such as the old leader rejoining after the new leader is chosen (in which case, the old leader&apos;s stale data is discarded, and starts following) and &lt;strong&gt;split brain&lt;/strong&gt; (where multiple nodes think they&apos;re the leader. One of them eventually wins out)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Types of Replication Logs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statement Based replication&lt;/strong&gt; - In this form of replication, statements are streamed to followers as is. It is conceptually easy and compact, but problems may arise when statements use things like rand() and now() and autoincrement. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write ahead log replication&lt;/strong&gt; - this form of replication is done by sending the on-disk representation deltas to followers (recall that the write ahead log is used in crash recovery purposes). This may be a problem if upgrading database versions, but the greater principle is that by coupling the replication log with its representation, you can encounter difficulties (as you loose a degree of flexibility)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logical log (or row based) replication&lt;/strong&gt; - describes the exact changes that are happening on each row. Avoids the problems of statement based (i.e. now and rand) and write ahead (coupling). Similar to write ahead log, this can result in a lot of data streamed to followers&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trigger based replication&lt;/strong&gt; - basically running some code to run some custom replication logic&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Replication Lag&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replication lag&lt;/strong&gt; - the phenomenon where a follower is significantly behind the leader, such that someone who reads from the follower might observe a database that is in an old state.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read-after-write Consistency&lt;/strong&gt; -  when you write to a database you would expect the change to be there upon subsequent reads. This consistency makes that guarantee&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monotonic Reads&lt;/strong&gt; - If several replicas are utilized, we can encounter a situation where some replicas are more behind than others. In such cases, read requests from replica to replica will look like we’re jumping around in time (possibly back in time). Monotonic reads are a guarantee which prevent such jumping around in time&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consistent Prefix Reads&lt;/strong&gt; - If there are two requests A and B, and B depends upon A, then we want to make sure no one sees B, unless they can also see A. This is a causal relationship, and the term “consistent prefix reads” simply means this causal ordering is maintained.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leaderless Replication&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read repair&lt;/strong&gt; - When a client reads a value from multiple nodes and detects a stale value from one of the nodes, they will then write back the correct value to the node that contained the wrong value.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anti-entropy process&lt;/strong&gt; - a background daemon that runs on some datastores that will persistently look for differences in data between replicas and restore them to a consistent state.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quorum&lt;/strong&gt; -  a subset of a cluster that must be in agreement for a decision to be recognized. For Leaderless systems (the Dynamo family of databases), this is w + r &amp;gt; n&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;w + r &amp;gt; n&lt;/strong&gt; - this inequality is a rather sneaky way to guarantee fresh reads. It states that if there are n nodes in a cluster, then the number of nodes that must be written to is w, and the nodes that must be read from is r. If this inequality holds, then ever read will contain at least one of the fresh writes due to &lt;strong&gt;an inevitable overlap&lt;/strong&gt;. Clever&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last write wins&lt;/strong&gt; - a very destructive way to handle concurrent writes, but is conceptually easy to remember as the name describes it perfectly: the last write to the DB should win. Used by Cassandra and optionally by Riak. (&lt;em&gt;Note on Cassandra&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Because Cassandra uses this strategy, it is recommended to make each write operation to Cassandra with a UUID and treat the entry as immutable. This is similar to a log, or event sourcing&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&quot;Happens Before&quot; relationships &lt;/strong&gt;- if we handle concurrent writes with care, we need to keep track of happens before relationships. This is typically done with version vectors&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-partitioning&quot;&gt;Chapter 6 - Partitioning&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hot Spot&lt;/strong&gt; - a partition receiving a unfairly high amount of load, e.g. it receives much more queries than other partitions. The presence of hot spots are antithetical to the goal of partitioning, which is to &lt;em&gt;evenly &lt;/em&gt;distribute data and query load across a set of nodes.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secondary Index&lt;/strong&gt; - an index that utilizes some other information other than the primary key. The keys in a secondary index are not necessarily unique, unlike a primary index.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Document-partitioned Secondary Index&lt;/strong&gt; - each partition maintains its own secondary index for its own data. Writing to the database in this case only requires that you interact with the partition containing the document you are writing to; however this complicates read queries as you must perform scatter/gather&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scatter/gather&lt;/strong&gt; - involves sending a particular query to all partitions (the scatter) and combining the returned results (the gather). This method can make read queries on secondary indices expensive.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Term-partitioned Secondary Index&lt;/strong&gt; - Instead of each partition maintaining its own secondary index, a global index is created covering the data in all partitions and is itself partitioned by term (or hash of the term). This makes reads more efficient, but writing to a document may affect different partitions of the global index.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-note-on-rebalancing-partitions&quot;&gt;A note on &quot;rebalancing partitions&quot;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of thinking of this as rebalancing partitions, a better way is to think of mapping keys to partitions, and then partitions to nodes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea here is to create the partition abstraction that is NOT 1-1 to nodes. This provides flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can define partitions as ranges over the keys (if they’re naturally ranges) or over the hashes of keys (if we’re using hashed keys). Mod N is bad because changes to N cause a lot of partition changes. Once we’ve sliced out P partitions, we can assign them to the N nodes. Generally, P &amp;gt;&amp;gt; N and the assignment of the P partitions to the N nodes is kept in some consensus system. More capable machines can own more partitions than less capable ones and addition of new machines can “steal” partitions from other machines.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Partitions can be dynamically determined too. If there are more nodes, we can choose strategies (e.g. smaller ranges) so that there are more partitions and keep partitions small.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-note-on-routing-to-the-correct-partition&quot;&gt;A note on routing to the correct partition&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supposing we have selected a partitioning scheme (e.g. hash or range keys), how things are routed depends on where the routing information can be: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;with the client&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;with some intermediary&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;or with the final destination&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the client has full awareness of the destinations, it can send requests directly to the correct destination. Sometimes, there are many clients or the clients don’t have full visibility into the destinations. An intermediary like a routing proxy could route to the right place. Otherwise, destinations can function as intermediaries when they receive requests destined for a partition that they’re not responsible for. Some systems are a hybrid of these routing strategies. In all cases, the router must be aware of the possible destinations or at least the next hop and that may require use of a membership system that is typically a consensus system.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[168-hours]]></title><description><![CDATA[I started tracking my time in 15 minute intervals. This is what my practice looks like]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/168-hours</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/168-hours</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 03:33:36 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/168-hours">&lt;p&gt;I started tracking my time in 15 minute intervals. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, I had skimmed through a book by Laura Vanderkam called &quot;Off the Clock&quot; which recommended this practice, and like I do with all good advice, I took it to heart and promptly forgot about it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until last week, when the same mortal fears which drove me to pick up &quot;Off the Clock&quot; in the first place guided me back. And this time, more resolute, and perhaps less intimidated after previous exposure to the idea, I&apos;m happy to say I succeeded in tracking my first week - or 24 x 7 = 168 hours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-benefits&quot;&gt;The benefits&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If time tracking sounds unbearable to you, know that I first thought it was pretty terrible too. Tracking your time is something the boss man would make you do, why would you do it to yourself? Why inflict beauracracy on your own life?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, because there are benefits. After one week, this is what I&apos;m seeing:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&apos;m suddenly aware of idle time&lt;/strong&gt; - previously, when I&apos;ve had unallocated blocks of time, I used to fill them with reading whatever algo-recommended Tweets, newsletters, HackerNews posts, etc. That might easily consume an hour of time. Now, if I have unallocated time, I suddenly become very aware that this time will be filled with an entry in my time tracker that says &quot;Random Internet&quot;, which makes me focus.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things can wait&lt;/strong&gt; - now that I&apos;m thinking about things in terms of getting them done in a given week, there&apos;s less urgency to do things &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. I want to end the week having spent 7 hours reading about MakerDAO. There&apos;s no reason to read it all tonight and blow past my ideal bedtime&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have something to optimize&lt;/strong&gt; - equipped with an exhaustive list of how I&apos;ve spent my week, I&apos;ve begun brainstorming how I can spend my time better. I can see where I waste time (I spent half an hour getting upset at Uber Eats last week, which resulted in no refund and lots of frustration) and adjust&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tracking encourages intention&lt;/strong&gt; - This goes hand in hand with optimization, but once you see how you&apos;re spending your time, you start asking &quot;how can I spend this better?&quot;. Not necessarily in terms of how can I get more out of it, but simply, &quot;did I have a week well spent?&quot;. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So to recap - I&apos;m &lt;strong&gt;more present&lt;/strong&gt; with how I spend my idle item, I&apos;m &lt;strong&gt;less likely to jump&lt;/strong&gt; on a task (so long as it gets done in the week), I can &lt;strong&gt;optimize the micro&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;strategize the macro&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of these were previously goals I wanted, but adopting this practice has given me a way to tackle them all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-practice&quot;&gt;The Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For time tracking, I use a copy of Laura Vanderkam&apos;s 168 hour worksheet (&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1AwIuqaXfZ8fz2y3i5Mcm8d9CdsYLVn--FbU8v70pORU/edit#gid=653777042&quot;&gt;link to her Google Sheets template&lt;/a&gt;). I&apos;ve added some conditional formatting so there&apos;s some color and personalization (which increases my sense of investment in this worksheet):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/168_worksheet_personalization.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;Added some color&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I&apos;m at my computer, I make entries about once an hour:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/168_retroactive_entries.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;What the entries look like&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I leave my computer, I&apos;ll come back in 2-3 hours and try my best to fill in what I did for that chunk of time. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a 15 minute block will contain multiple items. Vanderkam mentions that she often records all of them, separated by commas. I don&apos;t - some items simply get lost in the sands of time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, I can&apos;t remember what I did and I&apos;ll simply write &quot;???&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some tasks also don&apos;t like up perfectly with the 15 minute increments (although I find myself intentionally lining up tasks so they wrap up in 15 minutes).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s not perfect, but that&apos;s not the point. Just having rough record of my time is sufficiently useful for me to get all the benefits I outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And forcing myself to make entries (with a lot of copy paste), just makes me so much more aware of how this entry stacks up against the greater &quot;portfolio of investments&quot; I&apos;m making this week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the coming weeks, I&apos;m sure I&apos;ll learn much more about this practice - for example, if it&apos;s valuable to do for more than just a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But for now, I wanted to write about it and encourage everyone to consider it. The benefits are plentiful, the implementation is straightforward - and all I think you need is a push.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So check out Laura Vanderkam&apos;s time tracking templates (&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1AwIuqaXfZ8fz2y3i5Mcm8d9CdsYLVn--FbU8v70pORU/edit#gid=653777042&quot;&gt;15 min blocks&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1exRsksuzYbni4JTibsxWFCZUjQdu1608Zc4teb-ewhE/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;30 min blocks&lt;/a&gt;), make a copy, change the colors and get tracking!&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[postman-on-technology]]></title><description><![CDATA[Neil Postman warns us that technology is disruptive - not of industries, but of our culture and our wisdom. My notes from his talk in 1998]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/postman-on-technology</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/postman-on-technology</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 04:27:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/postman-on-technology">&lt;p&gt;I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.ucdavis.edu/~rogaway/classes/188/materials/postman.pdf&quot;&gt;this transcript&lt;/a&gt; of a talk delivered by Neil Postman about the dangers of technological change. While the tone is pessimistic, I think everyone working in technology should read it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll summarize and add my analysis to the talk in this post, but seriously, you should go read the transcript.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talk is centered around 5 thoughts on technological change (some I&apos;ve rephrased):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&quot;All technological change is a trade-off&quot;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The benefits of technology are not evenly distributed&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If the medium is the message, then technology changes the message&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&quot;Technological change is not additive; it is ecological&quot;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Technology tends &quot;to become mythic&quot;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-all-technological-change-is-a-trade-off&quot;&gt;1) &quot;All technological change is a trade-off&quot;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea here is that technology is a double edge sword - it is a tool that cuts both ways.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Postman starts by asking us to consider the printing press.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The printing press gave the Western world prose, but it made poetry into an exotic and elitist form of communication. It gave us inductive science, but it reduced religious sensibility to a form of fanciful superstition. Printing gave us the modern conception of nationhood, but in so doing turned patriotism into a sordid if not lethal emotion. We might even say that the printing of the Bible in vernacular languages introduced the impression that God was an Englishman or a German or a Frenchman&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What Postman is leading us to recognize is that technology does not care about culture. And in fact, it is often destructive of culture. Is this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creative_destruction&quot;&gt;creative destruction&lt;/a&gt;, or simply a bankruptcy of wisdom?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-the-benefits-of-technology-are-not-evenly-distributed&quot;&gt;2) The benefits of technology are not evenly distributed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this idea, Postman mentions that technology brings great benefit to some, but inflicts harm to others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By way of analogy, he asks us to consider the blacksmith at the dawn of the automobile. Many believed the automobile would bring them more business, but alas, that is not what happened. The automobile was the beginning of the obsolescence of blacksmiths.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to computers, Postman predicted that the winners of the computer revolution would be large scale organizations like the military, airlines, and banks. But most people would bear some degree of harm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;These people have had their private matters made more accessible to powerful institutions. They are more easily tracked and controlled; they are subjected to more examinations, and are increasingly mystified by the decisions made about them. They are more than ever reduced to mere numerical objects. They are being buried by junk mail. They are easy targets for advertising agencies and political institutions &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, if we look at his warnings, they have played out:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tracking&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Advertisements&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Control&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattstoller.substack.com/p/the-cantillon-effect-why-wall-street&quot;&gt;Cantillon Effect&lt;/a&gt;, which is the phenomenon where newly printed money will first increase inequality before leading to uniform inflation. Quite simply, the new money tends to be received by the rich. The rich will spend this unearned inheritance and cause prices to rise. Eventually, this money will find its way to the poor, but not before they have had to endure a period of higher prices without seeing higher wages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-if-the-medium-is-the-message-then-technology-changes-the-message&quot;&gt;3) If the medium is the message, then technology changes the message&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Postman cites Marshall McLuhan: &quot;The medium is the message&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He describes how writing first shifted the importance away from memory:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;But in a culture with writing, such feats of memory are considered a waste of time, and proverbs are merely irrelevant fancies. The writing person favors logical organization and systematic analysis, not proverbs&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And subsequent technology changes after writing:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The telegraphic person values speed, not introspection. The television person values immediacy, not history&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And finally, this brings us to computers:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;And computer people, what shall we say of them? Perhaps we can say that the computer person values information, not knowledge, certainly not wisdom. Indeed, in the computer age, the concept of wisdom may vanish altogether&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;While that&apos;s harsh, it&apos;s very true that the Internet has changed how we write (shorter pieces, otherwise the visitor bounces - with simple diction). Has it eroded our concept of wisdom?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s a useful question to ponder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-technological-change-is-not-additive-it-is-ecological&quot;&gt;4) &quot;Technological change is not additive; it is ecological&quot;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like Pandora&apos;s Box, once you&apos;ve opened the door to a new technology, there&apos;s no going back - and it permeates through all of life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This point is all about the idea that because technology touches everything, it&apos;s extremely hard to predict the higher order effects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But because we can&apos;t predict the higher order effects, we need to be hyper vigilant. Otherwise, the capitalists who create the systems won&apos;t be worrying about their impact on the culture:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The radicals who have changed the nature of politics in America are entrepreneurs in dark suits and grey ties who manage the large television industry in America. They did not mean to turn political discourse into a form of entertainment. They did not mean to make it impossible for an overweight person to run for high political office. They did not mean to reduce political campaigning to a 30-second TV commercial. All they were trying to do is to make television into a vast and unsleeping money machine. That they destroyed substantive political discourse in the process does not concern them.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Postman is talking about television, but you could easily see him talking about Facebook and Surveillance Capitalism today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-technology-tends-to-become-mythic&quot;&gt;5) Technology tends &quot;to become mythic&quot;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This last point is simply to say that very quickly, technology becomes something of a given - that&apos;s just the way things are. But the truth is, technology and the use of technology is a cage devised for all of us by those who seek to profit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Postman discusses how we take the alphabet for granted:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;I have on occasion asked my students if they know when the alphabet was invented. The question astonishes them. It is as if I asked them when clouds and trees were invented. The alphabet, they believe, was not something that was invented. It just is. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;And likens it to other forms of technology:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;It is this way with many products of human culture but with none more consistently than technology. Cars, planes, TV, movies, newspapers—they have achieved mythic status because they are perceived as gifts of nature, not as artifacts produced in a specific political and historical context&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is dangerous - to accept things the way they are, as opposed to question whether we can have something better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though the talk was from 1998, it might be more relevant now than ever. With &quot;Big Tech&quot; under scrutiny, the tide has truly shifted and we&apos;re all beginning to ask &quot;has all this technology truly made our lives better?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I personally believe that technology will march on, whether we like it or not. New mediums of expression will continue to arise. And we will soon be at the boundary of &quot;supassing&quot; humanity, as gene editing and AI mature with each passing month. That&apos;s a scary thought.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[two-energies]]></title><description><![CDATA[Sometimes, I've got a lot of energy. Othertimes, nothing. They connect together like booms and busts of the stock market]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/two-energies</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/two-energies</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 03:44:32 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/two-energies">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A few months ago in my notes, I talked about having &quot;Two Energies&quot;. I&apos;m feeling it again, so here&apos;s a reprint:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;2020-08-02&quot;&gt;2020-08-02&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I experienced a sharp turn in my energy levels. Monday and Tuesday were great. Then, something happened on Wednesday night.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My ability to think abstract thoughts and generate any semblance of creative work left my brain. I felt like Cinderella when the clock struck 12, or that movie Limitless when the Adderall++ pills began to wear off. The magic faded away and thereafter, I was forced to welcome the reign of tiredness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This happens to me a lot. I seem to operate in two forms, one in which ideas and productivity comes naturally - and another in which  everything is a struggle. I don&apos;t drink caffeine, and maybe that&apos;s part of my problem, but I find that these &quot;two energies&quot; and the transition between them feels a lot like the boom and bust cycle of the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bull market run up to feeling good is rooted in strong  personal wellness fundamentals (good sleep, exercise, diet, and  psychological care), but as the good times roll on, those fundamentals slowly (or quickly) fall by the wayside. Things continue to go well, but a reckoning is awaiting. Lack of sleep. Burnout. Anxiety. A crash. The bear falls into a sudden hibernation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So that&apos;s kind of where I&apos;m at right now. Wednesday was the bust in my boom and bust energy cycle, and the last few days, things went from bad to worse, and here I am trying to re-invest in the fundamentals to get myself firing on all cylinders again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;addendum-on-2020-10-25&quot;&gt;Addendum on 2020-10-25&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week, I felt like I was riding some upward momentum - and then, quite suddenly, I started to feel the wheels coming off. I noticed my average hours of sleep were falling, which was accompanied by some pain in my knees during my morning runs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And it all caught up to me on Friday in a crash.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I think the underlying fundamentals are strong. My poor sleep isn&apos;t due to anxiety (thanks to me newfound &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/books/rewire-your-anxious-brain&quot;&gt;understanding of anxiety&lt;/a&gt;), but poor time management and dumb diet decisions (I&apos;m lactose intolerant and I ate dairy).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a crash, but I&apos;m buying low.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[notes-on-waitzkin-at-sohn]]></title><description><![CDATA[In an interview, Josh Waitzkin shares some wisdom about learning and life. Here are some notes and takeaways]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/notes-on-waitzkin-at-sohn</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/notes-on-waitzkin-at-sohn</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 05:40:16 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/notes-on-waitzkin-at-sohn">&lt;p&gt;I watched a video today that dispensed some great wisdom on learning. It was of Josh Waitzkin being interviewed by Tim Ferriss at the Sohn Conference in 2019:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4r6gr7uytQA?feature=oembed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are my takeaways&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;finish-strong&quot;&gt;Finish Strong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Waitzkin shares that he was once skiing with Olympic gold medalist Billy Kidd when Kidd turned to him and asked  &quot;Do you know what the three most important turns of the ski run are?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most skiiers might say the middle turns. These are often done at the highest speed and greatest intensity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But that&apos;s not it. Kidd said the most important turns are the last three before you get on the lift. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People tend to get sloppy towards the end, but those three turns are what your body is subconsciously internalizing as you ride the ski lift back up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s true in martial arts - when Josh was practicing Taichi push hands (he became a world champion), he would always finish strong and making sure to execute the technique as well as he could before signing off for the day&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The last thing you do is what is going to burn most deeply over night. Harnessing unconscious learning is a huge part of what I do&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This story is fascinating because it reminds me of a video I watched of why Steph Curry is successful. The narrator was a coach at Kobe&apos;s Nike Skills Academy and Steph was a camper. He mentioned that Steph was the most impressive kid there, because he was &quot;meticulous&quot; with everything he did. But here&apos;s a gem:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Probably the most impressive thing that he did - as soon as the workout was over, he would not leave the court until he swished - SWISHED - five free throws in a row. Do you know how hard that is?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rxsdiusm1NQ?feature=oembed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&apos;s great wisdom in making your subconscious work for you. Steph - whether he knew it it or not- had found a way to channel it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-miq-and-your-subconscious&quot;&gt;Your MIQ and Your Subconscious &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Waitzkin introduces the concept of a MIQ or Most Important Question. He says you want to end your day thinking about your MIQ, then you want to relax, and in the morning, brainstorm on the MIQ as the first thing you do. Absolutely no Twitter, no phone use - you want to be &quot;preinput&quot; as Waitzkin mentions. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key is to leverage your subconscious - you want your subconscious to be working on the problem as you sleep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He cites how Earnest Hemingway would leave his work with something &quot;left to write&quot; - whether that was midsentence, midparagraph, or something unfinished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So what does this look like? It might be something like this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;MIQ: Do I intuitively feel like the VP of Sales candidate is an ethical person?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Relax: Stop thinking about the MIQ and go grab a glass of wine with your partner. (The art of letting go is important he says)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Morning: Before your mind gets influenced by any other source, start writing/brainstorming about the MIQ&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea of priming your subconscious is what I think Paul Graham was talking about in his essay &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/top.html&quot;&gt;The Top Idea in Your Mind&lt;/a&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;I think most people have one top idea in their mind at any given time.  That&apos;s the idea their thoughts will drift toward when they&apos;re allowed to drift freely.  And this idea will thus tend to get all the benefit of that type of thinking, while others are starved of it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So finishing your day with your MIQ primed is just another way of feeding your top idea to your subconscious for processing. Jumping on it as the first thing you do in the morning is a great way to see if your subconscious has generated any insights. Maybe not, but you need to give it a chance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And to pick your MIQ - Waitzkin has this little gem of a quote:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Most great thinkers are like a knife through butter, and then they get stuck&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;That &quot;stuck&quot; is your MIQ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;extreme-relaxation-and-then-extreme-focus&quot;&gt;Extreme Relaxation and then Extreme Focus&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll let these quotes mostly speak for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imagine watching a boxer in slow motion:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;If you watch a great boxer, the relaxation before a strike is delivered is incredible&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;How do you apply this idea of extreme relaxation combined with extreme focus?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Most people in high stress decision making industries are always operating at this simmering six or four. As opposed to the unduluation between just deep relaxation and being at a ten. And being at a ten is millions times better than just being at a six&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The idea is if you feel &quot;always on&quot;, you&apos;re capping your energy such that your maximum is a &quot;simmering six&quot;. Waitzkin mentions the importance of being able to operate at a &quot;ten&quot; - and that can make all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my own life, I really think this is true - especially in times of judgement. When you are designing a system or deciding what kind of project to create, you want to make the decision when you&apos;re at a &quot;ten&quot;. If you&apos;re in execution mode, just pure labor, you can probably hang out at that &quot;simmering six&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;self-expression&quot;&gt;Self Expression&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just read these quotes and soak in the wisdom. May they inspire you&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;It&apos;s very easy to follow the mental models of others, or follow the paths of others. And it&apos;s usually disastrous&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;From my perspective the goal is unobstructed self expression. So first we have to understand what self expression is and who we are as a learner. We have to embrace every element of our funk and build around it.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;It&apos;s such a beautiful thing that happens&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;And I think a big part of being all in on something, and falling in love with something so deeply that you&apos;re just eating it, breathing it, you&apos;re sleeping it. You wake up in the morning wanting to do it. You want to train at it. Being just on fire, stoked out of your mind on the thing. It&apos;s this feeling that you&apos;re expressing yourself through what you&apos;re doing.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;If you&apos;re a writer, or a chess player, or writing books and doing brilliant podcasts. If you feel like you&apos;re expressing the core of your being, then it&apos;s beautiful.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;If I&apos;m doing it in a way that someone tells me versus a way that expresses the core of my being - it&apos;s a different world.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;It&apos;s not so easy to get to know ourselves. But I think the art of introspection. Psychologically. Somatically. Is one of the most important that we can take on&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I believe we are not getting enough out of subconscious minds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I like to say that when I am solving a problem, my strategy is mostly to &quot;prime my brain&quot; with all of the facts and algorithms/strategies and just sit there until I have an insight. Of course, I might be doing work like writing down facts or rearranging facts, but what I&apos;m really doing is I&apos;m just playing with the details such that my subconscious can find the solution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I love about what Waitzkin talks about is this deep respect for the subconscious, as well as the deep sense of self expression. Some things cannot be &quot;logicked&quot;. I do not believe you can truly rationalize your way to insights, no matter how logical they appear after the fact. And I know you cannot rationalize your way to discovering what you love in life. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Learn to work with your subconscious. Learn to love the &lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[good-meeting]]></title><description><![CDATA[I'm weird. I love meetings. Here are my tips for having good ones]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/good-meeting</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/good-meeting</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 02:48:06 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/good-meeting">&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m weird. I love meetings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s be clear - I hate bad meetings - perhaps more than I love good meetings. But I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; love good meetings. They can alter trajectories,  bring clarity, and energize a team. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, how do we have good meetings?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;mindset&quot;&gt;Mindset&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first thing I think people get wrong about meetings is their mindset. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meetings are often seen as a place for &quot;discussion&quot; or knowledge sharing - but that&apos;s too dull for my liking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I like to think of meetings as a team sport, where the objective is to agree upon a direction that gets the team fired up and to pair that direction with crystal clear next steps. We want to leave the room energized and ready to execute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s draw an analogy between basketball and meetings:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Basketball&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;Meetings&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;One basketball&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;One speaker&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Scoring&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;Making decisions or Identifying action items&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Passing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;Asking questions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;&gt;Setting screens&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;Mentioning overlooked facts/details&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I could probably stretch this analogy a little bit more, but I think we&apos;re pretty close to its breaking point already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the idea here is that if you view meetings as a team sport, you&apos;re going to stay engaged and get the most out of everyone. When that happens, we accomplish more than if we didn&apos;t work together, which is the entire freaking point of meetings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mindset shift - meetings are a team sport.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At Amazon, Jeff Bezos has implemented the &quot;weirdest meeting culture&quot;  for his executive team. I think it&apos;s brilliant. See the video below (starting at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/KPbKeNghRYE?t=1084&quot;&gt;18:04&lt;/a&gt; mark)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KPbKeNghRYE?start=1084&amp;feature=oembed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It starts with someone writing a six page memo:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;What we do is, somebody for the meeting has prepared a six page memo - a narratively structured memo - that has got real sentences, and topic sentences, and verbs and nouns. It&apos;s not just bullet points. And it lays out and it&apos;s supposed to create the context for what will then be a good discussion&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then the entire team reads the memo, in silence:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;And then we read those memos silently in the meeting. So it&apos;s like a study hall. And we do that, everybody sits around the table. And we read silently for usually about half an hour or however long it takes us to read the document. And then we discuss it. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is done to ensure the execs have read the memo:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The reason we read them in the room by the way, is because just like high school kids, executives will bluff their way through the meeting as if they&apos;ve read the memo... [This way] everyone&apos;s actually read the memo, as opposed to pretending.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Genius. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most bad meetings that I&apos;ve been a part of are bad because people aren&apos;t sufficiently prepared. Engineers haven&apos;t done enough work to understand what&apos;s feasible (not enough reading documentation and prototyping). Product managers haven&apos;t thought deeply about the ideal customer experience and the top customer pain points.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But when everyone is prepared and has done the &quot;homework&quot; (or is it workwork 🤔), then you have a chance of having a great meeting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me use another example to see if I can drive this home (taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2011/03/03/thomas-jefferson-meetings/&quot;&gt;John Cook&lt;/a&gt;). It&apos;s about Thomas Jefferson and the first meeting regarding the founding of the University of Virginia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;When they gathered at that first meeting to hash things out, Jefferson made sure to show up with meticulously prepared architectural drawings, detailed budgets for construction and operation, a proposed curriculum, and the names of specific faculty he wanted to import from Europe.  No one else in the room was even remotely as prepared... &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;His purpose was strategic: to show up at the meeting with something so substantive that everyone else would have to fall back into simply proposing modifications to it&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So by being extremely prepared, Jefferson was able to make tremendous progress. When someone has already done the work of preparing a proposal, it&apos;s so much easier to discuss &quot;diffs&quot; from the proposal, as opposed to starting from scratch. And maybe that&apos;s why Amazon&apos;s memo strategy is so effective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare-an-agenda&quot;&gt;Prepare an Agenda&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ok, so you already know this, but important things need to be repeated: prepare an agenda.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That said, you should leave room for creativity and &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; wiggle room for tangents. It&apos;s frustrating when a meeting organizer is too militant about following an agenda, but that&apos;s a million times better than not having an agenda at all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It only takes a few minutes. Just prepare an agenda.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;take-notes&quot;&gt;Take Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At least one person should be taking notes. If no one is taking notes, the meeting&apos;s value will have a half life of 30 minutes - no matter how good the meeting was, people will forget.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A recording is ok, but nothing beats notes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I like processing my raw meeting notes before sending them out. I whittle down points such that they are concise, and bold every decision and action item for a quick eye scan. It only takes about 5-10 minutes to do and makes sure a great meeting doesn&apos;t go to waste.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-is-not-time-to-socialize&quot;&gt;This is not time to socialize&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;re using meetings to socialize, then your culture is broken. Basketball players don&apos;t play games to hang out. NBA players don&apos;t discuss their favorite TV shows and books during games.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chit chatting with your coworkers is essential for team chemistry, but it needs to be happening outside of meetings (or in the gaps before and after the meeting). Try to eat lunch together. Spend time in 1-1s to get to know each other better. Host happy hours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But when it&apos;s time for meetings, it&apos;s time to focus. Socializing will happen later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are my thoughts on meetings as of October 2020, but I bet they&apos;ll evolve over time.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[writing-day-10-of-30]]></title><description><![CDATA[Today is day 10 of my 30 day writing challenge. Some reflections]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/writing-day-10-of-30</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/writing-day-10-of-30</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 23:56:57 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/writing-day-10-of-30">&lt;p&gt;Today is day 10 of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/30-days&quot;&gt;30 day&lt;/a&gt; writing challenge. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wasn&apos;t feeling like writing today, so I told myself &quot;just get something out there&quot; and keep the chain going.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And on a milestone day like today, I wanted to reflect on a few things I&apos;ve learned so far:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Writing every day is hard&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You have a lot to say&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You need a content pipeline&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Very few people will read your stuff&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Writing enriches your conversations&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-everyday-is-hard&quot;&gt;Writing everyday is hard&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now, it&apos;s taking me around 2-3 hours to produce each post. Some of the lazier posts take just under a couple hours, and my review of &quot;Rewire Your Anxious Brain&quot; was a few days in the making and took upwards of 10 hours, including 7 yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, like I talked about on day 1, there are ways to make it easier: using voice transcription software to &quot;loosen&quot; up your mind, sending emails to yourself from your phone - and a new tip: turn off your computer monitor and just write for 30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The only way to keep this up is to remove your inhibitions. Curb your perfectionism. Don&apos;t start in edit mode - start in brain dump mode - and edit later. The key is to make it easy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-have-a-lot-to-say&quot;&gt;You have a lot to say&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s what I wrote about in the last 10 days:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/talking-to-yourself&quot;&gt;Talking to yourself&lt;/a&gt; - how to make writing easier&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/combinatorial-networking&quot;&gt;Combinatorial Networking&lt;/a&gt; - how to generate more value with 2nd degree connections&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/writing-as-input&quot;&gt;Writing as Input&lt;/a&gt; - trying to write with less of a stick up my ass&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/start-where-you-are&quot;&gt;Start Where You Are&lt;/a&gt; - a mantra I learned from a tweet on Anthony Davis&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/subconscious-emotional-memories&quot;&gt;Subconscious Emotional Memories&lt;/a&gt; - how your amygdala stores memories inaccessible to your consciousness&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/where-are-you-from&quot;&gt;Where are you from?&lt;/a&gt; - my FIRST ever post on being Asian American. I&apos;ve been trying to post about Asian American issues for a couple years now, and I&apos;m psyched I got this piece out there&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/good-teammates&quot;&gt;Good Teammates&lt;/a&gt; - I&apos;ve been thinking about the question &quot;What makes a good teammate&quot; for years, and decided to start compiling some thoughts&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/metawork&quot;&gt;Metawork&lt;/a&gt; - Why is planning so important? I talk about the work before the work&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/books/rewire-your-anxious-brain&quot;&gt;Book Review: Rewire your Anxious Brain&lt;/a&gt; - I&apos;ve been hoping to get those out for weeks, and I finally did. It finally happened&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I thought I&apos;d be struggling to find topics to write about. And that&apos;s true, many days felt like a struggle, but it turns out I had more to say than I thought.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-need-a-content-pipeline&quot;&gt;You need a content pipeline&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I realized is that you need a content pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You need to be constantly thinking &quot;oh, this might be some great content&quot;. This does a couple things. First it makes life a little more interesting as you&apos;re constantly surveying for something to turn into a post. Second, it forces you to learn better, as you only can write a post if you&apos;ve thought clearly and done your research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the other reason you need a content pipeline - it&apos;s the same reason why companies have a backlog of things they will rarely, if ever, get to. A backlog is similar to the &quot;deleted scenes&quot; from a movie, except the items on a backlog haven&apos;t been made yet. They exist as a foil to the actual content that gets created. It&apos;s as if to say, &quot;I chose to write about this topic OVER every topic on the backlog.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That selection, of choosing the topic that you did against everything in your backlog means that you&apos;re more excited about a given topic than everything else on your list. That excitement will shine through, and make your writing better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s good to have options.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;very-few-people-will-read-your-stuff&quot;&gt;Very few people will read your stuff&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;On its best day, my website had 60 visitors. This was almost entirely from Reddit, regarding a book summary I had written (about &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/books/the-boron-letters&quot;&gt;The Boron Letters&lt;/a&gt;). On most days, I get single digits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Very few people will read your stuff and that’s ok. (see the next point for why)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m not gonna lie, a big part of why I’m doing this is to eventually learn SEO. But right now, SEO is such a far out day dream. I have no organic clicks, no back links, and no strategy to get them. My daily visitors routinely number in the single digits, although recently I might be getting closer to 10. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want these numbers to go up eventually, but right now, I don&apos;t really mind if they stay small for a while - the writing itself has been worth it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-enriches-your-conversations&quot;&gt;Writing enriches your conversations&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simply sharing my writing with friends and family has enriched my conversations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At work (and previously in school), I love good meetings when everyone had done the reading and came prepared with their questions, comments, and insights. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I share my content with my friends and family, it’s like I force them to do the reading and now the conversations are primed with rich fodder to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This alone has been worth it, and is the primary reason I write. Sometimes I write with a family member in mind. Other times, it&apos;s a couple friends. But my best stuff, I want to share with someone specific - and when I do that, my writing improves (hard to run the counterfactual, so you&apos;re just gonna have to take my word for it).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I still have 20 days to go! But I’ve already learned a lot from the first 10. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today was supposed to be a “mail it in” day, a cop out, but I kind of like what I have. Will probably do another one of these at day 20, and of course, another one at day 30 (look at me, thinking in terms of a content pipeline).&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[metawork]]></title><description><![CDATA[All things are created twice. Do the metawork so the real work gets done right]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/metawork</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/metawork</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 04:18:46 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/metawork">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you’re going grocery shopping.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You haven’t eaten all day and so when you see the mini cherry strudels at the bakery, you place them in your cart. When you stop by the snack aisle you load up on kettle chips and double stuffed Oreos. By the time you get to the checkout, your cart is loaded with ready to eat, canned, preserved, packaged foods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s never a good idea to go grocery shopping when you’re hungry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the mistake here isn’t the fact that you were shopping under the influence of hunger. It’s that you didn’t come with a list - you didn’t do the work before the work. The metawork.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metawork is generally used in a negative light to refer to useless meetings and mission statement workshops. But despite office workers&apos; disdain for corporate busywork, there is a strong relationship between metawork and the successful execution of the work that follows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why do we need metawork?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s my experience that Stephen Covey was right when he said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;[A]ll things are created twice. There’s a mental or first creation, and a physical or second creation, to all things.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which sounds nice and all, but it’s the consequence of not doing this “mental” creation that puts it in perspective:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;We are either the second creation of our own proactive design, or we are the second creation of other people’s agendas, of circumstances, or of past habits.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So consider again the case of grocery shopping. Without a list, we are subject to the arrangement of the store and the placement of items on the shelves. We are subject to our cravings at the time of shopping. We are reliant on our memory to restock our supplies of eggs or milk or bread. On different days, we will get different results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And all too frequently, the result requires a repeat trip to the store. Do they accept returns for opened boxes of cherry strudel?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;metawork-prevents-stagnation&quot;&gt;Metawork Prevents Stagnation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you go to the gym without a workout plan, you might really break a sweat. Use a machine here, lift some weights there, maybe toss in some kettle bell swings and a few bar bell workouts. But after 3 months of doing this, there&apos;s a good chance you&apos;ll hit stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Plans are worthless, but planning is everything.&quot; Your first workout plan might get an overhaul after just the first session, but it&apos;s the commitment to a certain fitness goal which allows each workout to build on the previous one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;imagination-is-cheap&quot;&gt;Imagination is Cheap&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metawork allows you to imagine different paths before you actually walk down them. It allows you to eliminate possibilities that sound interesting before you have to pay the dear cost of execution. Metawork is a cheap way of avoiding bad outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-do-metawork&quot;&gt;How to do metawork&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once you understand the importance of metawork, your philsophy towards work begins to change. You start hunting for ways to derisk projects and make the task at hand much more approachable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For writing, this is what I do for metawork:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Start with a good question (or questions) about the topic you want to explore&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Turn on a tape recorder and talk to yourself&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Turn off you computer monitor and just write (Optional: a shot of your beverage of choice)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create an outline&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For coding, I&apos;ve found the following helpful:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Generate a list of questions about your unknowns&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Search through documentation to find answers to those questions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rapid prototyping to prove or disprove unknowns&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In both cases, metawork needs direction and the best way to start is with questions. As you answer your questions (via research or doing), you will find those answers simply lead to more questions. And more questions. Until suddenly, you hit a point where rubber meets the road. You have no more questions. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is clarity. Now you&apos;re off to the races.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-example-of-metawork&quot;&gt;An Example of Metawork &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I found myself the beneficiary of metawork done well. In the morning, I spent 5 minutes thinking about a task I had been dreading and avoiding. I asked myself, “what information do I need to gather such that I can turn unknowns into knowns?”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After prototyping a little and gathering more information, it became crystal clear what needed to be done. I estimated that cumulatively, I’d need about 2.5 hours. Once I was done, I found it took 2 hours and 36 minutes. Not bad.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[good-teammates]]></title><description><![CDATA[Working on a good team is a joyful. Over the years, here are a few patterns I have seen in good teammates]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/good-teammates</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/good-teammates</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 18:30:04 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/good-teammates">&lt;p&gt;I think a lot about why teams work well together. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ever since I was a kid, my favorite part of playing basketball was making a pass, which led to a bucket, which led to a high five. It&apos;s not just the assist that&apos;s fun, it&apos;s the entire process - everything before (the trust and chemistry) to everything after (the celebration and reflection).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m drawn to software because it&apos;s a team sport. I hate working alone because such a large portion of my brain is dedicated to teamwork and working solo feels like under utilizing valuable resources. It&apos;s wasteful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But today, I wanted to reflect on qualities of good teammates. Obviously, this list isn&apos;t conclusive, but I intend to elaborate on this concept with time. I expect this will be just one post of many.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-nose-for-value&quot;&gt;A Nose for Value&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is my experience that good teammates have a sense for what is valuable work. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In basketball, people often say a player has a &quot;nose for the ball&quot; - the player happens to be in the right place at the right time. Of course, there&apos;s luck, but when &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bDhoYiaQ200&quot;&gt;Marcus Smart&lt;/a&gt; or Jimmy Butler routinely find themselves making play after play, there&apos;s more than just luck happening. They seem to know where the ball is going to be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Likewise, great teammates have a sense for doing work that matters. With software engineers, it&apos;s a sense for what parts of a codebase are risky - and thus, where we should double down on high quality work, testing, and documentation. It&apos;s a combination of knowing which features get used a bunch, which code paths get executed often, and what parts of the codebase need frequent updating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it means reworking code to get the result into a simpler state. Sometimes it means shipping out something hacky to capture team momentum and boost morale (with a cleanup task in the back of their minds). Sometimes it means spending one hour to document a process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An average engineer will work on whatever comes their way, sometimes optimizing just to optimize. But a good teammate will work on what matters. They won&apos;t always get it right, but you can tell they&apos;re skating to where the puck is going to be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;higher-order-value&quot;&gt;Higher Order Value&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not only do good teammates have a sixth sense for value - they also understand the velocity of value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thinking in terms of velocity is similar to the mindset of &quot;it&apos;s a marathon, not a sprint&quot;- but deeper. In actuality, business is not a marathon. You&apos;re never done. You&apos;re building a system, a lifestyle, a philosophy that can endure. Good teammates understand why we try to introduce process into our work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But it goes deeper than that. Good teammates can see leverage. Again, from the vantage point of software engineers, they understand the value of CI/CD pipelines. They understand the importance of short testing cycles. They understand the importance of well written libraries, and code that can be reused by many aspects of the company. They see a beautiful API and they see combinatorial leverage. They understand that not only can you produce technical debt, you can actually produce technical wealth. They can think &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/chitchcock/1281611&quot;&gt;in platforms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are things you can do to increase velocity and good teammates seek to make those changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And in fact, it goes even further. If someone understands higher order value, they start seeing the value of culture, of hiring, and the forces that shape the processes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remember: position -&amp;gt; velocity -&amp;gt; acceleration -&amp;gt; jerk -&amp;gt; snap -&amp;gt; crackle -&amp;gt; pop&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good teammates see the big picture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;written-communication&quot;&gt;Written Communication&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of the best teammates I&apos;ve worked with are excellent communicators in writing. English isn&apos;t always their first language and their writing might contain grammatical blemishes (which are endearing 🧡), but after reading something they&apos;ve written, you understand the point being made - and quite often, that energizes you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writing is important because it:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Scales&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Demands mastery (or the pursuit of it)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rewards brevity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Can compound (articles can be improved over time; can be referenced in future articles too)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good teammates excel at written communication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;intellectual-honesty&quot;&gt;Intellectual Honesty&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a quality I&apos;ve come to understand from working with bad teammates. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bad teammates frequently obscure the truth. They will often obfuscate concepts such that no one understands exactly what is going on, but they seem to say &quot;don&apos;t worry. Trust me, I know how this works&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, trust is not a bad thing. In fact, it&apos;s a very healthy thing. But the bad thing is when trust is being used as a proxy for mastery before mastery has been demonstrated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You&apos;ll be able to detect this if - after seemingly every conversation with someone, you leave thinking &quot;I don&apos;t understand what&apos;s going on&quot;, or &quot;Hmm, this feels way more complicated than it is&quot;. When you poke and prod, the person maintains the illusion of expertise, but you&apos;re still not any closer to understanding what is going on. Sometimes, the problem is that you need to learn more before it makes sense (especially if you&apos;re junior), but more often than not, you&apos;re dealing with some form of charlatan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My rule of thumb is not to trust someone until they&apos;ve explained a concept to me - in a way that is easy to follow and demonstrates knowledge that is supple and flexible. Until then, I assume I&apos;m either dealing with an average teammate (nothing wrong about that!) or a quack (definitely someone to avoid).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good teammates are intellectually honest. They don&apos;t try to present themselves as experts. There is no insecurity when they admit their limits. But when they talk about something they do understand, it&apos;s a &quot;no flex zone&quot; of pure knowledge transfer. You&apos;ll feel smarter, or at the very least, have a list of topics to research next. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A dangerous caveat is the previously intellectually honest teammate who has grown accustomed to feeling a sense of mastery in their old domain, but is a relative novice in their new domain. Without someone to keep them intellectually honest, they might become a charlatan to maintain the feeling of being a master. This is exceptionally dangerous. So watch out for experienced people changing domains who have an ego.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;emotional-awareness&quot;&gt;Emotional Awareness&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good teammates have good emotional awareness. I think this manifests in at least one of two forms:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Explicit: Honest communication of how they feel&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Implicit: Highly tuned ability to read between the lines&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emotional awareness is important because projects often collapse when the team cannot function effectively. People are not listening to each other. Values are out of whack. It results in people working on opposite things. One teammate might be writing a design doc. Another might be building a &quot;prototype&quot; (which they 100% intend to deploy to production). One teammate might be cleaning up code. Another might be making more messes. Chaos.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good teammates make it clear to the team and their manager how they feel about something. Or, they understand how everyone else feels and skillfully adapt to what the team needs. In other words, they&apos;re either a little blunt (but not quite an abrasive jerk), or they&apos;re great listeners.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, only listening and adapting is a long-term losing strategy. It might help the team in the short run, but it will eat you up inside. You&apos;ll feel bad for not expressing your thoughts and values, grow resentful, and it may impact your performance. It might not be your MO, but if you&apos;re someone who frequently prefers adaptation - start expressing your disagreements with poise and confidence: &quot;If I understand you correctly, you&apos;re saying X. From what I see, I believe the right conclusion is actually Y. Here are my reasons&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t think I captured everything about good teammates in this article, but I like this list so far. The qualities I find important:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A Nose for Value&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Understanding Higher Order Value&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Excellent Written Communication&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Intellectual Honesty&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Emotional Awareness&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A couple undercurrents that cut through all of these is an eye for simplification, valuing truth over ego, and seeing the big picture. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But let me add one more thing before we go - in addition to all of the above, good teammates seem to experience great joy when the team succeeds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like I mentioned to above, one of my favorite parts of playing basketball was giving out high fives. I think another great quality of good teammates is they love to create situations where everyone is high fiving. That might actually be the best measure of team health that I can think of. The number of high fives between members of a team.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;🙌&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[where-are-you-from]]></title><description><![CDATA[My thoughts on the question "Where are you from?"]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/where-are-you-from</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/where-are-you-from</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 22:34:30 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/where-are-you-from">&lt;p&gt;&quot;Where are you from?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I used to hate this question. I hated answering it. I hated talking about it. Most of the time, I gave a fake smile with a canned response, brushed it off as no big deal, and got back to my life. I liked to pretend that nothing uncomfortable just happened. But make no mistake, this question used to strike a nerve.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I get it, you want to know my ethnicity. And I&apos;m proud to tell you that I&apos;m Chinese American. But until recently, this question triggered me and it&apos;s only in the last couple years that I&apos;ve realized why.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Growing up, I ignored race. I attempted to erase all parts of me that weren&apos;t &quot;normal&quot;. And for the most part, I succeeded. I lived my life without thinking about being Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is, until I&apos;d get the question - &quot;Where are you from?&quot;. Instantly, it all came tumbling down. You can&apos;t run from this fact: people see your race before they see you. You are your stereotype before you are a person. It&apos;s just how it is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, this question doesn&apos;t bother me. I&apos;ve stopped pretending that race doesn&apos;t exist. I&apos;ve stopped trying to forget my cultural heritage. I&apos;ve stopped wanting to &quot;fit in&quot;, because the real goal was never to fit in, but to achieve mutual respect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-track&quot;&gt;A track&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I think about the question &quot;Where are you from?&quot;, sometimes I hear the hook from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=10yrPDf92hY&quot;&gt;m.A.A.d city&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Man down, where you from, n***?&lt;br&gt;F*** who you know—where you from, my n***?&lt;br&gt;Where your grandma stay, huh, my n***?&lt;br&gt;This m.A.A.d city I run, my n***&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kendrick has strayed to a part of town where he doesn&apos;t belong - someone else&apos;s turf. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Where you from&quot; is a simple question, but it conveys power. Just in case Kendrick isn&apos;t sure, the questioner makes it explicit: &quot;This m.A.A.d city I run&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, you don&apos;t really understand something until you&apos;ve seen it at its extreme. This hook makes it so clear why I hated the question &quot;Where are you from?&quot;. It&apos;s because the implied answer is &quot;Not here&quot; and the subtext is &quot;Remember, this is my turf&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;roots&quot;&gt;Roots&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;These days, I answer the question &quot;Where are you from?&quot; with my story - Oklahoma born, Texas/Kuwait raised, with roots in Sichuan. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t mind when people are curious about my heritage, in fact, I encourage it. I understand it&apos;s not cool to be Chinese right now, that today, China is the bad guy and Hong Kong and Taiwan are the good guys (in terms of Good Asians 2020 edition, that always shifting classification). But it is who I am, and I&apos;m proud of my roots.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Go ahead, ask me &quot;Where are you from?&quot;. It&apos;s okay.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[subconscious-emotional-memories]]></title><description><![CDATA[Our brains form emotional memories that are inaccessible to our conscious minds]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/subconscious-emotional-memories</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/subconscious-emotional-memories</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 23:18:21 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/subconscious-emotional-memories">&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m currently in the process of writing a book summary for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Rewire-Your-Anxious-Brain-Neuroscience-ebook/dp/B00QG5SW58&quot;&gt;Rewire Your Anxious Brain&lt;/a&gt; and want to share a few thoughts on the Amygdala - the two almond like structures in the brain which are responsible for triggering anxiety and fear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to consciousness, I previously thought we had a conscious brain and a subconscious brain. To me, the subconscious was a single, black box. But what this book helped me realize is that within this black box, there are many components - and the Amygdala is one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most startling fact about the Amygdala is that not only does it &lt;em&gt;trigger&lt;/em&gt; the physiological response of “fight or flight”, it also &lt;em&gt;stores&lt;/em&gt; emotional memories. These emotional memories are entirely inaccessible to our conscious, thinking mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-experiment&quot;&gt;An Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The existence of emotional memories has been known for a long time. In 1911, Édouard Claparède conducted an experiment on one of his patients who had lost her ability to form new memories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the book says:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;One day her physician performed a little experiment (one that wouldn’t be ethical by today’s standards). When he reached out to shake her hand, he stuck her hand with a pin he’d hidden in his palm. The next day, when the woman saw the doctor extend his hand, she quickly withdrew her hand in fear. When asked why she refused to shake his hand, she couldn’t offer an explanation. In addition, she reported that she had no memory of seeing the doctor before. She had no cortex-based memory of an event that would cause her to fear the doctor; but her amygdala had created an emotional memory, and her fear was the evidence of it. (p. 33)&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though the patient couldn&apos;t form new memories, she could form new emotional memories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-this-matters&quot;&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our brains are complex and when it comes to our psychology, it may not be useful to tell someone that their problems are just “in their heads” (even though that is technically true). That’s because the head is made up of multiple systems, and each must be trained via different practices. Meditation is wonderful, but it cannot dislodge a highly negative emotional memory. You do not meditate your way out of trauma (although it will probably help).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ll discuss anxiety much more when I finish the review of the book (along with a survey of the suggested treatments in the book), but for now - I thought it was worth admiring how complex our brains really are - and respecting the importance of emotional memories that exist beyond our consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[start-where-you-are]]></title><description><![CDATA[Making a change? Here's a lesson from Anthony Davis: Start where you are. Use what you have. Do what you can]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/start-where-you-are</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/start-where-you-are</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 20:23:27 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/start-where-you-are">&lt;p&gt;During the finals, the NBA&apos;s social media team shared this story:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Start where you are. &lt;br&gt;Use what you have. &lt;br&gt;Do what you can. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A short story on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AntDavis23?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@AntDavis23&lt;/a&gt; narrated by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DevInTheLab?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@DevInTheLab&lt;/a&gt;, and inspired by Arthur Ashe. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Game 4 ▶️ 9pm/et, ABC &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/8gKCZUYT0R&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/8gKCZUYT0R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; NBA (@NBA) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NBA/status/1313612644880916481?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 6, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s the story of how Anthony Davis emerged from a small, poor, no name community in the South Side of Chicago, by leaning on a philosophy called &quot;The Disciplined Life&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Start where you are. Use what you have. Do what you can.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I thought that was calming. It&apos;s similar to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serenity_Prayer&quot;&gt;Serenity Prayer&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;God, grant me the serenity to accept the things I cannot change, &lt;br&gt;courage to change the things I can, &lt;br&gt;and wisdom to know the difference.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s a concept driven home in The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People with the &quot;Circle of Influence&quot; (what you control) vs &quot;Circle of Concern&quot; (what matters to you) and the story of Gandhi:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Look at Gandhi. While his accusers were in the legislative chambers criticizing him because he wouldn’t join in their Circle of Concern rhetoric condemning the British Empire for their subjugation of the Indian people, Gandhi was out in the rice paddies, quietly, slowly, imperceptibly expanding his Circle of Influence with the field laborers. A groundswell of support, of trust, of confidence followed him through the countryside. Though he held no office or political position, through compassion, courage, fasting, and moral persuasion he eventually brought England to its knees, breaking political domination of three hundred million people with the power of his greatly expanded Circle of Influence.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;re looking to embark on a difficult journey - maybe a career change, or a job hunt, or starting a business - it can feel deeply uncomfortable. If you&apos;re trying to change our society - fighting against systemic racism, or maybe building multi-generational institutions that improve your community - then the state of the world today might overwhelm you. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But in all cases, it&apos;s useful to remember: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start where you are. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use what you have. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do what you can.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;✌️&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[writing-as-input]]></title><description><![CDATA[Day 3 of my 30 day writing challenge, and I'm making a shift in how I think about the pieces I write]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/writing-as-input</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/writing-as-input</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 17:15:52 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/writing-as-input">&lt;p&gt;Today is Day 3 of my 30 day writing challenge - where the goal is to produce 30 pieces of writing on my website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s just a few days in, but I think I’m already seeing the need for tweaks. The first thing that I realized was the tone of my first two pieces were heavy on insights. There’s nothing wrong with an insightful essay, in fact, those are terrific. But I cannot keep up that pace for 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I’m realizing is that the usefulness of a piece is largely determined by the quality of its inputs. The internet philosophers who put out pithy, insightful content (i.e. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval/status/1002103360646823936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1002103360646823936&quot;&gt;Naval&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sive.rs/hellyeah&quot;&gt;Derek Sivers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.akimbo.link/blog/s-6-e-6-the-overton-window&quot;&gt;Seth Godin&lt;/a&gt;, et al) get there by condensing years of experience into tiny morsels for us to enjoy. They are useful primarily because the inputs are so hard earned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the key insight for me was that my 30 day practice shouldn’t just be about &lt;em&gt;generating&lt;/em&gt; insights. Rather, I should be &lt;em&gt;collecting&lt;/em&gt; more observations, links, facts, and research. Instead of focusing only on outputs, I want to enjoy gathering inputs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If cooking is a bit like writing, then writers must also have a practice of sourcing excellent ingredients. A skilled chef might be able to transform humble ingredients into a delectable dish, but delicious inputs allow even the novice to whip up something great.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So moving forward, you’ll notice many more observations, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/books/how-to-take-smart-notes&quot;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;, and initial reactions to things I stumble upon. These next 27 days will be just as much about &quot;writing, as an output,&quot; as it will be about &quot;writing, as an input&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy sourcing!&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[combinatorial-networking]]></title><description><![CDATA[According to LinkedIn, most of us have 50,000 second degree connections. Here's a thought on how to meet more of them]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/combinatorial-networking</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/combinatorial-networking</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 23:14:43 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/combinatorial-networking">&lt;p&gt;On the Meyer&apos;s Briggs scale, I&apos;m slightly more introverted than extroverted. Some might call that an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ambivert&quot;&gt;ambivert&lt;/a&gt;. But whatever I am, I know I like meeting people, but I just &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; doing it at networking events. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&apos;ll talk about a networking strategy I&apos;ve unintentionally been using. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;second-degree-connections&quot;&gt;Second Degree Connections&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2020/liquid-the-soul-of-a-new-graph-database-part-1&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; last week about LinkedIn&apos;s graph database Liquid. The article was interesting to me, but not because of the database. Rather, my attention was fixated on the motivation behind why they needed to build it:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;t&lt;em&gt;he value of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://economicgraph.linkedin.com/&quot;&gt;economic graph&lt;/a&gt; for the average member lies mostly in their second degree network&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;LinkedIn needed a proprietary graph database because they wanted to help customers get more connected with their second degree connections - apparently, the most valuable type of connection. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How large and how valuable?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;the set of second degree connections is typically at least 50,000 entities (e.g.,people, schools, employers). It is large enough to be diverse, but at the same time, actionable: you are one new connection away from something that can happen. In fact, your next job is probably in your second degree network.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;50,000 is a lot. That&apos;s much larger than a solid Twitter following. That would be a very significant mailing list. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the fact that these connections can be made via a warm intro - that&apos;s pretty eye opening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;combinatorial-opportunity&quot;&gt;Combinatorial Opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being connected to 50,000 people indirectly vs being connected to 50,000 people directly is obviously a very different level of connection. But the point still stands - most of us are far more connected than we might think we are.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consider, for a moment, the network expanding events that may have happened in your life:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Going to college&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Changing jobs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Moving to a new city &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Joining a club&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Attending a class after work&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you look around at the people in your life, there&apos;s a very good chance they have walked extremely different paths from you. What does that mean? Well, it means your network is packed with dormant, combinatorial opportunity:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if you asked your &lt;strong&gt;current coworkers&lt;/strong&gt; to introduce you to &lt;em&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;former coworker&lt;/strong&gt; of theirs&lt;/em&gt; that they loved working with? And of course, you&apos;d return the favor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if you asked some &lt;strong&gt;college friends&lt;/strong&gt; to introduce you to &lt;em&gt;one person they&apos;ve met &lt;strong&gt;since school&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; that they think you&apos;d get along well with? And again, you&apos;d do the same.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if you asked your new &lt;strong&gt;friend from cooking class&lt;/strong&gt; (or whatever class you&apos;re taking these days) to join your &lt;strong&gt;college friends&lt;/strong&gt; for a discussion on travel (or whatever people talk about these days)?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can see where this is going - take people you know from one context, and intentionally connect them to people from another. Meanwhile, asking if they can do the same for you. There are A LOT of context combinations!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of us do this already, but it only happens once in a while. But what it we did this &lt;em&gt;intentionally &lt;/em&gt;and&lt;em&gt; frequently&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping Up&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, you might see where this is going - but let&apos;s start combinatorial networking right here - you and me!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;re a first degree connection, message me and let&apos;s trade combinations! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we haven&apos;t met before, just reach out -  cite this article (or anything from this website) in a Twitter DM and let&apos;s set up a time to meet!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cheers all 🍻&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[talking-to-yourself]]></title><description><![CDATA[Writing online can be scary. If you're freezing up, here's a tip to make it more approachable]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/talking-to-yourself</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/talking-to-yourself</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 23:00:04 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/talking-to-yourself">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today, I&apos;m starting a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://pliao39.com/30-days&quot;&gt;30 day challenge&lt;/a&gt;: one post a day on my website. This is day 1/30.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you first start writing online, it can feel like everyone is watching. Yet when you check your stats, it turns out that no one is watching. Thus, getting started feels like you&apos;re writing to both everyone and no one, whichever one makes you feel worse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The combined stage fright and lack of attention might be enough to paralyze you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;re freezing up, here&apos;s one strategy that can help - talk to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;talking-to-yourself&quot;&gt;Talking to Yourself&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I&apos;m stuck, I often find myself reaching for the voice transcription app, &lt;a href=&quot;https://otter.ai/&quot;&gt;Otter&lt;/a&gt;. Talking to yourself is the easiest way to get unstuck. It&apos;s a combination of therapy, planning and discussion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/otter_ai_list.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I&apos;m feeling bad and need to work through some stuff on my mind. Other times, I&apos;m excited and simply need to organize my thoughts. A lot of the time, it&apos;s a combination of both.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the screenshot above, I&apos;ve recently gotten in some therapy and long term planning sessions with Otter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What&apos;s great about Otter is you can glance over the transcription and quickly jump to relevant sections. In fact, you can even search your recording (assuming the transcription quality worked for you). It&apos;s not perfect, but it saves you from having to listen to the entire recording just to find where you might have talked about Wu Tang Clan:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/otter_wu_tang_search.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;When did I mention Wu Tang again&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The content from talking to yourself might just be the perfect starting material for your next post. Give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;email-yourself&quot;&gt;Email Yourself&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another way I&apos;ve been talking to myself is via daily morning emails composed from my phone. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I start off with a &quot;brain dump&quot; for anything on my mind, and then write a list of tasks I know I need to get to. As a productivity system, it&apos;s less than ideal, but as a way past writer&apos;s block, it&apos;s very useful. For example, this was my email today:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/talking-to-yourself_email.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;Today&apos;s email to self&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&apos;s something about writing on my phone that removes paralysis. Kind of like how the &quot;Sent from my iPhone&quot; signature gave people the license to have typos in their emails, writing this email from my phone relaxes me and allows me to write.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On occasion, my brain dump actually gives me topics to write about. If you look closely, today&apos;s brain dump mentions &quot;I need more essays on my website&quot; - and that ended up being the germ which became this post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-it-easy&quot;&gt;Make it Easy&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writing online is tricky, and there&apos;s a lot more that goes into it than simply writing and pressing publish. But it&apos;s even harder when your brain is conspiring against you to make it seem scarier than it actually is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To get past that fear, I find that talking to myself (either via Otter or Email) is extremely effective. It gives me more ideas, puts me at ease, and overall - allows me to continue pushing forward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;re looking to write online, but aren&apos;t sure where to start, try talking to yourself first. You might just stumble upon an idea you&apos;re excited to share with the rest of us.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[30-days]]></title><description><![CDATA[What can you do in 30 days? It turns out - quite a lot. Here are some stories of people who catalyzed big changes with 30 day challenges]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/30-days</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/30-days</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 18:40:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/30-days">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I watched a short TED talk called “Try something new for 30 days”: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UNP03fDSj1U?feature=oembed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s a nice message of things you can do in 30 days, but ends with a wake up call:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;I guarantee you the next 30 days are going to pass, whether you like it or not&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I heard that, I panicked. It spurred me to research 30 day challenges - and so, here we are.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presenting five inspiration stories of what you can do in just 30 days:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-bootstrap-a-business&quot;&gt;1) Bootstrap a Business&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pieter Levels is a solo internet entrepreneur who makes hundreds of thousands dollars a year (and publishes his numbers &lt;a href=&quot;https://nomadlist.com/open&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). He’s a digital nomad and lives the dream of not having a boss and traveling the world. He’s a success and inspiration to so many entrepreneurs across the world. But did you know that his story got started with a… you guessed it, 30 day challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He didn’t call it a 30 day challenge, but rather, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://levels.io/12-startups-12-months/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;12 Startups in 12 Months&lt;/a&gt;”, but that’s basically just twelve 30 day challenges in a row. The businesses that account for the majority of his revenue were started in just 30 days!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-learn-to-dance&quot;&gt;2) Learn to Dance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IKxElccv0d8&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;Ashly Perez learned to dance in 30 days&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now I know she had excellent instruction, but that doesn’t take away from the work she put in. At the beginning of the YouTube video, Ashly was AWKWARD. She walks awkward, she moves awkward, and her vibe is awkward. But by the end - just watch it for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IKxElccv0d8?feature=oembed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-launch-a-youtube-channel&quot;&gt;3) Launch a YouTube Channel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes Theory is a YouTube channel with over 5 million subscribers but they got their start with a 30 day challenge of their own:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yDBWDrY22Tc?feature=oembed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2015, as new grads discontent with the idea of applying for jobs they had no interest in, Thomas, Matt, Amar, and Derin, decided to do something different. They got together, brainstormed 30 things they had never done before and spent the next 30 days making videos of each. The series became a hit, and it launched their channel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The origin story of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://socialblade.com/youtube/top/5000/mostsubscribed&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;1,695th largest YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; started with a 30 day challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-get-in-shape&quot;&gt;4) Get in shape&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is probably the most common category, but I&apos;ve found dozens of videos and apps that all are focused on the 30 day timeframe:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://30dayfitness.app/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;https://30dayfitness.app/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cCjwIhh83jI&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;30 Murph&apos;s in 30 Days&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BCuwDhmiOFQ&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;Work out like Chris Hemsworth for 30 Days&lt;/a&gt; (this is impressive)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pnqO8sh7ztc&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;100 Burpees for 30 Days&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got so inspired by one of them, that I’m starting my own “100 Burpees in 30 days” challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Update 2020-10-13: I&apos;ve completed multiple 30 day exercise challenges, and while I don&apos;t recommend it as a long term strategy, it works wonders to kickstart your commitment to fitness!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-write-a-novel&quot;&gt;5) Write a novel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;(OK, I stole this one from the TED talk)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All across the country, every November, thousands upon thousands of aspiring novelists commit to writing 50,000 words - enough for a manuscript of a novel. And many succeed! You might have heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Novel_Writing_Month#Published_NaNoWriMo_novels&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Water-Elephants-Novel-Sara-Gruen-ebook/dp/B003I1WY2A/ref=pd_sim_ebk_14_1/141-2356308-5486001?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;pd_rd_i=B003I1WY2A&amp;amp;pd_rd_r=2e46474b-09f8-4efa-997b-4c6cb1671924&amp;amp;pd_rd_w=WCj3V&amp;amp;pd_rd_wg=uZFrt&amp;amp;pf_rd_p=dc5f8131-4953-4e94-b701-14887e2f8999&amp;amp;pf_rd_r=A7RQ7JT5M2MTG3NR1APF&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=A7RQ7JT5M2MTG3NR1APF&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;Water for Elephants&lt;/a&gt; (New York Times Best Seller for 12 weeks)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Night-Circus-Erin-Morgenstern-ebook/dp/B004J4WKTW/ref=sr_1_2?dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=The+night+circus&amp;amp;qid=1585261608&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sr=1-2&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;The Night Circus&lt;/a&gt; (New York Times Best Seller for 7 weeks)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Wool-Omnibus-Kindle-Motion-Silo-ebook/dp/B0071XO8RA/ref=sr_1_3?crid=27CP7ZTYEPQOC&amp;amp;dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=wool+hugh+howey&amp;amp;qid=1585261625&amp;amp;s=digital-text&amp;amp;sprefix=wool%2Cdigital-text%2C175&amp;amp;sr=1-3&quot; rel=&quot;noopener nofollow ugc&quot;&gt;Wool&lt;/a&gt; (A self published success with over 15K+ reviews on Amazon)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/30days_books.jpg&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;Books that got started with a 30 day challenge&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;They all got their starts in just 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-wrap-it-up&quot;&gt;To wrap it up&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&apos;s obviously much more behind the scenes - Pieter had started unsuccessful online businesses in the past. Novelists incubate ideas and refine their skills over years. Yes Theory didn&apos;t create their sense of humor during the 30 day challenge, that was in place before they started.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still, a 30 day challenge was the catalyst they all needed to make a big change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;30 days is short enough to feel manageable, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.695.830&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&quot;&gt;long enough&lt;/a&gt; to start changing your brain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So - how are you going to spend the next 30 days?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[airpods]]></title><description><![CDATA[Some lessons from AirPods: small delights, naming matters, real life virality]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/airpods</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/airpods</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 01:08:13 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/airpods">&lt;p&gt;Apple AirPods are wildly successful. Everyone seems to have a pair. Estimates show that revenue generated from AirPods is hitting an annual run rate in the billions. If AirPods were a startup, it’d easily be a decacorn. Not bad for a product that was widely panned by Silicon Valley (except Chris Messina, who proved &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/chris-messina/silicon-valley-is-all-wrong-about-the-airpods-8204ede08f0f&quot;&gt;prophetic&lt;/a&gt;) at its launch in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What lessons can we draw from a product that has infiltrated the ear canals of millions, with projections to reach tens of millions more? Here are three:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Small Delights&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Naming Matters&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Real Life Virality&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-delights&quot;&gt;Small Delights&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I first started using AirPods, I noticed small delights:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The charging case’s magnetic snappiness&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Seamless pairing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A battery indicator appearing on your iPhone when the case is opened&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The “AirPods have graced your ears” sound when you put them in&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pause on removal&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A tiny green light on the case that tells you everything is alright, and the smooth fade to orange when the AirPods return home to charge&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fast charging&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The case’s smooth contours&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;By themselves, none of these details is enough to win you over, but in their aggregate, AirPods deliver a cascading combo of magic moments that leave you enchanted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stack magic moments and customers will fall for your product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;naming-matters&quot;&gt;Naming Matters&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in 2016, AirPods was a new product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s imagine for a moment that they were instead named Apple Buds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would the product still have taken off? Probably.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But doing so would have been a wasted opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A name is a young products’ most effective marketing weapons. It can evoke an emotion or feeling (Fast, Uber). It can be suggestive of a style or aesthetic (Warby Parker -&amp;gt; Hipster). It can also hint at a product’s function.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the case of AirPods, by channeling their own history (the iPod), and mashing that with a word that previews the product’s primary value add (Air = wireless), Apple generated an iconic name that practically explains the product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Apple Buds - Conveys, these are some earbuds from Apple&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Apple AirPods - Conveys, this is some wireless device that is important for music&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Names matter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How do you pick a great name? I don’t think there’s a formula you can follow (or at least, I know of none). But here are some thoughts on good names.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;They are easily pronounceable (for the target audience)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;They hint at the products’ function&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;They utilize good metaphors&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;They have character&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;An example of a product that has all of these:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stripe - uses a playful metaphor (the magnetic stripe on a credit card)  to hint at the product’s function&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Character is undoubtedly the most tricky thing here, but I think it’s often the most important. Could a story be told about how a customer uses your product? Does your product’s name fit in this story? Does it flow naturally, or does it sound misplaced? If it fits, you’ve probably got a winner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That said, here’s a process you CAN (and probably should) follow. Pick a fallback name (Apple was a fallback name) and stick with it until something better comes along. Stripe was originally called dev/payments, until one day, they figured to call themselves Stripe. When you stumble upon a name that’s so much better than the fallback, the decision to change will be effortless.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;real-life-virality&quot;&gt;Real Life Virality&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;AirPods are viral. They’re bright white and stand out in a crowd. Simply by using them, AirPod owners are providing Apple with free impressions on future potential customers. Every time someone walks onto the subway wearing AirPods, someone else goes “Hmm, those AirPods are everywhere”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact, I wouldn’t be surprised if AirPod adoption is higher in places where public transportation use is high. Or, perhaps, among cohorts of people who utilize public transportation versus those who commute in solitude (i.e. driving).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Andrew Chen recently wrote about this &lt;a href=&quot;https://andrewchen.co/irl-channel/&quot;&gt;IRL Channel&lt;/a&gt; of growth. It’s the phenomenon where digital products, when used in the real world, form impressions on new customers and spur further growth. This is a type of virality enjoyed by AirPods, Uber/Lyft, Amazon Echo, and others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is there an element of real life usage in your product? Can you accentuate it?  Red JUMP bikes stand out more than other bike share products. The neon pink Lyft mustache dashboard lights stood out more than whatever Uber was doing at that time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on real life virality!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The success of AirPods cannot be attributed to only these three elements (i.e. Apple removed the headphone jack from the iPhone!), but consider them useful tools if you’re trying to create a blockbuster product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy hacking!&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[itchier]]></title><description><![CDATA[Should you "scratch your own itch" before validating the market?]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/itchier</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/itchier</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 20:40:33 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/itchier">&lt;p&gt;Successful entrepreneurs solve their own problems:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shopify&lt;/strong&gt; - Tobi wanted to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tobias_L%C3%BCtke#Career&quot;&gt;sell snowboards online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nomad List &lt;/strong&gt;- Pieter &lt;a href=&quot;https://levels.io/product-hunt-hacker-news-number-one/&quot;&gt;wanted to find&lt;/a&gt; good travel destinations for digital nomads like himself&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stripe&lt;/strong&gt; - The Collison brothers had sold their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/auctomatic&quot;&gt;last business&lt;/a&gt; and realized how difficult it was setting up online payments&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basecamp&lt;/strong&gt; - Jason’s web consultancy &lt;a href=&quot;https://basecamp.com/about/story&quot;&gt;couldn’t find project management software&lt;/a&gt; that stuck. Borne of frustration, they built their own.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Airbnb&lt;/strong&gt; - Joe and Brian &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.airbnb.com/about-us/&quot;&gt;couldn’t make rent&lt;/a&gt;, but they had an extra airbed&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, they “scratch their own itch”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this advice everywhere. So much so you might have grown numb to its wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I know I did. I saw it so many times, I began to confuse &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mere-exposure_effect&quot;&gt;familiarity with understanding&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it meant:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Find one of my problems&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;See if others also have the problem&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Test if they’re willing to pay for it.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;But that’s not what it means. All “scratch your itch” means is solve your own problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Full stop. Nothing else. Nothing about finding paying customers. Just scratch your own itch, and no more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;makers&quot;&gt;Makers&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What?! That’s the opposite of everything I’ve read about validation!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You see, something important needs to happen first - a change within your own mind. Instead of focusing on making money, you need to focus on making. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiehackers.com/podcast/140-arvid-kahl-of-feedbackpanda&quot;&gt;an IndieHackers podcast between Courtland Allen and Arvid Kahl&lt;/a&gt; and they both talked about the importance of finding a good market. In the past, they worked on unsuccessful businesses and didn’t want to repeat their mistakes. And thus, it was important for them to start a business with the wind behind their backs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s essential advice. But notice a key detail - they had failed at previous endeavors (Arvid around the 45:00 mark, Courtland mentions his past stumbles on the podcast all the time). They were &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;makers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;metamorphosis&quot;&gt;Metamorphosis&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, I conflated coding ability with being a maker. They are not the same. Working at a startup doesn’t make you one either. In fact, you can be a maker without knowing how to code. A maker is someone who lives this entire process: ideation, building, &lt;strong&gt;shipping&lt;/strong&gt;, engaging passionate fans, and incorporating &lt;strong&gt;feedback&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s an &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/identity-based-habits&quot;&gt;identity&lt;/a&gt;, a habit, not a skillset. And once you do all of that, something fascinating happens:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You get &quot;itchier&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You start seeing more solvable problems - you get more and&lt;strong&gt; better ideas&lt;/strong&gt;. Which motivates you to build and &lt;strong&gt;ship&lt;/strong&gt; and get more &lt;strong&gt;feedback&lt;/strong&gt;. And when you do, you get itchier again. It&apos;s a virtuous cycle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is it the most efficient? Probably not. But you gotta start from somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[idea-to-product-hunt-launch]]></title><description><![CDATA[Built a "throwaway project" to get a feel for launching on ProductHunt]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/idea-to-product-hunt-launch</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/idea-to-product-hunt-launch</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 21:58:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/idea-to-product-hunt-launch">&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I launched &lt;a href=&quot;http://emojicp.com/&quot;&gt;Emoji cp&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.producthunt.com/posts/emoji-cp&quot;&gt;Product Hunt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It finished the day 13th out of 20 products with 67 upvotes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not bad for a 3 day project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More importantly, I learned a couple things about Product Hunt and I wanted to share:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;60 Character Pitch&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Voter Turnout&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Be Consistent&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;60-character-pitch&quot;&gt;60 Character Pitch&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most important asset you&apos;ll need for Product Hunt is a tagline - your 60 character pitch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, the thumbnail can steal the show, but Product Hunt is a battle of taglines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down a Product Hunt Launch widget:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/nLASNG57SeZRsI4uy5wJHvEtSzRcoa5aVSWjTtIVZ0VguWgx2cdxhDbwT1o2ISRRbCakG1VHisc55rvnJ7J4g2v_yuEf6deslKSV6ZwrPYKWbnMX3cBVL5Ms9paqi4LXAWRCkRDK&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are six things here:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Thumbnail&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Title&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tagline&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Categories&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Comment count&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Upvote count&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;And you can control 4:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/VQpKoDiM_EzWU0Dz2tsK-tFqPGZeoIidZN17eBBpZIDdyTR66BpKdPJh0ZUjhr_H5r72ke9TrELe4EeipHoplG_4QAJKVLPJpbS_MWT5sult9iRMkmKr0MwzcRGSb1wo6DbbdLb_&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There’s a good chance you’ve already chosen a name (a url is required for submission), and the categories leave little room for creativity. Thus, you’re left to experiment with the thumbnail and the tagline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m no master of the thumbnail, but I have a tip for the tagline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the constrained real estate, there’s only space to convey your &lt;em&gt;differentiated&lt;/em&gt; value. What makes your product pop?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To jumpstart your brainstorm, here are products with taglines that rock:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Superhuman - The fastest email experience ever made&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Good Eggs - Absurdly fresh groceries, delivered&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Yellowtail Wines - Great tasting, quality wines for everyone to enjoy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;DuckDuckGo - The search engine that doesn’t track you (informal tagline)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice how they all differentiate themselves:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Superhuman is &lt;strong&gt;faster&lt;/strong&gt; ⚡️&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Good Eggs is &lt;strong&gt;fresher&lt;/strong&gt; 🥬&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Yellowtail Wines is &lt;strong&gt;more approachable&lt;/strong&gt; 👋&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;DuckDuckGo is &lt;strong&gt;more private&lt;/strong&gt; 😎&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you launch, prepare your hard-hitting, differentiated 60 character pitch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;voter-turnout&quot;&gt;Voter Turnout&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just lied when I said you can only control 4 sections in your launch widget (sorry!). The upvote count is actually a bit more in your control than you might think.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Product Hunt’s launch guide (&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.producthunt.com/how-to-launch-on-product-hunt-7c1843e06399&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) encourages you to reach out to friends on Facebook and followers on Twitter. They discourage asking for upvotes, but encourage organic, authentic sharing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For Emoji cp, I made a Twitter post, which 3 friends presumably saw, as they upvoted Emoji cp within an hour. I can’t tell if they enjoyed the product, or if they were showing their support (or both), but their upvotes made a difference! (Thanks guys ❤️)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the first hour of launch, products jostle for position. In a hierarchical game like Product Hunt, products at the top accrue advantages. This is for a couple reasons:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Traffic&lt;/strong&gt; - many people never scroll past the 5th product. Furthermore, products in the bottom half are hidden behind a “load more” button. Thus, products at the top receive an unfair amount of traffic compared to products at the bottom. Assuming your widget converts at a fixed percentage: More traffic (🚦) = More upvotes (⬆️).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Influence&lt;/strong&gt; - when a product has a lot of upvotes, it influences others to give it more of a chance. Some people will upvote only once there are sufficient upvotes. (Subconsciously, I&apos;m kind of like this). So really, More upvotes = Better conversion! The power of the herd is strong 🐮&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early upvotes from friends and followers give you an early boost in the rankings. And then, the benefits of increased &lt;strong&gt;traffic&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;influence&lt;/strong&gt; start working for you, not against you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Voter turnout matters - get your constituency behind you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Btw, if you’re launching a product on Product Hunt, make sure you let me know. Knowing what I now know, I&apos;ll help you out! &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;be-consistent&quot;&gt;Be Consistent&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emoji cp’s Product Hunt launch had one big problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tagline on the website and the tagline on Product Hunt were different.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Website: Search for emoji. Click (or press Enter) to copy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;ProductHunt: Find and copy emoji, fast&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If customers like your product, they’ll want to tell their friends. When they do that, they’ll use some variation of your tagline. If you have multiple taglines, customers need to decide which one to use - &lt;strong&gt;IF&lt;/strong&gt; they can even remember any of them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have one way of talking about your product. Use it as your Product Hunt tagline. Put it on your website. Use it in your tweets. Be consistent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Caveat: you want to avoid semantic satiation. So on the same page, do not use the tagline 25 times. Rather, the idea here is to keep a consistent tagline across &lt;strong&gt;distinct&lt;/strong&gt; impressions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A successful Product Hunt launch can accelerate your product&apos;s adoption by weeks - and it&apos;s useful to get it right. Emoji cp was a fun side project of mine, so I didn&apos;t take it as seriously as others on Product Hunt do. That said, I learned some serious lessons:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;60 Character Pitch&lt;/strong&gt; - differentiate yourself with a value-dense tagline&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voter Turnout&lt;/strong&gt; - Upvotes beget more upvotes, so get your people out to the polls&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Consistent&lt;/strong&gt; - Make it easier for word of mouth to take off and be consistent with your language&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, it&apos;s important to note that Product Hunt’s greatest strength is also its greatest weakness. Product Hunt drives traffic to you. It’s good at answering the question: “Do a lot of people like this product at least a little bit?”. It does not really give you an answer for the more important question: “Does anyone love this product?”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For true insights, you need to listen to your fans. The comments section on Product Hunt is helpful (I received two roadmap suggestions that hinted at where Emoji cp should go), but you’ll need to dig for insights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, the most important piece of customer feedback I received wasn’t on Product Hunt at all! It came from a post I made to MakerLog:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/3SMhng0QHQpD1AeQdfV3cwwxSveAbUFgLc4ooadWZ6TV3RY_RB3ZBNCWlI9QuDCjUqtHHDGwXbWatygpZGjhME9AVcfgk0OXLfDstAjRb3ktbr3xyMiv-ZiV182QZlazbuegDpP0&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which led to a fellow Maker to send out this tweet:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-embed-card&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Been using &amp;quot;Emoji cp&amp;quot; all day and totally loving it&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;⌨️ Type to search, up/down arrows to select, Enter to copy&lt;br&gt;👐 No need to lift hands off keyboard&lt;br&gt;🖱️ Mouse usage optional&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;⚡ Fastest emoji site i&amp;#39;ve used by far!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/7oCGOfAXRL&quot;&gt;https://t.co/7oCGOfAXRL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;creator: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pliao39?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@pliao39&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/7TUJGLviLq&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/7TUJGLviLq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Carl Poppa (@poppacalypse) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/poppacalypse/status/1206471682539409408?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This singular tweet was arguably just as important to me as the Product Hunt launch. The value proposition was validated (at least by one user), and it made it 💯% clear to me what made Emoji cp different.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;A successful Product Hunt launch is great, but remember that it&apos;s just a start. Leverage that influx of users to find your true fans - and that&apos;s where the real work begins.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy Hunting!&lt;/p&gt;</content></item><item><title><![CDATA[job-search]]></title><description><![CDATA[The story of how I landed at Uber. At a glance: 65 days, 18 companies, 9 onsites, 3 offers. Lots of details for job seekers]]></description><link>https://pliao39.com/job-search</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://pliao39.com/job-search</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Liao]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 06:38:00 GMT</pubDate><content type="html" xml:base="https://pliao39.com/job-search">&lt;p&gt;This is the story of my job search. I shed light on the entire process, from generating a list of companies, to getting offers and all the trials in between. For job searchers, I hope this will: 1) serve as a useful reference and 2) be a voice of comfort on those (inevitable) discouraging days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Duration: 65 days (spanned 10 discrete weeks)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Location: San Francisco/Bay Area&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Role: Software Engineer (Backend or Full-stack)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My background/experience: 3 years of Full-stack experience. Non-traditional background (Economics degree)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;18 companies contacted&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;13 Recruiter Screens&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;11 Technical Phone Screens&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;9 Onsites&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;3 Offers&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;44 technical assessments (including take homes)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;25 non-technical assessments (Recruiter screens, behavioral interviews)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pliao39.s3.amazonaws.com/job-search_summary.png&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the spreadsheet with my information&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1bxEsnmu3G26o-OjhyL0jT2bayUXgjgOtV4nUScl9SlY/edit#gid=0&quot;&gt;Here’s a link to the spreadsheet in the image above.&lt;/a&gt; It also includes data from my roommate who also recently went through a job hunt (although his data isn’t quite as detailed)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Story time:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&quot;weeks-1-2-homecoming-networking-and-starting&quot;&gt;Weeks 1 &amp;amp; 2: Homecoming, Networking, and Starting&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;On January 24, 2018 at 9AM I arrived home on flight UA2 (Singapore to San Francisco). For the last 3 months, I had been traveling solo in Asia. After being laid off from my last company, a solo trip was just what the doctor ordered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I was away, one of my roommates, Richard (not his real name), quit his job and moved into full-time job search mode. Richard is also a software engineer and failed 3 Technical Phone Screens and 5 onsites before his first offer. That’s 8 “No’s” before the first “Yes”. After accumulating those scars, he was a battle-tested vet. Richard became my sherpa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s the advice he gave me:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get ready for lots of BFS/DFS problems. Some good ones: &lt;a href=&quot;https://leetcode.com/problems/number-of-islands&quot;&gt;https://leetcode.com/problems/number-of-islands&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://leetcode.com/problems/max-area-of-island&quot;&gt;https://leetcode.com/problems/max-area-of-island&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://leetcode.com/problems/minesweeper&quot;&gt;https://leetcode.com/problems/minesweeper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;For some reason, the LRU cache problem comes up a lot. Think about it too: &lt;a href=&quot;https://leetcode.com/problems/lru-cache&quot;&gt;https://leetcode.com/problems/lru-cache&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get used to rejection.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do a few problems from each chapter of “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crackingthecodinginterview.com/&quot;&gt;Cracking the Coding Interview&lt;/a&gt;”, no need to do all of them (although that won’t hurt).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;a href=&quot;https://triplebyte.com&quot;&gt;Triplebyte&lt;/a&gt;. But definitely prepare before you take the TripleByte quiz. (Triplebyte is how Richard found his first job a couple years back)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The knowledge that Richard had gone through his own struggles before landing at Google was comforting. With that, I began the first steps of the job search: Identifying Opportunities, Networking and Resume Polishing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;identifying-opportunities&quot;&gt;Identifying Opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started with a list of companies that interested me. These were companies that I was impressed by from a distance, either through blog posts (often authored by the company themselves), podcasts, or from people in my network. AngelList puts out curated lists of companies they call “&lt;a href=&quot;https://angel.co/job-collections&quot;&gt;job collections&lt;/a&gt;” which I drew upon for inspiration. I referenced the &lt;a href=&quot;https://breakoutlist.com/&quot;&gt;Breakout List&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.wealthfront.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/2018_Career-Launching_List-10.pdf&quot;&gt;Wealthfront’s List of Career Launching companies&lt;/a&gt;, although those sources are sparse on useful information. Next, I glanced at the list of portfolio companies at some well known VCs. From these mostly nebulous sources, I made three lists: Low-Mid Interest, Mid-High Interest and Crypto companies. Finally, I used Glassdoor reviews to sanity check if any of the companies on my list had red flags.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t discover &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.keyvalues.com/&quot;&gt;Key Values&lt;/a&gt; until week 4 of my process, but I wish I found it earlier. Key Values is a website that helps engineers find teams that share their cultural values. The profiles on Key Values are the closest thing to a company’s culture resume anywhere on the internet. Two reasons why I wish I knew about Key Values in week 1:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;It would have pushed me to think about culture even more. Up until this point, I had been evaluating companies based on three things: chance of financial success, mission alignment (did I care about the product?), and perceived operational efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I would have found more companies (By week 4, I was mostly executing off of the lists I formed in weeks 1 and 2)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;More on Key Values in the Appendix! But for now, just make sure to leverage Key Values early.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;networking&quot;&gt;Networking&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I was traveling, I received an email from a recruiter at Greylock who connects engineers with Greylock’s portfolio companies. I couldn’t meet then, but when I returned, I bumped the thread and set up a time to chat. This relationship would ultimately prove quite fruitful and I encourage you to establish an open communication channel with recruiters at VCs. They’re wonderful people – and everybody loves a good matchmaker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I started reaching out to friends who worked at companies that were on my lists. This was admittedly not a very expansive network, and I only knew people who worked at 3 companies on my initial list: Affirm, PagerDuty and Uber. I asked if they would feel comfortable referring me and all three were happy to help.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I reached out to friends and asked if they could introduce me to second degree connections. Often, I found that my friends were excited to make introductions if they could. Richard connected me to one of his good friends who worked at BitGo. Another one of my friends couldn’t introduce me to anyone, but he dogmatically encouraged me to apply to his company: Coffee Meets Bagel (CMB). While I didn’t get past the recruiter screen at CMB, his referral proved to be highly useful for our next topic: Resume polishing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;resumes&quot;&gt;Resumes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep resumes short. I have been part of the resume filtration process before and believe long resumes are a disservice to those who must read them. Respect other people’s time!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1wHtmSZ4JgV3WiZtjv5uyxc0z6qOtIVVM/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;the resume I used for my job search here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In one evening, I summed up my 3 years of professional experience into 4 or 5 bullet points. On another evening, I wrote descriptions for recent hackathon projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I sent my resume out for comments. Unsurprisingly, those who gave me the best comments were friends referring me to their own companies. My friend at CMB helped me eliminate vague bullet points. My friend at Uber gave me tactical advice: “Don’t list a technology on your resume unless you’re willing to be grilled on it”. So true. Don’t give your interviewer a chance to put you on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next, I copied the updates from my resume into LinkedIn. And I marked that I was no longer at my previous job (it had been recommended to me to initially show that I was still at my previous company following the layoff, but it was time to rip off that band-aid).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My mindset for updating my resume was MVP. Honestly, resumes only serve two purposes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get you noticed by recruiters for the job you want&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A conversation starter for every interview&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Does your resume perform those two jobs? Great. Is it as simple as possible? Great. Now ship it. There are more important things to focus on. If you want any resume help, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pliao39&quot;&gt;connect with me&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And finally, I got a friend to take a new photo of me (via my iPhone). I’ve started using it everywhere, on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/pliao39&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pliao39&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and on this website. (PS If anyone out there knows someone who shoots great headshots, hit me up, I’m on the market for a new one)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;fortune-favors&quot;&gt;Fortune Favors&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;…the unprepared? On January 30, I had been back for 6 jetlagged days. On that day, I was scouring the net for the answer this question: If I failed the Triplebyte quiz, could I try again? (The answer appears to be&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/6y4ekx/can_i_retake_the_triplebyte_quiz/?st=jgbdyg8r&amp;amp;sh=d5a5d321&quot;&gt; yes, but after 4 months&lt;/a&gt;). But suddenly, I felt a compulsion to ignore Richard’s advice and jump into the quiz – preparation be damned. My heart rate rose. I gazed at the start button. &lt;em&gt;Click&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first 3 or so questions surprised me – I couldn’t answer them! Had to select “I don’t know”. I felt twinges of panic. And regret. Should have prepared! How is this quiz so hard! But the first punch in the face turned out to be the worst. I answered one question with confidence and then another. Each one calming my nerves. Eventually, I got on a roll.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later (I don’t remember when), I got an Intercom message on Triplebyte’s site: “Congrats on doing very well on the quiz! The next step is a technical interview with us.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wow, okay. Hurdle cleared.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&quot;weeks-3-6-the-grind&quot;&gt;Weeks 3-6: The Grind&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;pep-talk&quot;&gt;Pep Talk&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The job search process can completely shake your self confidence. You know what you’re capable of. You know what you’ve done in the past. In fact, no one in the world knows your ability better than you do (although &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2018/03/you-dont-know-yourself-as-well-as-you-think-you-do/554612/&quot;&gt;collectively, your co-workers probably do&lt;/a&gt;, but that’s collectively). Yet, here you are, being evaluated and tested. All of your past accomplishments are invalidated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This sucks. Doing something you haven’t done in a long time (interviewing) and getting judged on your ability to do that thing can mess with your head.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might start avoiding companies that you suspect will reject you (this is what I was subconsciously doing at first). You might lose motivation, stop studying and cease applying altogether. You might be led to feel incompetent, unintelligent and unemployable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of my friends texted me: “How do you stay positive?”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Me: “I don’t haha”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to this feeling, I started to question the usefulness of interviews and their ability to detect my value. For a while, I stopped preparing for interviews and pursued other interests (for me, I studied other things: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptozombies.io/&quot;&gt;CryptoZombies&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://hpbn.co/&quot;&gt;High Performance Browser Networking&lt;/a&gt;, both of which are great resources, btw. Of course, I procrastinated with the usual suspects as well: watching sports, reading random articles on the internet).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many smart people have abandoned the idea of getting a traditional job and have sidestepped the interview process altogether by starting their own companies. In one of his recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://steveblank.com/2018/04/11/why-entrepreneurs-start-companies-rather-than-join-them/&quot;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt;, Steve Blank analyzes the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2596846&quot;&gt;Asymmetric Information and Entrepreneurship&lt;/a&gt; and summarizes one of its conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“People choose to be entrepreneurs when they feel that they are more capable than what employers can tell from their resume or an interview. So, entrepreneurs start ventures because they can’t signal their worth to potential employers.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began to feel that way. And on top of that, I met up with a few friends who had struck out on their own and started businesses: &lt;a href=&quot;http://vietcetera.com/&quot;&gt;Vietcetera&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://originofmind.clothing/&quot;&gt;Origin of Mind&lt;/a&gt;. With Vietcetera, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/haontran&quot;&gt;Hao&lt;/a&gt; is spotlighting an emerging Vietnam, with a focus on culture and business. The vibe is a bit like The New Yorker, but more entrepreneurial and a whole lot more Vietnamese. With Origin of Mind, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/alalafox&quot;&gt;Alex&lt;/a&gt; is using clothing to spark conversation on some of the country’s most important social issues. She launched in Oakland with the “On Education” collection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began to wonder if I should follow in their steps and do something of my own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But at the end of the day, I focused on my long game. Yes, my present situation sucks. Yes, this process is uncomfortable. Yes, there might be very intelligent ways to forgo it entirely. But what are my long term goals? What kind of opportunities do I want to be looking at in 10 years time?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My long term goals are nebulous. I know it has something to do with community building, entrepreneurship and technology. Only, the shape hasn’t crystallized yet. And thus, I decided to invest in education. I determined that I would be able to learn the most by working with people who possessed managerial, technical and entrepreneurial skills that I lacked. (And hustling on the side – but, that’s always).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But perhaps most significantly, I simply felt this had to be done. The job hunt was something I had been fearful of and as I learned in a meditation class: “What we need to do is often what we fear the most” (Tim Ferris also has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/314018-what-we-fear-doing-most-is-usually-what-we-most&quot;&gt;a variation&lt;/a&gt; of this saying). I can be extremely stubborn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are no right answers. Everyone is at a different place and has a different destination in mind. But if your conclusion, like mine, is to continue with your job search, read on, I’ll drop a few tips on how to get through the grind of getting to onsite interviews.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-a-scheduling-tool&quot;&gt;Use a Scheduling Tool&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may waste a lot of time scheduling. Solve the nightmare of double bookings (when two companies book the same time), excessive back and forths, and large blocks of wasted time with a tool like &lt;a href=&quot;https://calendly.com&quot;&gt;Calendly&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://youcanbook.me&quot;&gt;You Can Book Me&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve seen people use &lt;a href=&quot;https://mixmax.com&quot;&gt;Mixmax&lt;/a&gt;, which directly allows people to book a time within an email. They’re all great tools, and any of them will do. If you find yourself thinking too much about scheduling, use a scheduling tool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;connect-with-decision-makers&quot;&gt;Connect with Decision Makers&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you can, connect with decision makers. If the CTO reaches out, take the call 100% of the time. If you’re going to reach out to a company, ask for introductions to decision makers. I find that conversations with decision makers are much more invigorating. Instead of sizing you up, wondering if you will pass their technical challenges, decision makers are thinking about fit. They spend the phone call trying to probe if you’ll be excellent on their team. This will be a great way to break up the monotony of talking to recruiters. (And anecdotally, converts much better too!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact, I believe there is a way to conduct a job search that revolves entirely around connecting with decision makers – instead of a numbers game, it’s all about developing mutual trust with a small number of people who are looking to stack their teams with absurdly strong talent. But, that’s an entirely different approach from the one I conducted and a discussion for a different time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-screens&quot;&gt;My Screens&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For me, weeks 3 – 6 were dominated by phone screens and take homes. This section of my job search was a grind. I spent a large percentage of my time waiting for phone calls. I tried to utilize that time to study, but was very inefficient. Nonetheless, I did the bulk of my studying during these weeks. On some days I did one or two Leetcode problems (it’s okay if you fail lots of questions and need to look at the answer after 25 minutes. I did this a lot. Just try to find a similar question and use what you learned). On other days, I worked on problems from Cracking the Coding Interview. On other days, I read sections from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Algorithms-Eastern-Economy-Thomas/dp/8120340078/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1524621154&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=clrs+algorithms&quot;&gt;CLRS Algorithms book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For some reason, interviewers love to ask questions that involve BFS/DFS (as Richard foretold), tree traversals, and 2 pointer problems. The last category is nebulous, but is a very useful tool in your toolbox. It involves using two (or more) pointers in crafty ways (maybe you have one pointer start at the beginning of a sorted array and another at the end, maybe you have two sorted lists and use a pointer for each…). If you have identified a brute force solution that requires O(n^2) comparisons, this is often a fruitful question: “Can I do better if I use two pointers to get everything done in O(n) time?”. This was a surprisingly helpful tactic for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another note – I loved take homes. As a practicing software engineer, I found that take home assignments gave me a chance to send a true signal about my abilities. They weren’t algorithm heavy, but tested my ability to write non trivial, production-level code. Affirm provided the option of either a take home or a technical phone screen. I gladly took the take home – not only did I get a chance to write code that simulated real work, I learned some useful domain knowledge that helped me understand their business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this grind, I also experienced rejection. At the recruiter screen, I was rejected by Crew and CMB. At the technical phone screen, I was rejected by Pinterest and Blend. Blend in particular hurt, I had gotten excited about the idea that Blend would be a good fit. But as Richard advised me at the very beginning, get used to rejection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Believe it or not, rejection is a good thing. It means you have pushed yourself to your current boundaries. Furthermore, it toughens you for future encounters, improving your ability to stay calm under pressure. Getting rejected by Pinterest and Blend also made me a little better at technical questions (I implemented improved solutions to the problems immediately after the screens).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But don’t worry, the rejections didn’t stop there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&quot;weeks-7-10-onsites-and-offers&quot;&gt;Weeks 7-10: Onsites and Offers&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;week-7&quot;&gt;Week 7&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of my phone screens and take homes started to convert and suddenly, it was onsite season. My first two onsites were with Sonder and Google. I failed both. Interestingly, they were polar opposites. Sonder asked 0 algorithm questions, focusing entirely on system design and object oriented programming. Googled asked 5 algorithm/cleverness questions. I was completely stumped by one of the questions and spent most of the 45 minute session trying to keep a level head. I walked out of the interview embarrassed. I refer to this interview as The Disaster. (The other 4 were ok).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I went home to Texas for 5 days (Thursday through Monday) after my Google interview. Taking a planned vacation in the middle of onsite season was incredibly important. It gave me a chance to integrate the lessons of failure, as well as a chance to relax and get ready for the next wave of onsites. I highly recommend a period of rest if you can make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;week-8&quot;&gt;Week 8&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following week, I had onsites with Intercom, b8ta and Solv. With the scars from my recent failures, I walked into those onsites with confidence. At both b8ta and Solv, one of my interviews centered around CSS, which I bombed. But unlike The Disaster at Google, I did not panic, not even a little. I stayed calm, openly told my interviewers that CSS was the weakest of my full stack skills and we proceeded to have a surprisingly not-awkward session of me DuckDuckGo-ing basic CSS. I was rejected by b8ta and Solv. In their email to me, Solv told me this: “While everyone appreciated your personality, communication and problem solving, tech thinking, we hit a road block on the core front end skills..” Haha, fair enough!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Intercom called me to let me know they were extending an offer! Everything changes when you get your first offer. Your belief in yourself is finally re-validated. Just as importantly, other companies will pick up the pace and get with your timeline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;week-9&quot;&gt;Week 9&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next week, I had onsites with Earnin, Affirm and Uber. At this point, the onsites felt routine. Once in a while, I felt that my interviewers were really testing me, pushing the envelope to see how I would react. I clearly communicated what I completely didn’t know and stretched to hit the questions I thought I could get.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earnin and Uber extended offers. Affirm would not get back to me until the following week with a soft rejection: the team I had interviewed with would not be moving forward, but they could reconsider me for a different team. I accepted the rejection and declined to move forward with the other team.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an aside, the length of time a company takes to get back to you after the onsite is incredibly revealing. If it’s in 1 or 2 days, the result was either a clear yes or clear no. This is ideal. If it’s longer than 3 days, then the result was either contentious or the company doesn’t operate efficiently. Neither of those are good things. You want to go to a team that wants you, not a team that is settling for you. And you definitely don’t want to go to team that doesn’t respect candidates’ time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;week-10&quot;&gt;Week 10&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my final week, I managed to squeeze in one last company into the mix. I had alluded to BitGo earlier in my blog post, but what I did not share was that I had actually designed my entire interview process with them in mind. I shared this with Richard one day. I had been reading High Performance Browser Networking and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Belshe&quot;&gt;Mike Belshe&lt;/a&gt;, the CEO of BitGo, kept popping up in the book. While at Google, he had masterminded the SPDY specification which laid the foundation for HTTP 2.0. I had been reading some Bitcoin blogs and &lt;a href=&quot;https://lopp.net/&quot;&gt;Jameson Lopp&lt;/a&gt;, a BitGo engineer, kept popping up. (Jameson has since left, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lopp/status/969567040401965056&quot;&gt;but on great terms&lt;/a&gt;). I wanted to be in the Crypto space and BitGo was the one company I really had strong interest in joining.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard had a good friend at BitGo who referred me. The company sent me a HackerRank coding challenge. I did it (although one of my solutions didn’t pass all tests). I didn’t hear back for a while, assuming that I had been screened out. Then, out of the blue, I got a message from BitGo in week 9 – they wanted to set up a technical phone screen. We squeezed in the phone screen on Friday of week 9 and my onsite was on Monday of week 10.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I thought the BitGo onsite was solid, despite it being my 7th onsite in 13 days. My solutions weren’t as sharp as they could have been, but they weren’t bad. In my tired state, I tried to communicate my strong interest in BitGo. They asked for references and I waited for them to check in with some of my former coworkers. 4 days later, I got a call from BitGo letting me know that they would not be matching my other offers and would not extend one of their own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard this time and time again. The more you want to work at a company, the more desperate you come off, and the less desirable of a candidate you become. This is by no means a deal breaker for companies, but you should avoid doing what I did. Don’t design your process around one company. The chances are, they won’t reciprocate and might even read your enthusiasm as uncomfortable desperation. Just keep an open mind, your best opportunity might not even be one you were hoping to get. It’s sort of like Frank Ocean said/sang: “The best song wasn’t the single”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a related note, an hour after I heard back from BitGo, I spoke with a Director of Engineering at Uber (my manager’s manager). I was sold. On March 30, 2018 at 2PM I contacted Intercom, Earnin and Uber and communicated my decision. It had been 65 days since I touched down in SFO. The job search had finally ended. I was Uber bound.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&quot;lessons&quot;&gt;Lessons&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had a few takeaways from my job search.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Act&lt;/strong&gt; before you feel ready&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do you feel 40% ready? Great! You’re more than ready to get out there&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Always be &lt;strong&gt;networking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Even when you’re job searching, form new connections! But never ask new connections for help. Always have the mentality of being a valuable addition to people’s network.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Leverage your close connections for introductions to companies&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ask your close connections for referrals (there’s usually a referral bonus anyways)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Respect other people’s &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt; (but especially, your own!)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Concise resumes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@Torbahax/how-to-write-emails-like-a-ceo-d6a2906611e0&quot;&gt;Concise emails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use a scheduler (like Calendly, You Can Book Me, Mixmax or some competitor)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Study in &lt;strong&gt;manageable&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;bits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Spend 25 minutes on a problem and if you’re going nowhere, peek at the solution&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Don’t try to cram multiple topics in a day. For example, I took one evening to understand min/max heaps. Nothing more. It was one of my most productive study sessions.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Don’t get tunnel vision. Have a mentality of &lt;strong&gt;abundance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;“The best song wasn’t the single”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tons of excellent companies out there. If you get rejected from one that you particularly like, don’t sweat it. There will be more. Always.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Embrace &lt;strong&gt;failure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Failure sucks! But each failure is an asset. It’s like fertilizer for growth. So long as you are putting in effort, failure will accelerate your progress like nothing else. Getting used to it will give you an edge&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Being laid off doesn’t matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The pain from being laid off will heal with time and as you talk more openly about it.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;While it might be a sore topic for you, most people will not prod. They might be curious as to what happened, but a simple tautology or circular definition is almost always enough to appease their curiosity: “The company didn’t meet its financial aspirations and elected to downsize. I was affected”&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Let me know if you want to talk more about it&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s going to suck! Putting yourself out there for assessment and evaluation is a vulnerable experience. It’s not pleasant. And if you’re like me, you probably won’t enjoy it. But deep down, you’ll know whether or not this process is something you must do. For me, I felt that I had to do this. I felt compelled to push through.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And if you ever need someone to rely on, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pliao39&quot;&gt;come find me&lt;/a&gt;. So long as I’m not inundated with projects, I will make time for you. I believe we all need a strong support network in difficult times and I’d be thrilled to become a node in your network!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h1 id=&quot;appendix-recommended-companies&quot;&gt;Appendix: Recommended Companies&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my job search, I applied to 18 companies and talked with 13. There lots of great things to say about each, but I want to highlight a few that I’m extra excited about. These are companies that I would strongly recommend to friends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;intercom&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.intercom.com/careers&quot;&gt;Intercom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m really excited about Intercom both as a business and as a place to work. Intercom’s engineering values of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.intercom.com/run-less-software&quot;&gt;Run less software&lt;/a&gt;” and “&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.intercom.com/shipping-is-your-companys-heartbeat/&quot;&gt;Shipping is your company’s heartbeat&lt;/a&gt;” really resonated with me. As someone who has been heavily influenced by the book &lt;em&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/em&gt;, Intercom’s engineering culture felt incredibly efficient. Jamming with the team on a hackathon-like project was energizing and fun. The team is entrepreneurial and pragmatic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For anyone who loves building excellent product, I would strongly advise Intercom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;solv&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.solvhealth.com/careers&quot;&gt;Solv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My phone call with Daniele (CTO and co-founder at Solv) was one of the highlights of my job search. We talked about life, healthcare, Bill Gurley, prioritization and my work style. I left the call feeling incredibly excited. The onsite with Solv was great, but unfortunately, my CSS deficiencies were a deal breaker.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in healthcare, like working with smart and passionate people, then you have to check out Solv. (You should also read the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Catastrophic-Care-Everything-Think-Health/dp/034580273X&quot;&gt;Catastrophic Care&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;earnin&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.earnin.com/Careers&quot;&gt;Earnin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I went onsite at Earnin, I was impressed with their engineering culture. Interviews felt collaborative, the assessments were diverse (system design, algorithm, short answer, object oriented design), and the people were down to earth. The more junior engineers talked about how they felt supported by the senior engineers, and the more senior engineers mentioned how they liked mentoring. This all happened without any top down directives with regards to mentoring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for a strong group of engineers who have built a great organic culture, I believe you’ll find it at Earnin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;triplebyte&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://triplebyte.com&quot;&gt;Triplebyte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ok, so I didn’t interview for a position at Triplebyte, but I worked with them. Of all my 44 technical assessments, the Triplebyte interview was the most fun and engaging. My talent manager was enthusiastic and genuinely wanted to place me at a great company. The only thing about Triplebyte that is a bit hit or miss is their matching process (a bit opaque and not always successful). Still, it is absolutely worth your time to work with Triplebyte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an aside, I would have paid just to take their assessment and “get Triplebyte certified”. That would be a nice feature for those with non-traditional backgrounds to signal that they’ve been vetted by at least one 3rd party.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Try out their &lt;a href=&quot;https://quiz.triplebyte.com/&quot;&gt;practice quiz&lt;/a&gt; – it’s actually kind of hard (I learned a couple things even from this practice quiz!). Read their &lt;a href=&quot;https://triplebyte.com/blog&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. It’s excellent. And if you’re curious about salaries, check out their &lt;a href=&quot;https://triplebyte.com/software-engineer-salary&quot;&gt;aggregated salary visualizations&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t talk about salary in this post, but I will comment that those graphs were in line with my offers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id=&quot;appendix-critical-resources&quot;&gt;Appendix: Critical Resources&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-values&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.keyvalues.com/&quot;&gt;Key Values&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I mentioned it earlier, but I want to reiterate – Key Values is the closest thing to a company’s culture resume anywhere on the internet. Companies get to talk about what they think is important and highlight their cultural strengths.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, browsing Key Values will reaffirm your beliefs in your own cultural values. This is incredibly important to be thinking about throughout your job search. While Key Values may not have the company profile that you’re looking for, it will categorically make your job search better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do yourself a favor and use Key Values from the start. And check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.keyvalues.com/culture-queries&quot;&gt;culture queries&lt;/a&gt;, it will get your mind thinking about the important things.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;angellist&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://angel.co/&quot;&gt;AngelList&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;AngelList is a fantastic resource to get in contact with startups. I know so many people who have gotten jobs through AngelList, and in fact, it was how I got my first job. One thing to be aware of is that on AngelList, a company can see the number of companies a candidate has indicated interest in. Don’t be the person who is “interested” in 723 companies. Be selective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;glassdoor&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glassdoor.com/Reviews/index.htm&quot;&gt;Glassdoor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let it be known that I believe Glassdoor is the Yelp of company culture reviews. It’s heavily influenced by disgruntled employees and coordinated manipulation (I stumbled upon a well known company with over 40 reviews, the majority of which were generic 5 star reviews published within a 7 day span). The product is occasionally unusable (because they constantly direct you to use their job search product). But it has some great authentic reviews. And it’s not going anywhere because of its strong network effects. Ultimately, those brief moments of authenticity are worth the noise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I love and hate Glassdoor.&lt;/p&gt;</content></item></channel></rss>